Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who continues
to fight against fate.
Simon learns the sad secret
behind Nia's birth.
Confronted with the devious trap
set by Guame of the Four Generals,
...the Core Drill on Simon's chest
gives off a blinding light,
...and Gurren Lagann
stands reborn.
The man has gotten back
on his feet.
So, even the great Guame, the Immovable,
with his long, distinguished service,
...was given the runaround
by these humans. Pathetic.
I don't have to take that from someone
who never leaves the comfort of the Capital.
The Spiral King has but to give the word,
and his servant, Cytomander, will go forth.
And Adiane?
She has yet to return.
That woman doesn't know
when to give up.
And Dai-Gunzan?
Proceeding on a direct course
here to Teppelin.
Luck seems to have turned
in Adiane's favor.
What do you mean?
They're heading right for the sea.
Episode 12:
Yoko, Will You Do Me a Favor?
It's a big water puddle!
Are you guys stupid?
This here is called "the sea!"
The sea?
It's a place where water from rain and rivers
and stuff gathers from around the world.
I'm amazed you know all that.
I've heard stories about it before,
but this is my first time seeing it.
The sea, huh?
Listen up!
Water in the sea is salty!
Salty sea water,
salty pee water!
- Yeah, so what?
- It's just something to go around.
- Go around!
- Around! Go around!
What's with those ridiculous outfits?
If you've come to the sea,
you've got to go swimming!
In addition to swimming, we can
also confirm if the water is salty.
Yeah! Get into your swimsuits
and let's all go swimming!
- All go swimming...
- In our swimsuits...
And that means--
You clowns!
What are you thinking, you perverts?
Making our way to the Capital is our
top priority right now, remember?
We don't have time to goof off!
That's not entirely true.
Take a look. This is Teppelin Palace
at the heart of the Capital.
Oh, I see. To get to Teppelin, we have
no choice but to cross this sea.
Right. But Dai-Gurren is land-based,
so it can't go into the water.
Then how do we do it?
I thought this might happen!
So for just such an occasion,
I whipped up a set of aquatic gear!
It won't be ready for
a while yet, though.
That means--!
That you have plenty
of time to goof off.
Awesome!
Yahoo!
C'mon, guys!
Let's suit up, too!
You're not going?
Swimming around
under the sun, huh?
I guess that might be fun.
Salty!
Yes, very salty.
When tears stream down women's faces,
this is where they end up!
Here they come!
What the hell? What's with that thing
wrapped around her waist?
Yeah, what's up with that?
She's showing LESS skin than usual!
Take away the skin, and what's she
got left? Just a big-ass rifle.
I know all that! Besides, don't you think it's
better to leave a little to the imagination?
Are you stupid?! Everybody knows
the more skin you show, the better!
Screw you! I'll fill you
full of lead!
Excuse me...
I've never worn an outfit like this before.
Do you think this is all right?
Truly, it is better to
conceal than reveal.
- Jealous?
- Hardly!
When you're at the beach...
...it's time for beach volleyball!
Beach volleyball?
What's that?
It's a game where you smash this ball as
hard as you can into your opponents' area.
As hard as I can?
Perfect! When it comes to physical
contests, I'm obviously the--
Did I do that right?
Nia, that was awesome!
I was given basic instruction
in sports at the palace.
It was considered part of a
well-rounded lady's education.
S-She's a lot more formidable
than she looks...
C'mon, everybody! Let's do the
watermelon splitting game next!
Why, you! Why, you!
Goodness, I did it!
Nia, you're awesome!
All right, everyone!
Your attention, please!
I will now explain how my
aquatic equipment works.
First of all...
Good work.
She's completely blended in.
She's a sweet girl, don't you think?
Yeah, I can see that...
You're mad that she's stolen
the boys away from you?
- No, of course not.
- I'll bet.
After you swim, you gotta
have a barbecue!
Here!
Go on, Yoko!
Eat up!
S-Sure.
Yoko dropped her crab!
Nia slaved away to make that!
Gotcha!
Just kidding!
I'll make you another, Yoko.
I'm sorry.
I don't want any!
Yoko?
- What's HER problem?
- She can't take a joke!
Yeah, it joke!
- Learn to read the room, lady!
- Yeah, read room!
It's (more or less) all done!
Will this really work?
It's all good!
(More or less...)
So, what's different?
The bridge doesn't look
any different.
All that's left is a few last
fine adjustments.
- Hey, that's my--
- Launch!
Dumbass! Give us
a little warning first!
- Well?
- Incredible!
- In that case, make it official!
- Right!
Set course for Teppelin!
Aye aye!
That one looks funny!
It's weird!
Gimmy, what's that?
Oh, wow! Bubbles are coming
out of their butts!
Ship detected on the underwater radar!
Closing in at high speed!
It's almost directly beneath us...
This reading is a Gunmen!
Hard right rudder!
Too late!
What was that?!
Submarine Fortress Gunmen:
Dai-Gunkai
Torpedo Gunmen 1, 2, and 3,
direct hits!
I guess this is what they mean
by moths flying to the flame.
Right.
I'll go out in Sayrune.
You take command
of Dai-Gunkai.
Yes, ma'am!
All right, you stinking humans! I'm gonna
make you regret that you shamed me!
I'll send you straight
to the bottom!
Gurren Lagann
Open fire!
Yeah! Direct hits on all shots!
No, no hits at all.
Enemy ship descending!
Switch over to depth charges!
- Coming right up!
- You got it!
Detonations above
the port bow!
Lousy humans... That's pathetic.
You'll have to try harder than that!
Tubes 1 through 6, fire!
I'm going out!
Cover me!
Hey, wait a minute!
What's going on?!
The Gunmen haven't been
waterproofed yet!
You should've said
something earlier!
Torpedo Gunmen to
the left of the ship!
It's no use!
It's too fast!
It's way faster than
those torpedoes earlier!
It's on a direct course!
Take immediate evasive action!
Major damage to No. 3 Bridge!
Gimmy and Darry are safe!
Hurry, close emergency bulkheads!
The torpedo Gunmen is coming around
again for another pass! It's fast!
From its shape, it's not a torpedo...
It's a Four Generals custom Gunmen!
If this keeps up, we're history!
I guess our only option is to
take a chance with our Special.
Gurren Lagann's special regenerative ability
should make it watertight, too!
Underwater combat
should be possible, too!
- We haven't exactly confirmed that...
- We'll find out soon enough in the water!
We're counting on you boys!
- How are we?
- Leakage points, zero!
We're good to go!
I knew it could--
Is this it?!
You bastard!
Stinking human, challenging me
to battle in the water...
...was the last mistake
you'll ever make!
General Adiane has
the upper hand!
We are now making
for Dai-Gunzan.
Gurren Lagann, I had hoped
to dispatch you personally.
But I will offer you
to General Adiane!
Vent all of my anger
on them, ma'am!
Dai-Gunkai!
Arm Cutters!
Foot flippers destroyed!
Propulsion is down!
They've grabbed us!
What? What are they up to?
Down trim full!
Dive, full power!
We're being pulled under!
Simon!
Dai-Gurren's in trouble!
Guys!
Crap!
Oh, so you think you can afford to divide
your attention while facing me, do you?
Don't insult me!
It's no use!
She's moving too quickly!
We're taking on water!
So much for
the tough guy act.
- We're gonna drown!
- We're taking on water!
What do we do?!
Everyone.
Please remain calm.
Nia?
Everything will be all right. I know that
Simon will come up with something.
How do you know that?
Just because, no real reason.
Just because?
It's not based on anything in particular.
I just know Simon will find a way.
That's what I think.
This is bad! Dai-Gurren is way
beyond its maximum depth!
- It's all over! We're gonna die!
- That's cold! I can't swim!
Please, do something!
What will you do? You and your friends
will be crushed flat by the water pressure!
We don't have time...
...to fool around down here...
What?!
...with you and your friends!
What the--?
You're not getting away!
He's fast!
Bloody Clasper!
Impossible! Nothing is faster
than me in the water!
Oh, I get it!
It's drilling the water!
I guess soil isn't the only thing
your drill can move through, Simon!
Gurren Lagann closing in fast!
Fire, fire!
Oo!
Impossible!
This isn't over yet!
Desperate times call for
desperate measures.
I'm going to make use of the
princess here a little longer!
Put Nia down!
Careful, now. I dare you
to take one step.
I'll crush her into goo!
- I'll shoot him.
- Wait a minute, Viral.
I have a hostage and all, so I'll
make them kill each other.
All right, humans! Train your
main guns on Gurren Lagann!
Listen up. On my signal,
blow Gurren Lagann to pieces.
Or else!
Yoko!
And what have we here?
That toy won't work on my Sayrune.
Or are you going to kill the princess
and remove her as a bargaining chip?
Yoko!
Hey, Yoko!
Let's not be hasty here!
Don't do it, Yoko!
Be quiet.
Yoko!
Interesting...
What will you shoot next?
An arm? A leg?
If you make her suffer too badly,
I might start to feel sorry for her!
What?!
My shoulder!
Gramps? What are you
doing here?
Careful! Fire at that angle,
and you'll kill us both.
Are humans that stupid?
I hate to break it to you,
but yeah. We are.
To hell with it!
Open fire!
General Adiane!
No you don't!
Thymilph... I'm sorry.
Let's ride this wave
straight to shore!
She is dead?
Damn you, Gurren Lagann!
Damn! DAMN!
Yoko, could you
do something for me?
Sure, what?
I'd like you to
tidy up my hair.
Oops. This stuff isn't exactly
my strong suit.
Don't come complaining
to me afterwards.
It will be fine.
Another "just because"?
Yes!
Why did you close your eyes
back there?
You are a master
with a rifle.
It was because
I had faith in you.
Boy, what a moron...
No, no!
I meant myself.
Okay, all done!
There's something refreshing
about it!
Yeah, I think so, too.
What do you think?
It's fine, I guess.
You really think so?
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
What will it take to get a smile out of
that boy who is looking up into the sky?
I'll cook dinner
and wait for him.
Eat Up, Everyone
Next time on Gurren Lagann,
"Eat Up, Everyone".