Gurren Lagann
Sugita kisetsu wo nageku hima ha nai
I don't have the time to lament the seasons that have passed
Nido to mayotte shimawanu you ni
So that I won't ever waver again
Kazoekirenai hon no sasayaka na
With countless, tiny little
Sonna koukai kakaeta mama
Regrets carried in my arms
Sono senaka dake oikakete koko made kitanda
I've come this far, having chased only after your back
Sagashite ita boku dake ni dekiru koto
It's something only I, who sought you, can do
Ano hi kureta kotoba ga ima demo
Those words you gave me that day, even now,
Kono mune ni tashika ni todoite iru kara
Definitely reach my heart
Kinou yori mo kyou ha bu ha boku no
I've realized my reason for having been born
Umarete kita wake ni kidzuite yuku
Today more than I did yesterday
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who continues
to look for his own path,
...even while being
betrayed by fate.
It has been seven years
since Teppelin's fall.
Human civilization has evolved
at an astonishing rate.
As Lordgenome predicted, the instant
that the one millionth human was born,
...an unknown destructive
weapon suddenly appeared.
The declaration of war against humanity
came from an unexpected person.
Attention, humans of Earth.
We, the Anti-Spiral races,
have determined that humanity...
...has achieved Spiral Power
danger level two.
We hereby activate the
Humanity Annihilation System.
Is that Nia?
Episode 18:
Tell Me The Secrets of This World
I say again...
The Humanity Annihilation System
has been activated.
What the hell is our little
princess talking about?
Hurry, pinpoint the
transmission origin!
It's no use! It's using an encryption
I've never seen before!
Find a way!
Rossiu! Where's Nia?!
That's what I'd like to know!
She's not answering
her cell, either.
Is it really Nia that's saying
all that crazy stuff?!
It shut off...
Yeah, that's right! Trust your friendly
New Government Council!
How could something wipe out
the whole human race?
Huh? What's that? Reimburse you
for your burnt-out house?
You stupid bastard! Gurren Lagann
was fighting to protect the city!
What's going on?
It's chaos in here!
Where have you been, Dayakka?!
My apologies for calling you in,
Provisions Bureau Chief Dayakka.
That's okay, there's nothing
a new father can do right now.
What are all these
calls about?
The citizens are nervous about
that declaration of war.
Speaking to executives of the
New Government, core Team Gurren members,
...will go far in alleviating the
worries of the general public.
That is Chief Advisor Rossiu's
thinking on the matter.
I'm getting more gripes about
smashed houses than nervous citizens.
Everybody's real attached
to their new lifestyles.
- Listen, we tough!
- Quit bitching and let us do job!
Where is he?
Considering how to deal
with the situation.
Please leave all of that
to the Chief Advisor.
In other words, keep us old-timers
busy fielding the complaint calls.
Sounds like something that smartass
Rossiu would come up with.
It's a success. We've activated
the bio-computer.
Very well. Good work.
Now, everyone leave the room.
No one is allowed in
until I give authorization.
Very good, sir.
Now, then. This time, you will tell me.
Tell me all this world's secrets.
Wake up, Lordgenome.
Nia, are you here?!
Old Coco?
Have you seen Nia?
Well met. This is Nia.
I can't come to the phone right now.
When I said "I can't come to the phone"
just now, I CAN, I'm just not near mine.
And when I do come home, I prefer to use
the home phone than my cell phone.
Nia, please come home...
We finally found you,
Supreme Commander Simon!
Where do you think
you're going?
Out of my way, Gimmy!
Gurren Lagann has been
ordered back to base.
Besides, all combat has been
prohibited except by Grapearls.
You two were no match
for that thing!
We could have beaten it
by ourselves!
I'm searching for Nia!
This is an emergency! Stand aside!
I won't!
That's an order from the
supreme commander!
Gunmen dispatches fall under
Chief Advisor Rossiu's purview.
Not even the supreme commander
is allowed to ignore the rules.
You little--
The citizens are worried.
Gurren Lagann is no
ordinary Gunmen.
It's a symbol of the retaking of
the surface. A symbol of strength.
If people see it flying around, they might
worry that another big battle is coming.
That isn't something
you would do, Simon.
You sure can make a
persuasive case these days, Darry.
You win. Take Gurren back with you.
I'll go in Lagann.
I won't draw any attention
in this, right?
Commander Simon!
Gimmy, don't bother. Nobody can
stop him when he gets like that.
I swear... I wish he'd hurry up and
realize that the times have changed.
Maybe he doesn't WANT
them to change.
That's just thinking
of himself.
Well, well.
Hi, Leyte. Makken.
Simon?
So, I guess she didn't
come here, either.
I'm sorry we couldn't
be of more help.
That's okay, I just came on
the off chance she was here.
Simon, is everything okay?
They saw the broadcast on TV?
Nia's transmission.
Yeah.
Don't you worry!
No matter what happens,
we'll come up with something!
I don't know what this Humanity
Annihilation System thing is,
...but it's nothing
to worry about!
YOU'RE the one we're worried about.
He looks pretty depressed.
Shame he's not a mecha...
THAT, we could fix.
Nia, where are you?
Was that really you, Nia?
Nia!
Gurren Lagann
Where am I?
It has been seven years
since your death.
No, it wasn't YOU that died.
Lordgenome's knowledge and
memories are preserved as data.
We didn't go as far as reproducing
his personality, as well.
So, you would dig up a coffin and
drag out the corpse inside, eh?
You have an odd notion of fun.
We had to because you died
without telling us anything.
This time, you can't get away.
Now, tell me. What are Spiral Power
and the Anti-Spiral?
What do they have to do
with humanity?!
I've been looking everywhere!
Where have you been?
A place unknown to you.
Because I have learned.
L-Learned what?
That you and I are
completely incompatible.
The Spiral Nemesis will bring about
this universe's destruction.
We Anti-Spirals exist to
prevent that event.
D-Do you have a fever or something?
I understand you even less than usual.
Simon, the Core Drill you carry
is the very symbol of the Spiral Nemesis.
Its power, the power of the Spiral,
will destroy the universe.
Spiral Power is the
power of evolution.
Lifeforms that carry helical DNA,
galaxies that take spiral shape,
...they are amplified to infinite levels by
Spiral Power, which magnifies everything.
That is the underpinning
of this universe.
However, there arose a group
who feared that power.
That group is the Anti-Spiral races.
My original body, Lordgenome,
was once a Spiral Warrior...
...who fought the Anti-Spirals
in order to protect the galaxy.
Spiral Warrior?
Lazengann, the gigantic Teppelin,
even the Gunmen,
...were originally weapons
to fight the Anti-Spirals.
Wait, are you telling me
that Lagann was also a--
Exactly.
It was one of our most
powerful weapons.
It's a Core machine that is
activated by Spiral Power,
...one which can control whatever
mecha it combines with.
Who would have imagined that something
sealed away underground...
...would be discovered
by humans?
The hand of fate at work again.
But why?
If you were one of these Spiral Warriors,
why would you subjugate humanity?
Why force us underground?
We had lost.
The Spiral races were left with no choice
but to flee to their various homeworlds.
Earth is one such world.
After the Anti-Spirals
conquered the galaxy,
...they installed Spiral lifeform
annihilation devices...
...on any world where they detected
a Spiral lifeform signature.
When the above-ground lifeform
population exceeds a set limit,
...the device detects this,
then activates.
And that's why you drove
all humanity underground?
Think what you will of me, but I was trying
to preserve humanity as a species.
I did this by maintaining a bare
minimum population underground.
Why didn't you just come out
and tell us this?!
Why did you use force
to subjugate us?!
It wouldn't have worked.
Foolish lifeforms that are driven
by the Spiral instinct...
...blindly strive to
reach the heavens.
Words and reason alone are
insufficient to curb that drive.
The only thing that can...
is fear.
And even so, you rebelled
against me.
Even as a thousand years of
boredom weighed down on me,
...my will was strong enough to keep
the Spiral instinct bottled up.
And yet, your rebellion broke
my control and made my blood boil.
That is the terror of the
power of the Spiral.
Not even Lordgenome was able
to curb his instinct to fight.
That's crazy!
I won't accept that!
How could my and my Bro's fight
be the result of that?
It has been seven years
since you came to the surface.
How far has human civilization
advanced in a mere seven years?
Don't you find the speed
somewhat suspicious?
That is the potential
of Spiral lifeforms.
Having passed one million, human numbers
and civilization will advance explosively.
They will become a power that
will be a threat to our own.
And so, we will destroy you
before that can happen.
That's what the Humanity
Annihilation System is?
That mecha earlier?
No matter what comes, we have
Gurren Lagann! We'll beat them!
So please!
Snap out of it, Nia!
That isn't possible.
I am the messenger
of the Anti-Spirals.
A virtual lifeform that lay hidden
in helical genetic code,
...awakened when the Spiral Lifeform
Annihilation System was activated.
Please, Nia! I'm begging you!
Talk to me in words I can understand!
You never talked using words
like that, remember?
When you talked, it was rambling
and incomprehensible...
But it was warm,
and sweet, and...
Aw, I can't explain it, but
you know what I mean, right?
You didn't used to be like this!
What you see now is the real me.
Please, Lordgenome, you have to tell me!
What is the Humanity Annihilation System?!
What does it do to
annihilate humanity?
In three weeks' time, the moon will
leave its orbit and impact the Earth
And that will be
the end of it.
T-The moon?
Word of this can't get out
to the populace!
There'll be a huge panic
in seconds!
Lordgenome, this is top secret.
Discuss it with no one but me.
Rossiu! This is where
you've been?!
Don't enter
without permission!
Dumbass! Who cares
about that?!
The moon probe Gunmen
has been destroyed!
That ain't the half of it!
Check out the TV! The TV!
Why, that's--
It's been running live on TV
for a few minutes now.
She says the moon
is gonna fall.
Impossible...!
The little princess said it
plain as day!
It's hard to believe, but after what
happened to the moon probe, who knows?
Can we believe her, Rossiu?
We were driven underground
because of some war...
...between the Spiral
and Anti-Spiral races.
It's just like Lordgenome predicted.
The moon will become
Hell's messenger.
It's coming down
on top of us!
I was too late... My worst fears
are coming true.
What the hell is this?
I've seen this guy
before somewhere.
I'll explain later. Let's go
to the Defense Planning Room.
It's ironic that the human whose genes
contained the Anti-Spiral factor...
...would be born as
Lordgenome's daughter.
However, now that is has activated
and I have become an Anti-Spiral,
...I can never be made
human again.
Nia!
Nia, where are you going?!
Hey! What's going on?!
Mugann have appeared again.
- Mugann?
- That machine from earlier.
That type has been
codenamed Mugann.
Move it, Gimmy, Darry!
Commander!
Simon! If you attack it and aren't careful,
it'll cause another big explosion!
We need a plan!
I'll come up with something
while I'm fighting!
This is what I was
talking about!
Leeron, have you found an effective
means of attacking it?
This is data we got from
Gimmy and Darry.
It looks like a powerful energy field
is erected around the body.
That energy barrier
neutralizes our attacks.
Then we just need to hit it with
more power than it can handle!
We can't do that.
You saw that huge explosion, right?
A Mugann is essentially
comprised entirely of explosives.
When the energy field goes down
and it stops functioning,
...the entire body converts into
energy in a split second.
Its molecular structure
is that unstable?
That would make spatial transference
easier, don't you think?
What the hell are those two
talking about?
Don't look at me.
Out of the way!
Oops!
Don't say "oops,"
you bastard!
Don't you think you've
done enough damage?!
Normal attacks aren't effective... When it's
destroyed, it goes up in a huge blast...
What are we supposed
to do?!
Quit that whining. Our first order of
business is to halt their advance!
Simon!
Simon, wait a minute!
At least draw it out
of the city first!
We can't wait!
Gimmy! Darry!
Shoot down the fragments!
All of them!
- Roger that!
- Roger!
One down, one to go!
- Simon!
- Thanks!
And that's how it's done.
Now I get it! We just need to detonate
them before they get to the city!
I knew Simon could do it!
Assuming they only come
at us in pairs.
What's wrong?
If they appear in larger numbers,
that won't be a viable method.
Besides... It'll have the opposite
effect on the populace.
What's going on?
Dumb bastard! Is trashing stuff
all you're good for?!
It's all your fault!
Get away from us!
The moon's gonna fall on us!
What were you thinking?!
Go away! It's your fault
they're attacking us!
I can't believe it...
He should have listened...
This is...
This is what my fighting
has caused?
Remain calm, everyone!
Please listen to your government!
- Look, guns!
- They're gonna shoot us!
No, you're wrong!
We have no intention of--
Stop that.
No guns.
- Are you trying to kill us?!
- Get them before they get us!
Chief Advisor!
Are you all right?
It's not serious.
I'm fine, Kinon.
An injury is an injury.
You should get it treated.
I certainly hope
that this doesn't spread.
It will. Human impulses catch fire
and spread in the blink of an eye.
Just like they did when we
defeated Lordgenome.
But in this case, those impulses
are directed somewhere else.
Chief Advisor Rossiu...
Someone must be made
to take responsibility.
That is how a government functions.
The Anti-Spiral...
Who in the world
are they?
Nia...
What's all the ruckus, Rossiu?
Rossiu?
Supreme Commander Simon.
I hereby place you under arrest.
To Be Continued...
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Nariyamanai kodou ga itsumo itazura ni kokoro ni tane wo maku
My ever-sounding heartbeat always idly sows a seed in my heart
Sono tane ga kibou no hana wo sakasu ka mo shirenai
That seed might bloom into a flower of hope
Dakara kou shite yume wo egaku koto ga dekirunda
That's how I can sketch my dreams like this
Bunansou na nukemichi ga ukande ha kieteku
A loophole that seems safe comes to mind, but then disappears
Sou yatte boku ha tamesarete dou yatte omoi todokeyou?
By doing that, I'm tested; how can I get my feelings across?
Mayowazu ni mae he susunde
Let's advance forward without hesitating
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Dakara kakko tsukenaide kitto hana ha saku hazu sa
So don't try to look cool; I'm sure our flowers have gotta bloom
Bokura ha kagayaku yo Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
We're gonna shine! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Next Time
The million apes pray in unison,
asking for three things.
Prosperity, happiness, and...
No, now it's simply for survival.
Next time on
Gurren Lagann,
We Will Survive, By Any Means Necessary
..."We Will Survive,
By Any Means Necessary."