Your actions are baffling, Irregular.
Why do you resist me so?
You are a virtual lifeform that was spliced
into the genomes of Spiral races.
When the remnants of a Spiral race
rise up in rebellion against us,
...you would be awakened
and become our messenger.
That is your sole reason
for being.
The fact that you were born to a Spiral
warrior and loved by a Spiral warrior...
...is nothing more
than a coincidence.
There is nothing special
or unique about you.
It is a rare thing for a messenger
to be this recalcitrant.
The reason for your defiance...
The reason for their obstinacy...
If we can determine those,
we can surely find the key...
...to exterminating all Spiral
lifeforms in one blow.
No matter how deeply you probe my body,
you will never understand!
We have no need to understand.
We only need to KNOW.
Then you will never be able
to defeat them.
He will come.
You can be sure of that.
I'm here, Nia.
Just like I promised.
Impossible!
Sentient lifeforms can't possibly escape
from a extradimensional labyrinth!
Don't underestimate us!
We don't care about time or space
or extradimensional whatevers.
We don't give a damn
about that.
Force your way down a path YOU
chose to take, and do it YOUR way!
That's the
Team Dai-Gurren way!
Even when trapped
by the cycle of karma,
...the dreams we left behind
will open the door!
Even if the infinite universe
stands in our way...
...the seething of our blood
will determine what will be!
We'll break through time and space...
...to grab hold of our own path!
Tengen Toppa  Gurren Lagann
Tengen Toppa
Gurren Lagann!
Who the hell do you
think we are?!
Final Episode:
The Lights In The Sky Are Stars
This is surprising.
No Spiral race
has ever made it this far.
Being exposed to such
Spiral power,
...it is no surprise that our messenger
was made irregular.
As you wish.
We will fight you on
an even playing field,
...using the same form
that you find such comfort in.
What does he mean?
It is their way.
They are trying to inflict
absolute despair on us...
...by fighting and defeating us
on equal terms.
Lordgenome, your body--
We are in a Super Spiral Universe,
where thought is given form.
This is only a temporary body,
but allow me to join you in this fight.
I'd be honored.
Nia. I don't believe I have the right
to act as your father after all I've done,
...but you have done well.
Thank you, Father.
Have you snapped out of your
1000-year doldrums, Spiral King?
I am no king. Right now,
I am but a simple warrior.
Just as you are, Viral.
Yes, sir!
Is that all you have...
...Spiral race?
I'll handle this!
You waste your time!
- I'll help!
- Me, too!
And me!
This universe is under
our complete control!
Your chances of winning here
are zero!
Is that a--
Why, that's--
That is the Anti-Spiral's homeworld!
What?!
She is correct.
We Anti-Spiral were once a
Spiral race like yourselves.
But when we learned that the
evolution of Spiral Power...
...would lead to the destruction
of the universe,
...we annihilated all those who
possessed the power of the Spiral,
...and drove the few surviving lifeforms
to the far corners of the universe.
We halted our own evolution...
...and locked ourselves away
in this pocket universe.
On our homeworld, we sealed away our
bodies and any possibility of evolution.
This ugly form is the symbol
of our determination!
Foolish creatures who are
drunk on your Spiral Power...
Do you possess the resolve
to go to such lengths?
We were prepared to defend
the universe...
...by defeating our former fellow Spirals
and halting our bodies' evolution!
Do you possess resolve
that is on par with ours?!
We say no!
No! No! No! No! No!
Not in the least!
You possess neither will!
Nor resolve!
Nor reason!
You use your Spiral Power to satisfy your
own desires, and have grown drunk on it!
That is the Spiral races'
fundamental limitation!
It is for that reason that
we must exterminate you!
What's going on?
We're not even denting the thing!
We'll never be able to protect
Earth at this rate!
He's right, until we get
back to Earth, we--
Look! It's the Earth!
That's really the Earth?!
Some sort of fold in the
fabric of space-time, maybe?
Yes, probably.
The battle between Tengen Toppa
Gurren Lagann and the Anti-Spiral...
...probably interacted with the Spiral Realm
Perceptual Teleportation System, and--
And it created a spacetime
teleportation bypass.
Fascinating. That is your
homeworld, is it?
Gurren Lagann
Sis! Sis!
W-Wait a minute, Kiyal!
What's the big emergency?!
Look! That!
W-What is that?!
I'm getting a reading on the
Perception Teleportation System!
An unbelievably huge reading!
That's the Anti-Spiral?
Super Dimensional anchor!
You think I'm gonna let you
lay a finger on my Earth?!
- Hey, that's--
- Gurren Lagann!
- Give it all you've got, Gabal!
- Leave it to me!
That planet don't belong to you!
"I Got The Best Wife
In The Universe" Swing!
Now! Eat this! And this!
And this! And this!
That won't work.
Probability Alteration Missiles, huh?
I'm impressed!
You bet! When it comes to spacey
interruptions, I'm your man!
You continue to struggle, even
knowing what you know now?
Of course we do!
The tomorrow we're trying
to grab for ourselves...
...isn't the tomorrow that
you've set out for us!
It's the tomorrow that WE chose!
That WE chose for ourselves!
A tomorrow we chose
out of all the infinite universes!
We'll fight our way through!
We'll keep fighting
and protect the universe!
We'll stop the Spiral Nemesis, too!
You can't possibly do all that!
Just watch us!
Such arrogance coming from a lowly
species that is kept suppressed by us!
We will make you regret
your arrogance!
I'm reading a massive
energy buildup!
It's on par with the birth
of the universe.
It's almost like
a big bang...
And they're going to
hit us with that?
Infinity Big Bang Storm!
Burn in the everlasting hellfire
of the universe's creation!
Be utterly annihilated, down to
the very last scrap of DNA!
Hang in there, Darry!
You, too, Gimmy!
Crap!
This is bad! We can't take
much more of this!
- Simon...
- Honey...
It looks bad, but it will take more
than this to finish them!
Not yet!
We're not done yet!
Simon! Leave this to me!
Lazengann Overload!
Father!
Do not grieve for me, daughter.
My soul once drowned in a sea of despair
and weariness, but has been reawakened.
If the life of this temporary body will
create a tomorrow for all Spiral life,
...I will gladly give it.
Yes. I agree with you completely.
Nia, what are--
Simon, you've come all this way so that
you could do what you had to do.
Isn't that right?
I understand.
We'll win this fight.
Count on it.
Obviously.
Your deaths will be for nothing!
Now, begone!
Lazengann is undergoing
quantum breakdown!
That's what I was
waiting for!
Simon! Take it!
Lordgenome!
Let's do this together!
Impossible! He allowed himself
to undergo quantum breakdown...
...so he could become one
with the energy?
Eat this!
Never!
How can this be?
Where are you drawing
this power from?
We evolve beyond the person
we were a minute before.
Little by little, we advance a
little further with each turn.
That's how a drill works!
That is the path that
leads to extinction!
Why can't you see the limitation
of the Spiral races?
No, that's YOUR limitation!
You sit here in your
closed-off universe,
...locking away other lifeforms
like you're some kind of king!
That's nobody's limitation
but your own!
He's right! We humans used to have
somebody much, much bigger than us!
For his sake,
we'll move forward!
The human spirit is limitless! I've staked
everything on its greatness, too!
Mark my words. This drill will
open a hole in the universe.
And that hole will become a path
for those that follow after us.
The dreams of those who have fallen.
The hopes of those who will follow.
Those two sets of dreams weave
together into a double helix,
...drilling a path
towards tomorrow.
That's Tengen Toppa!
That's Gurren Lagann!
My drill is the drill that
creates the heavens!
Simon!
Get in there!
Lagann Impact!
If this is how it must be,
protect the universe at all costs...
Of course we will.
Humanity isn't that stupid.
What happened?
The energy that maintained that universe
between dimensions has vanished.
Simon! Do you read me?!
Simon!
We're being contacted by one planet after
another from across the galaxy!
The freed Spiral races are
sending us messages of joy!
There are so many others
like us out there!
Simon!
It's all over, Nia.
Yes.
Let's go home.
Welcome home, Mistress Nia.
Thank you, Old Coco.
Look at this, Simon!
See?
It's beautiful.
Thank you.
I mean it.
Nia, I'll never forget you.
Even if the universe ends.
Don't be silly.
It won't end.
That's what we've all
worked so hard for.
Yeah. You're right.
I love you, Simon.
Yeah. Me, too.
I love you.
Simon...
It's all right.
We knew this would happen.
Nia and I knew.
But it's not--
Defeating the Anti-Spiral meant
that this was going to happen.
Nia was a virtual lifeform
created by the Anti-Spiral.
I suppose we should be amazed that
she hung on as long as she did.
She always was
one tough cookie.
Then... Then you... Then you should
just use the power of the Spiral!
You can use that power
to bring Nia back!
And not just her!
All the other people we lost!
Simon isn't God, Gimmy.
Those who are dead
are dead.
If we bring them back to life, they'll just get
in the way of the next generation, right?
It's in your hands now, Rossiu.
Simon...
Me, I'm Simon the Digger.
There's someone better suited
to go through the tunnels I dug.
You can count on me.
It was fun while
it lasted, Simon.
Simon!
The Galactic Spiral Peace Conference...
I hope it goes well.
We may be fellow
Spiral races,
...but we're different species, and we
all have different ways of thinking.
In the end, it's taken 20 years
to put it together.
The job would have been impossible
for anyone else, President Rossiu.
I wonder what he's up to...
Don't worry. He's out there somewhere,
watching over us.
That's the sort of man
he is.
This is Nakim. I've been selected
to represent the entire galaxy...
...as a member of the
Grapearl Squadron.
We won't allow the Spiral Nemesis to occur.
Well, I'm off, Miss Yomako.
- Goodbye!
- Goodbye, Principal Yomako!
Goodbye!
It's finally time, Gimmy.
Yeah.
Captain, the Grapearl Forces are about
to lift off from the surface.
Good! Spin up the
Super Spiral Engines!
As soon as the Grapearl Squadron is
aboard, Super Teleport into deep space!
We're representing Earth out there!
Put some spirit into it, people!
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Nariyamanai kodou ga itsumo itazura ni kokoro ni tane wo maku
My ever-sounding heartbeat always idly sows a seed in my heart
Sono tane ga kibou no hana wo sakasu ka mo shirenai
That seed might bloom into a flower of hope
Dakara kou shite yume wo egaku koto ga dekirunda
That's how I can sketch my dreams like this
Bunansou na nukemichi ga ukande ha kieteku
A loophole that seems safe comes to mind, but then disappears
Sou yatte boku ha tamesarete dou yatte omoi todokeyou?
By doing that, I'm tested; how can I get my feelings across?
Mayowazu ni mae he susunde
Let's advance forward without hesitating
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Dakara kakko tsukenaide kitto hana ha saku hazu sa
So don't try to look cool; I'm sure our flowers have gotta bloom
Bokura ha kagayaku yo Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
We're gonna shine! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
What's wrong, kid?
I can't drill a hole
in this thing...
You're putting too much force into it.
Try turning the drill more gently.
Like this?
Hey, it worked!
You're awesome, mister!
Of course it worked!
Who the hell do you think--
Yum!
Nah, I guess I'm nobody.
Awesome! It's Gurren Lagann!
Look at all the Gurren Laganns!
You know, I think you're right.
I wonder if I can go, too?
Sure you can. The lights
in the sky are stars.
Yeah, they're stars. Stars where our
Spiral cousins are waiting for us.
The End