Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
Just then, a Gunmen's
big mitts came at me!
The mighty Kamina
was in a tight spot!
What saved me was Lagann, under the
control of my blood brother Simon.
"You won't lay a hand
on my brother!"
As that shout rang out, the Gunmen's
hand was shattered by a drill!
Thank you, my friend!
My brother!
Lagann ripped its hatch open, and this
is what I said to the Beastman inside.
"Hey, animal!"
The other hero of the hour
is pretty reserved, I see.
"Hero"?
No, I'm no hero.
Tell me...
Is he okay?
Bro?
Yeah. He wanted to go to the surface
to be reunited with his father,
...who left him when he
was young, right?
But then he found out he'd
been dead all this time.
He's pretending not to care, but that had
to come as a shock, don't you think?
I think it's something else.
He didn't want to see his father.
He hated himself for not being able
to go with him in the first place.
He's now a man who CAN go.
That's why he wanted to see his dad.
But doesn't that still boil down to him
wanting to be reunited with his father?
No, it's different!
Totally different!
I think.
I don't really follow you.
Sorry, it's not very easy
to put it into words.
That's okay.
Thank you.
I hope he really is okay.
Sorry for asking such
a strange question.
Episode 3:
Who Do You Think You Are, Having Two Faces!?
This turned out great.
They said they combined
all three of those Gunmen.
What's that logo
on your back?
Ain't it great? That's the logo
of Team Gurren!
So anyway, I'm about to go hunting.
Would you mind keeping me company?
Say what? What're we supposed to do
if Gunmen show up while we're out?
I don't think any more will come today.
They only come in the morning.
Oh, really?
They seem to have a set of rules
that they operate by.
We have to find food and water
while there's no fighting.
It's a bit of a hike,
so give me a lift.
All right.
Simon, let's go!
Me, too? Are you sure you
want me to tag along?
I guess.
So let me get this straight, all those
weapons are from your village?
That's right. For generations, it stood
guard over a forbidden storehouse.
But one day, poison gas started
leaking out of the storehouse,
...and our underground village
became uninhabitable.
Apparently, Littner Village is a weapons
cache that was built centuries ago.
Ah, and that's why you
came to the surface.
It was because of the weapons that
we were driven to the surface,
...and it's those weapons
that let us fight the Gunmen.
Ironic, isn't it?
Got it!
This rifle is powered by electricity, so if
I swap out bullets for these arrows...
Wow, you're good!
I'm the best shot in the village.
That's why I'm allowed to use it.
What do you say?
Want to try it?
Can I?
Got one!
Wow.
Ah, there it is!
Huh?
There are two arrows?
I'm impressed, human.
Who the hell are you?
Human Eradication Forces,
Far East Theater Commander Viral.
Say what? "Human
Eradication Forces"?
Here are two useful pieces
of information:
First, the Human
Eradication Forces...
...eradicate all humans
who come to the surface.
Second, that game is my dinner.
You will return it to me.
It is, is it?
Gosh, I'm ever so sorry.
I'll return it
right this minute!
It's still alive?!
You're not getting away!
Who's running? Don't insult me!
Who the hell do you think I am?
I'm Kamina of Team Gurren! Parents
use my name to get children to behave!
And I never turn my back
on an enemy!
That bravado will get you killed.
You fight well, but you're just
an amateur at swordplay!
Do you honestly think you're
a match for a trained soldier?
Dumbass! Real men
don't think, they ACT!
What was--
Damn, you dodged it...
Impressive, you managed
to injure me.
But a sneak attack is just a sneak attack.
It's only a surprise once.
It's over!
Bro!
Simon! Nice save!
I came when I heard gunfire!
A miniature Gunmen?
He spotted me
way up here?
A rebel faction, eh?
Perfect timing.
Uh-oh.
Simon! Kamina!
Yoko!
You're hurt!
Are you okay?
Yeah! The important thing is to
get to Gurren and take him on.
That S.O.B. boarded
his own Gunmen.
We'll take him on,
Gunmen to Gunmen!
Bro!
H-How did you
get there?
Leeron calibrated it for us.
Now we can remain in contact
with each other during a fight.
What's the plan?
We fight him, what else?!
But he seems a lot tougher than
what we've fought before.
Don't let him scare you, Simon.
You've got Lagann! You've got your drill!
Yeah, but--
Here we go!
I was recalled here because there were
reports of humans stealing Gunmen,
...but it looks like I'll have this
wrapped up before dinner.
"Gunmen"? That lame thing
isn't its name!
This is Gurren!
You're one cocky bastard,
a Beastman with two faces...
Faces? Oh, that. It's traditional for
a warrior to have a crested helmet.
It's not the place of some lowly human
to lecture me on such matters!
You people need to make up
your damn minds!
What are you,
humans or animals?!
You acquit yourself well enough in person,
but your mecha skills need improvement!
Kamina!
Simon, I'll cover you!
Get in there!
Yeah!
Get back, Yoko!
- Simon! Let's do the you-know-what!
- Got it!
Chew on this!
Finishing move!
Perfect Combustion of Manly Souls!
Cannonball Attack!
Pathetic.
I thought I told you. A sneak
attack is a sneak attack.
It's only
a surprise once!
Simon! Kamina!
He's mopping the floor with you!
It's all over!
Die!
They're gone?
They've mastered the art
of running away, I see.
No matter.
I'll wrap this up tomorrow.
Gurren Lagann
Simon, why'd you drill a tunnel?
I was scared.
I wanted to run away.
I don't want to do this anymore.
Let's go back to the village.
They have tough guys like that on their side.
We can't handle this by ourselves.
I don't want to die. And I don't
want to see you die, either.
If this keeps up, you're gonna
end up like your dad.
Simon! Your drill is meant
to dig towards the heavens!
- It's not for running away!
- But...
Tomorrow's the final showdown!
I'm getting some sleep.
You should go to bed, too.
Let me pilot Lagann.
I'll pilot it instead
of Simon tomorrow.
If I don't, you'll be killed
for sure this time.
I'll have Ron calibrate it
to let me operate it.
When it comes to combat,
I'm more used to it than that boy.
Simon can't handle this.
He's not the fighting type.
Look what happened today!
He ran away!
Simon will pull through.
Why? How can you say that?
Why do you have such faith in him?
There's no real logic to it,
I guess.
What is it, then?
It's all the same. I have faith in him
because I have faith in myself.
And because I can believe in him,
I can believe in myself.
It's all the same as far
as I'm concerned.
That's what it means
to be partners.
Don't put yourself out
on our account.
If he isn't beaten here,
we'll lose our home.
Plus, we're looking at a guy who found
some new power by doing something nuts.
You've got guts. I'll assign you
Team Gurren member names.
Team Gurren?
It's a place for manly souls.
I don't really follow you,
but we'd be honored.
This is odd... It's not starting
even with the key inserted.
Mechanically, there's
nothing wrong with it.
Even if everyone else should fall,
I won't take one step from this spot.
Yoko...
Because this is the
only home we have.
Because we have
nowhere to run!
Well, I suppose
it's do-or-die time.
If nothing else, I compliment you on
waiting here rather than fleeing, human.
And I compliment you on
not running or hiding,
...you sorta-human,
sorta-animal freak.
Attack!
Something itches.
Kamina!
You're members of Team Gurren!
I'm not gonna let this guy take you out!
You never learn any
new tricks...
..do you?!
Kamina!
No way.
On your feet.
Are you ready
to die?
I knew it, it's hopeless!
It's no use, everybody...
Let's give up, Bro!
Take a good look!
He keeps getting up.
Again and again!
Until you show up, he'll do it
as many times as it takes.
Kamina said something
to me.
"Don't believe in yourself. Believe in
the me that believes in you."
How about you?!
I...
I...!
Oh, getting up again,
are you?
I can't afford to be taken
down by you, not now!
If nothing else,
I compliment you...
...on not knowing when
to give up!
Kamina!
He's no match
for him!
Look, it's glowing!
This time,
it really is over!
What the--?
What kept you, Simon?
I'm scared. I'm so scared
I can't stand it.
But the thought of standing by and
watching you die is even worse!
Well put, little brother!
Time for the last resort! It's time
to break out the you-know-what!
The what?
Sorry, I don't know what.
Dumbass! What else
would I be talking about?!
We're gonna combine!
Combine?
Combine?!
Combine...
Forget about it.
We'll never know unless
we try, now will we?!
See that?! Now we have
two faces, too!
Now we're the same
as you, fuzzball!
You're stupid through
and through, aren't you?
It's the pilot's skill that makes all the
difference, not the number of faces!
Now die!
That's impossible!
Kamina! Simon!
Incredible!
What the hell is going on?
Bro, you were right!
We really combined!
It sure looks that way.
They combined...?
How could mere humans do that?
How ya like us now,
General Fuzzball?
Now we got a lid like you
and everything!
Go to hell!
Nope, nope, nope,
nope, nope!
A-A cross counter!
You best remember this, fuzzball!
Combining is all about one fighting
spirit slamming into another!
A combining of courage
that sets a man's soul on fire!
Gurren Lagann!
Who the hell do you
think I am?
From now on, the name of this
mecha is Gurren Lagann!
Gurren...
...Lagann.
Gee, how creative.
To think I'm now forced
to resort to my swords...
I underestimated you, human!
I told you, the name's
Gurren Lagann!
How did this happen? How could he
suddenly become so powerful?
All he did was attach
that miniature Gunmen!
How can this be?!
You'll never understand
as long as you live!
Why, you...
None of those dirty tricks,
you little--
Kamina!
Amazing, it even withstood
an attack like that!
It's so tough!
I wonder if it has a special energy field
that neutralizes the enemy's attacks?
Perhaps they really
are special.
Where'd you go,
you son of a bitch?
Hold up, Bro.
What?
You and Gurren are both in bad shape.
Chasing him would be a bad idea.
Simon...
It's not because I'm scared.
Well, I am, but that's not why.
It's so we can win
tomorrow's battles.
It's that sensible side of yours
that keeps me breathing.
Never mind.
Maybe you two really are
a good set of partners.
You and Kamina.
Well, um...
I'm sorry, I said some terrible
things about you.
Now I know better.
That's okay.
Hey, I found something
interesting in here.
Like what?
I found some data on a recall point
in Gurren's program files.
Recall point?
Gurren started out as an
enemy Gunmen, right?
So the place it goes to
for pickup...
...must be their headquarters?
Sorry, Dad, but I'm
gonna move on.
I'm gonna go see what's over
every horizon in your place.
You're really going?
Yeah.
We identified their headquarters,
so it'll be a quick job to crush it!
I'll be okay now. Even if I
get scared, I'll tough it out.
Here's a parting gift. Sorry.
A lot of us want to go with you, but--
Protecting your women and children
is an important job.
But looking at you two, I feel like
we can strive for bigger things, too.
Yeah, so--
Hey, wait a minute.
What's with those bags?
Oh, you don't need
a top-rate mechanic?
Well, I hadn't--
I guess we do.
Dayakka, are you sure?
Ron begged us to let him go.
I had no choice.
But he...
Come on, I can't let something
so fascinating pass me by.
Besides, it's possible that these
boys might make a change.
Change what?
Something.
Be good boys and see to
my luggage, would you?
See ya around!
You can go.
We'll look after Littner Village.
You have your own path
to walk down.
Still, I had no idea you were
a sucker for his type, Yoko.
Geez, it's not like that at all!
Thank you, Dayakka!
Until we meet again, Yoko!
We'll ditch you and that heavy ass of yours
if it ever slows us down, cellar chick.
Pipe down, you.
Want me to put lead slugs up your butt
and out your nose, Beloved Leader?
Wait just a minute! Team Gurren
is its own worst enemy?
Our enemy's the Beastmen!
You got that right!
Let's get to it, you fuzzballs!
This time, we're gonna
attack YOU!
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
Faces, faces, faces! Sad faces,
sulking faces, smiley faces!
Small faces, large faces,
angry faces!
Happy faces,
Gunmen's pale faces.
Next time on
Gurren Lagann,
Having Lots of Faces
Doesn't Make You Great!
..."Having Lots of Faces
Doesn't Make You Great!"