Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
So, I hear that Adiane blew it.
She went over our heads and boasted
in front of the Spiral King.
She will not come
crawling back now.
That said, would you do me the honor
of letting me strike next, Sire?
Wha--?
Guame? You, too?
This miniature Gunmen of unknown type
that they use, it concerns me.
And by combining with
this miniature Gunmen,
...they also say that Gurren Lagann
exhibits power it should not possess.
You have a good idea
what it is, I take it.
The humans have uncovered something
they should not have.
That is all it amounts to.
Whatever it is, it can't be
brushed off so lightly.
Please, Sire. Indulge me.
Guame, you dare tell me
what to do?
I was amazed back there.
There are few in this world who can
make the Spiral King do anything.
In that one regard, I bow
to your superiority.
It is because that miniature Gunmen
may very well be an incredible find.
And besides, he and I
go way back.
You're going up against a bunch
of battle-hardened barbarians.
There's no telling what
they'll come up with.
Needless to say,
I have a plan.
As I thought.
You think of everything.
Episode 11:
Simon, Hands-Off
Everyone!
Yeah?
What's this?
That? It's garbage, obviously.
It's a trash heap.
But this is Simon's!
It's too much!
Come on, he's a lost cause.
He's turned into a spineless kid
who's good for nothing but digging.
He'd be better off going back
to Giha Village.
But he's--
There's no place here for somebody
who can't pull his own weight.
Don't coddle Simon
too much, all right?
Coddle him?
He needs to snap himself out of this funk,
or it doesn't mean anything.
Oh, this must be that "Bro" person
you keep talking about.
I'm crazy, aren't I?
No, you aren't crazy.
When he's set in stone like this,
even I can see it.
I can see how much
you care for this person.
Digging tunnels is all I'm good for.
Back in our village, everybody said
I was creepy, or I smelled bad.
My Bro was the only one who hung out
with me and didn't make fun of me.
He was tough,
and kind, and big.
I wanted to become the kind
of man that Kamina was.
I tried, but it was no use.
I can never be like Kamina.
These are really good!
R-Really?
Can I stay and watch
for a while longer?
Sure...
Please help us!
Our village is under attack
by Gunmen!
Someone!
Someone, please help us!
The Gunmen are almost
upon us! Aieeee!
This is terrible!
Let's go help them at once!
I guess I can pinpoint
their location, but...
But this is awfully fishy.
It stinks? It smells?
For one thing, the enemy is sure to have
picked up that transmission, too.
And would people living underground
have equipment like that?
Shut up, shut up!
Don't worry about the details!
Do you want those babes' village to get
wiped out while we're standing around?!
He'd set out without a moment's hesitation!
That's what Kamina would do if he was here!
That's right.
He wouldn't hesitate.
That's for sure.
Right!
Dai-Gurren, move out!
That's the village entrance, huh?
Five Gunmen, huh? And we can't
use our main guns, either...
Fire!
There's a village under there!
Don't open fire, dumbass!
Sorry, I couldn't help myself.
The enemy Gunmen are fleeing.
Sweet!
Just as I planned!
All right, let's go see if
the village is safe!
It's nothing but young, hot babes!
What a dreadful village...
Thank you! Because of you,
our village has been saved!
There's no need to thank us. After all,
the Spiral King is everyone's enemy.
S-Still, from what we've seen, there
doesn't seem to be a single man here.
How, exactly, did that happen?
Well, about that...
Stay right where you are, humans!
I can't believe it! This was
a Beastman trap?
I said it was fishy...
You bastard!
What were you thinking,
you moron?
Dai-Gunzan has been secured.
We will now begin searching for Nia
and the miniature Gunmen.
Very well. Put your backs
into it.
Yes, sir.
Beastmen are their enemy, so they
assume all humans will be their allies.
What a bunch of fools...
It looks to me like they don't even
know who their #1 enemy is.
Don't resist, punk!
You there!
You're Princess Nia, aren't you?
General Guame says that
he wants to see you.
Guame? Very well,
I will see him.
Just don't hurt this boy.
Relax, we haven't been given
orders to kill anyone. Yet.
N-Nia!
Stay put!
Don't worry about me.
I will be fine.
Nia...
Simon.
You aren't your Bro, Simon.
I think you should just be yourself.
You're with me.
Come on.
Nia...
Damn it, let go of me, you furballs!
That's humans for you, no manners.
That's MISTER Furball to you.
I am Guame, the Immovable,
one of the Four Generals!
I'm taking back Dai-Gunzan.
I'm going to execute you publicly
as a warning to the others.
Stay put in here
until we're ready for you!
The Spiral King has issued
orders to eliminate you.
Then what Adiane said is true?
It is indeed.
If you'd died in your sleep in that box in
the valley, it would have been painless.
His Majesty is imbued with immortality.
He's lived for a thousand years or so.
Creating and raising children
is a pastime for him.
When he grows tired of one,
he disposes of it.
Just like he would a doll.
That's all it is.
Like a doll?
I'm told that you asked him,
"Why was I born?"
That was a bad move. His Majesty
detests human self-awareness.
Who can blame him? Why would a puppet,
a plaything, need self-awareness?
I am just like that doll...
Truth be told, though,
you are far too lovely to kill.
I've given some thought to the matter
of finding a way that you might live.
Would you be interested in becoming
chief of this village?
Its chief?
Indeed. After all, the girls here
are from villages far and wide.
Someone needs to teach them proper
etiquette before they're sent off to the king.
To what end? What becomes of them
after they are sent away?
The Spiral King lavishes them
with his affections.
It's a fair exchange, isn't it?
They get to experience luxury that they
would never know living underground.
The girls who are sent away,
they're more dolls, aren't they?
That's right. And once he grows tired
of them, they're discarded.
Just like you were!
Gurren Lagann
Don't underestimate folks who
were raised underground!
We'll bust outta this place
in no time flat!
That hurt...
Head hurt...!
It's no use! People are getting hurt
with nothing to show for it!
This bedrock is incredibly tough!
I've never seen anything like it!
It's hopeless... Our bodies will
give out before that rock will.
After all that, we haven't
so much as scratched it.
It's enough to make you despair...
Is this the end?
If only Kamina was here...
So, this is what he meant.
Kamina said something
to me once.
"He's always the one
who saves my ass."
who never gives up."
He said that?
My confidence was shot. I thought we
were heading in the wrong direction.
I freaked out. "Why did my dad
make it and I can't?"
Honestly, I was just acting tough.
Everyone was whining,
and they stopped digging.
I was at the end of my rope.
But Simon kept on drilling away.
His drilling let me
put on a brave face.
By dumb luck, he broke through
the last boulder right then.
We got lucky.
But I have faith in that luck,
and in Simon, who brought us that luck.
Whenever I feel timid and weak,
whenever I feel like I'm losing confidence,
...I think back to the sight of his back
all hunched over, digging away.
I think to myself, "I'll be a man that
won't be laughed at by that back."
Listen, Simon. Never forget this.
Believe in yourself.
Not in the Simon
that I have faith in.
Not in the Kamina
that you believe in, either.
- Believe in the Simon--
- ...who believes in you!
Lagann?
Lagann!
Huh? Was there a hole
here before?
General Guame, there's no sign of the
miniature Gunmen anywhere on the ship!
Don't give me that!
It has to be here somewhere!
Rip out the armor plating
if you have to, just find it!
Y-Yes, sir!
Why are you in such
a panic, Guame?
What?
You're afraid of him, aren't you?
You're scared of Simon.
Huh? Who is that?
Simon is the boy who first helped me
when I came down to the surface.
Not only that, he is the boy who
always protects me when I need him.
He will never lose
to the likes of you!
Ah, I see. He's that thing's
operator, is he?
Hey! Find the boy named Simon
among the prisoners and bring him to me!
Yes, sir!
- And the preparations for the executions?
- Everything is ready.
Excellent. The first one we will
put to death is this Simon boy.
I won't let you do it!
I'm the one who gets to
decide such things.
Be a good little discarded doll
and do what I tell you to do!
I will not.
You don't say? In that case,
you'll have to die, too.
I will not!
Oh?
I may be just another
cast-off doll,
...but I have learned one thing
since coming to the surface!
And what's that?
Just as Simon believed in his Bro,
I believe in Simon!
So, you won't yield, not even at
the bitter end. You're too naive.
I've lost interest in you.
I've no need for you!
W-What the--?
Gramps? What are you
doing here?
Nia! I'm here to rescue you!
Come on!
Simon!
Come with us--
Huh?
Why, you!
Come back here!
General Guame!
Follow that mini Gunmen!
I'm sorry I took so long.
That's okay.
I figured it out.
Lagann told me, too.
I understand now!
So do I.
Thank you, Simon!
Simon, move your hands.
Now.
Yeah!
This is why...
...I always say humans
are savages!
Oh, crap!
Guame Custom Gunmen:
Gember
Consider the tables turned, humans!
You've thrown a wrench into my plans,
but I'm going to execute you myself!
The sight of my
mighty Gember...
...and that of your own miserable
deaths will be projected...
...above the heads of every
human on the surface!
Say what, you bastard?!
I'm the one you're going to fight!
You think that little thing
is any match for my Gember?
What's the matter?
Gurren's being eaten!
Take that! And that!
Just a little more!
- Rossiu!
- Simon?
Let's combine!
Right!
Damn it ! It's that
mini Gunmen!
I don't believe it! This is the
Gurren Lagann I've heard about?
My Bro is dead.
He's gone.
But he's on my back! In my heart!
He lives on as part of me!
If you're gonna dig,
dig to breach the heavens.
Even if it's my own grave
I'm digging, I keep going!
Once I've dug my way through,
that means I've won!
What? What are you
talking about?
Who the hell do
you think I am?
I'm Simon.
I'm not my Bro, Kamina.
I'm ME!
Simon the Digger!
Spare me your ranting!
Gember Press!
Finishing Move!
That move, it was--
GIGA DRILL BREAK!!
Retreat!
Sound the retreat!
Simon, there's someplace that
I'd like you to take me.
These are all princesses who
were thrown away like I was.
Generation after generation of
princesses who came before me.
ALL of these?
I'd like to give them all
a proper burial in a sunny place.
Please.
- Yeah!
- You got it!
To me, Father was
my entire world.
My whole life, I'd believed in no one but him.
Relied on no one but him.
That's why I wanted to believe
in him until the very end.
Why do you suppose
we were born?
Nia, here.
You can have it. I found it
while I was digging.
It's lovely!
It's hard to explain, but it doesn't matter why
you were born or if you were a princess.
Right here and now,
that's the Nia you are.
That's why you should
go on being yourself.
And I'll live my life
as myself, too.
Yeah, that's more like it.
That's the Team Dai-Gurren way.
Ain't that right, Leader?
You're the man that Kamina
picked for the job, all right.
That name you gave yourself
is pretty half-assed, though.
What? H-Hey, come on!
Yeah, you're right!
That needs a little work!
Thank you so much!
I've input the location of the Capital.
All we do now is keep going straight.
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
The salty air, the blazing sun...
This is the beach?
It's a large pool of soft water?
Or a large reservoir of hard feelings?
Next time on Gurren Lagann,
Yoko, Will You Do Me
a Favor?
"Yoko, Will You Do Me
a Favor?"