Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who has yet
to realize what his destiny is.
With a feeling of relief, Simon and Kamina
finally reach the village of Littner.
What they found awaiting
them there was Viral,
...a Beastman who piloted
a powerful Gunmen.
Simon leapt into the fray to assist
Kamina in his moment of peril.
In the course of this
fierce battle,
...their two Gunmen, Gurren
and Lagann, combined!
Gurren Lagann's drill sent
Viral's Gunmen, Enki, flying.
What unknown power lies concealed
within Gurren Lagann?
Episode 4:
Having Lots of Faces Doesn't Make You Great!
I'm starving...
I wonder how far away the
Beastmen headquarters is.
Special training?
Think back, Simon!
To our combining! Our combining!
That was so lame I'm embarrassed
to think about it.
Listen, Simon, a manly combining
ought to be more... beautiful!
The act of souls that
are a raging inferno!
- Yeah, that was pretty bad.
- Simon!
Jump onto my shoulders!
It's pointless to do that
outside our mechas!
Right, Boota?
Simon, c'mon!
Watch what you're doing!
Simon!
What?
Combine!
How am I supposed
to do that?
Combine!
Those two seem to be
enjoying themselves.
Really?
What did you want
to check up on?
Watch this.
Now, then...
First we pull on the gloves,
..and now it's time to
do your thing, loves!
You brought THOSE along?
You and your creepy toys...
There's no call to be rude, missy.
Attaboy, attaboy, you can do it,
way to go!
Just as I thought.
I've seen all sorts of Gunmen over
the years, but nothing like this.
What do you mean?
It's still just a theory at this point,
but if what I'm thinking is correct...
...this Gunmen is special.
Oops, sorry about that!
It got away from me!
Hey, Simon!
You okay?
Ready for more?
- I'm real sorry 'bout that.
- My poor little mechie...
Whew, lucky thing
I didn't hit Lagann!
Okay, Simon!
Get ready for round two!
- That one was my favorite!
- You can always rebuild it.
Now, combine!
C'mon, Bro, cut it out!
Simon!
Quit your running!
Combine!
Combine, damn you!
You're not making any sense!
You're gonna kill me!
What are those people doing?
Simon! Combine!
Cut it out, Bro!
Okay, let's get in there!
Bro, I'm running on fumes!
I can't run anymore...
Damn it, Simon!
For a real man, a growling stomach
is no match for his fighting spirit!
Mine's growling too, huh?
I'm starving...
Bro?
What the hell?!
Bro!
Hello, little boy!
He's so cute!
You had a close call,
but you're safe now!
What's the big idea?
A-A woman?
I bet you were scared!
Son of a bitch!
On your feet, Gurren!
At times like this, you gotta smack
machines to get 'em to work!
Crap!
Prepare to die,
you Beastman bastard!
What? Beastman?
Are you kidding me?
Ow...
You're a human?
That's pretty damn obvious!
Who the hell are you?
Bro!
You weren't being chased?
You do a pretty good impersonation
of a human.
Hey, if you don't watch your mouth,
I'm gonna kill you for real!
Let's see those pearly whites.
Well, I'll be...
You don't have fangs.
Even so, how are you gonna
reimburse me for all this, huh?!
Who throws bombs at people?
- Reimburse you?
- Look at this mess! How were you raised?
Anyway, what the hell is
a human doing in a Gunmen?
Everybody knows that Beastmen
pilot Gunmen.
So they say.
So I say!
Well, the reason for that is...
'CAUSE I STOLE IT, THAT'S WHY!
You liar!
I pilot it!
That ain't possible!
Who the hell do you
think I am?
Beyond the furthest horizon,
I crawled up from Giha Village!
I have defeated as many Gunmen
as there are stars in the sky!
When you hear about Kamina,
the badass leader of Team Gurren,
...it is me they speak of!
- Wonderful...
- He's cute!
Kamina!
Oh, Kamina!
You're so cool!
I think you're wonderful...
You're so debonair!
I'm Kiyoh, the oldest sister.
Um, I'm Kinon, the middle sister.
I'm Kiyal, the youngest!
And this is our big brother---
Kittan.
You've met.
That's right!
We're Beastmen hunters!
The Black Siblings!
We, um, use this burning water to,
uh, destroy Gunmen.
Oh, that's what these
black things are?
That's right, it's scary stuff, man!
It'll blow you up real good!
Knock on wood, huh?
Kiyoh! Kinon! Kiyal!
Get away from him!
He and I have something
to settle with our fists.
Your attention, please!
Playtime is over, children.
Gurren Lagann
Why do WE have to go out
and find lunch for everyone?
It means that hungry men
are absolutely useless.
You're so lucky, Yoko! You get to
travel with such a great man!
What's so "great"
about that bozo?
Well, he certainly has
a booming voice.
He looks tough...
Yeah, and his feet
don't reek.
And did you see those
long eyelashes of his?
Yeah!
Look, a watering hole!
Where there's water, there's animals!
Hey, check this out! There's a
cool one on the ground over here!
It looks delicious!
You're traveling to the
Beastmen's headquarters?
What's a bunch of rank amateurs
like you gonna do about 'em?
You're just scared.
I ain't scared of nothin'! I'm sayin' that
you shouldn't underestimate Beastmen!
I'm starving...
You, too?
We've been tracking a Gunmen
with 16 faces since this morning,
...and haven't had
time to eat.
With 16 faces?
There's no such thing!
You sure you weren't hallucinating?
What, you've never
seen one with 16 faces?
Wha--?
I'm so hungry...
When you're hungry, it's hard to work up
the energy to do anything, right, Simon?
Yeah...
That cloud looks tasty!
That meat cloud is mine!
I saw it first, so I have dibs!
You wanna start somethin', jack?
What are you boys getting
so worked up over?
- Look what we found!
- Doesn't this look delicious?
Doesn't it?
Uh, is this edible?
You can eat anything as long
as it's not rotten, right?
Let's dig in!
Did you just bite me?!
Our lunch just talked!
Bro, take a close look
at their stupid mugs!
Hey, these guys is humans!
They're so cute!
Our siesta's been interrupted!
Whatever!
Let's eat 'em anyway!
They're pretty uppity for
a bunch of hairballs!
Don't call us hairballs!
Everyone, to me!
T-That's all, folks!
They ran away!
Hey! You don't suppose
those things were--
I'm starving...
You're right! They seemed
like Beastmen!
I never let a single
Beastman escape!
Any Beastmen hanging around here
must be with that 16-faced bastard!
Those things are what
we've been hunting!
The Black Siblings...
...are on...
...the job!
Crap...
Simon! Team Gurren
is going, too!
Bro...
What are you doing?
- It's no use, they bounce right off.
- Bro!
Almost there!
Oh, crap!
Let the pros handle this, amateur!
Hurry up, Simon!
We'll take 'em down in Gurren Lagann!
How can this be? How can
they operate Gunmen?!
I won't stand for it!
Come on, Simon!
Time to combine!
Okay!
Dumbass!
What was that for, Bro?
Quit your whining! Don't you
remember your training, Simon?
We're gonna get killed if we don't do something!
Hurry, we have to combine!
What the--?
Combining with a measly
two units? Ha!
I'll show you what combining
is all about!
This is combining
using 16 faces!
I'm surprised. I had no idea there
were other combining Gunmen.
Isn't that how
all Gunmen work?
- It combined?!
- Dumbass!
That ain't combining!
Proper combining is all about--
Bro!
If we don't do something,
we're history!
Damn it, Simon! Manly combining
is a thing of beauty,
..an act of two souls that
are a blazing inferno!
Would you just shut up
and combine already?
He's right! Gurren Lagann's combining
is something else entirely!
Boota?
Thanks, Boota.
But why does Kamina
keep doing that?
Jump!
I get it!
Bro, I get it!
Bro!
Simon!
Yoko!
Stupid little kid...
Guess I'd better do something.
What're you--
We're going in.
Sorry, Bro...
That's all I've got.
Simon! Run!
Yoko?
Simon! Start running!
Yoko!
Look, the kid's running!
Throw your bombs!
Hurry!
Oh, I get it!
We set up a smoke screen!
- Good thinking!
- I have my moments.
Those 16 bastards
are freaking out!
Simon!
I understand now! I get what you
were trying to teach me!
Compared to those rocks you lobbed
at me, dodging these is easy!
- You're missing the point.
- Look, Bro!
Ow!
That's it!
Manly combining is about fighting spirit!
The beauty of soaring through the air!
Brotherly Combining!
Gurren Lagann!
Now THAT'S how it's done.
Gurren Lagann?
That was wicked cool!
Sixteen-face combining!
That thing is big, all right...
So what? That just makes him
a big blockhead.
What did you call me?!
Kittan!
Hey! Kiyoh!
Kinon! Kiyal!
Damn it... Damn it...
It's no use... I can't work up
the energy.
We're screwed!
There no food anywhere!
What, Boota? You want me
to eat your tail?
Okay...
Bro!
What now, Simon?
Even this drill is starting
to look tasty...
Bro! Put this in your stomach!
This is...
...delicious!
Having lots of faces
doesn't make you great.
Manly combining isn't like
some tawdry love affair...
...where you come and go
as you please!
That isn't a true bond!
That's just a sham, a pale imitation
of the real thing!
What in the world is
he rambling on about?
True bonds, huh?
That's it!
That's what is different!
Your combining doesn't have
any principles to stick to!
Bro! Our arm! Drills are
coming out of our arm!
So allow me
to stick it to YOU!
Let's do it!
- One!
- Two!
- Three!
- Four!
Five!
Jamo!
- Fifteen!
- Sixteen!
See, we stuck you
with our own principles!
Gurren Lagann
is fearsome, indeed...
Let's get out of here!
Be careful on the streets at night!
- They did it!
- I knew Kamina could do it!
That Gunmen of theirs
is awesome!
Oh, you girls are alive?
That was a close call.
We came this close
to being buried alive.
What's the matter, big brother?
I can't help it!
I thought you guys were...
We're a lot tougher
than that. Right?
C'mon, let's go see
Kamina and Simon!
Hey! Come back here!
Looks like I'll be up all night
making repairs again.
Hey! Hairmateur!
What the hell is that?
It means someone who's a hair's width
better than a regular amateur.
Hey! You still wanna start
something with me?
If you ever want to join the
Black Siblings, come find us anytime.
But you'll be the good-for-nothing
youngest of the family!
And if YOU ever wanna join Team Gurren,
home of all things manly,
...give me a shout whenever!
See ya!
Bye bye, darling!
I proclaim my undying adoration
for you, Kamina!
See ya, guys!
We'll meet again someday!
Goodbye!
Well, they're gone.
Yeah...
You know, that snack earlier
was really tasty.
That's all you get!
Simon, get back here!
Let me have some!
Forget it!
You want some, too,
don't you, Boota?
Pretty please, Simon?
No! Absolutely not!
Hey, Simon!
Simon, c'mon!
Forget it!
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
There are things you know in your head,
and things you know in your gut.
Even if you react instinctively,
it's not the same as using your head.
That's one thing I just don't get!
I Don't Get it, Not One Bit!
Next time on Gurren Lagann,
"I Don't Get it, Not One Bit!"