Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who continues
to fight against destiny.
Simon uses fighting to try to distract himself
from the hard blow of losing Kamina.
Lagann goes out of control,
and when it stops,
...Simon meets a mysterious girl
who appears from out of a box.
When Adiane, the Elegant, one of the
Four Generals, attacks Dai-Gurren,
...the girl runs out
and says the following:
First Princess Nia, daughter of
Spiral King Lordgenome, orders you!
Leave us!
One of the Four Generals: Adiane, the Elegant
- Impossible!
- She says she's Princess Nia, ma'am...
Don't be stupid!
A princess wouldn't go wondering
around outside the Capital!
But ma'am, she looks
exactly like her.
Adiane's Custom Gunmen:
Sayrune
You think so? In that case, we'll just
kill her and pretend we never saw her!
General Adiane, please watch what you say!
All of our transmissions
are being recorded!
Her back is turned!
Did our little princess
really stop her?
Fire main cannons!
Fire! Fire! Fire!
Weren't you listening?
They're still offline.
Listen, stinking humans!
Get this straight, I'm not retreating!
I'll be back, got it?
What's a "princess"?
It's what you call the
daughter of a king.
Unbelievable, we've got the daughter
of the guy we're fighting on board.
Does this mean we use
her as a hostage?
What's the plan, Kittan?
- Yeah, what's the plan?
- Tell us the plan!
In any case, we'll interrogate her
first thing tomorrow morning.
I'll put the screws to her and make her
spill everything she knows!
Episode 10:
Who Is This Bro?
Teppelin, Royal Capital Audience Chamber
Adiane, the Elegant, fled in the face the enemy?
What manner of joke is this?
Sire. The dastardly enemy was
holding Princess Nia hostage.
You fool.
I have long since cast her out.
I do not care what happens to her.
Cast her out? But Sire, I was not
informed of this development...
You dare use that to
excuse your failure?
No, Sire.
Adiane, you committed the grave offense
of fleeing in the face of the enemy,
...all to protect a girl who
is no longer a princess.
Oh, the absurdity of it all...
Please, Sire!
Give me another chance.
Oh? You dare tell me
what to do?
I would not dream of it, Sire!
What is it, then?
To prove my loyalty, I shall
set out alone in Sayrune.
I shall wipe out all the humans,
along with Dai-Gunzan,
...and kill Nia along with them
before sunset tomorrow.
Very well. But bear in mind that you
will not receive another chance.
Go.
- General Adiane.
- Ah, Viral.
I was under the impression
that you were badly injured.
No, ma'am. I will be returning
to my home unit tomorrow.
My failure to protect General Thymilph
is the greatest failure of my life.
That said, I would like
to ask a favor of--
General Adiane...
Go on.
I'll hear you out.
During your next sortie--
I ask that you--
Allow me--
To--
Accompany--
You.
I had Thymilph in my debt, but with
him dead, it was all for nothing!
And it's all because
you're so worthless!
W-Which is why I beg you to give me
a chance to avenge him.
I've already decided that I will be
going out myself tomorrow morning.
Go back to your den.
I will be the one who
will avenge Thymilph.
Hey, shove all the unusable parts outside!
We can't do any work with 'em in the way!
Thank you for the meal.
- Thanks for the meal!
Yum!
What's this stuff?
It looks great!
I can't cut mine...
Just a moment,
I'll cut it for you.
So, anyway... Um...
Princess?
Yes? Would you
like some, too?
Open wide!
Hey, that's good...
Old Coco is a really
good cook...
- Really?
- You serious?
What are you guys, stupid?! Why are you
sitting around over a friendly dinner?!
You don't have to roll out the
red carpet for her like this!
We're here to do an interrogation, remember?!
An interrogation!
How do you do?
My name is Nia.
And what is your name?
I'm Kittan!
I'm the eldest of the Black Siblings,
and I'm the leader of Team Gurren!
Ah, Kittan, is it?
It's nice to meet you.
Just 'cause you're cute don't change
the fact that you're the enemy!
- Yeah! She enemy!
- Yeah, he's right! She enemy!
Kittan? What does "enemy" mean?
An enemy is a bad person!
Somebody you gotta beat the crap out of!
Beat the... crap out of?
And what does that mean?
Well, uh... That's when you take
your fist and belt the guy, and--
What does "fist" mean?
Well, a fist is--
Why would you do that?
Duh! Because they piss me off!
What does "pissed off" mean?
- He came to interrogate HER--
- But he's being interrogated instead.
Our bro isn't too good
around her type.
Butt out!
Kittan, you are, um... a not-pissing-off
person who is very sweet.
Thank you! Our talk has been
very informative!
Well, sure! I'm the leader,
so it's only natural.
Hey, Simon. I've got an order
for you as team leader.
I want you to get all the enemy intel
you can out of Nia.
Why me?
Just do it. You were the one
who brought her here.
Man up and do something
about it.
She's a formidable opponent.
Know that you're in for a tough fight.
I heard many things
from Kittan.
He said that my father is doing terrible things
to the people on the surface.
But I find it hard to imagine that Father
would do such things without good reason.
And yet, I also do not believe
that the people here are bad.
We didn't do anything wrong.
It's the Spiral King who's the bad guy here.
Him and his people.
Do you hate my father?
Of course.
Do you also hate me?
I don't know anything
about you.
Why do you fight, then?
It was my Bro who gave me
the strength to fight.
Because he was there
to believe in me.
Simon.
Who is this Bro person?
Do you think Simon
will be all right?
Don't you have other things
to worry about?
If I don't finally get
Dai-Gurren here running again,
...a lot more than tears
will be spilled here.
Yes, but in Simon's case, he--
We're all fighting here.
That goes for you, too, right?
Yes...
Besides, if the reason that
Lagann isn't working...
...is because it doesn't feel like helping
a kid who's lost the will to survive,
...I think it has the right idea.
Oh, I see. He was killed
in a battle recently.
In that case, I suppose it's no wonder
that everyone here hates me.
No one hates you, Nia.
I don't think that Kamina
fought out of hatred.
It's hard to explain, but no matter how bad
the situation, he was always laughing.
I guess he was...
A man whose stupidity
knew no bounds.
I'd like to hear about him, too.
Keep talking.
This happened long before
we met you, Yoko.
We tried to break out of our
underground village ourselves.
But along the way, there was an earthquake,
and we were trapped.
Hey, I know this--
Never mind. Keep going.
I was terrified that I was going to be
buried alive just like my mom and dad were.
But Kamina urged us on, yelling,
"Onwards and upwards, men!"
Laughing all the while.
My hands stopped shaking.
When I'm focused on drilling, I can hear
the soil and the rocks calling to me.
"It's softer this way,"
or "Try digging over here!"
I follow their advice as I dig.
But if we'd have given up that day,
we all would have died.
The reason we didn't
was because of my Bro.
Because he didn't give up.
That's how he always was.
Without him,
I can't do anything.
That's why I have to become like him,
so I can do his share for him.
That's not true.
You rescued me
all by yourself, remember?
That wasn't--
You can do just fine
on your own.
Why are you obsessing so much
over this "Bro" person?
Why? Because--
You're just saying that because
you didn't know him.
I can't get to know
a dead person.
But you also can't rely
on a dead person, Simon.
Nia!
You can't know
how Simon is feeling!
You didn't even know Kamina!
I may not have known this Bro person,
but I do understand Simon.
Simon is not a helpless person.
He mustn't keep dwelling
over a dead man.
Don't talk like you're an innocent
bystander in all this, lady!
You know perfectly well
whose fault it is that Kamina died!
So don't you dare stand there
and calmly lecture him!
I apologize.
What you said is right. No amount
of grieving will bring Kamina back.
We know that.
Maybe it would be easier
if we could forget about him.
But we can't just... forget about him
like he was nothing!
She had tears in her eyes...
It isn't your fault, Nia.
I want to learn more
about you and your people.
Gurren Lagann
W-What the hell is that?!
We've got trouble! A wall of water
is coming this way!
Water?
Maybe he's seeing things
after being up all--
An enemy Gunmen
is on our deck!
I've returned, just as I promised!
You stinking humans!
What the hell was--
It's that chick with the fins
from yesterday!
First of all, would you be so kind as
to let me see our dear princess?
I need to thank her for all the things
she's done for me.
That bitch! The nerve of coming
with just one Gunmen!
I'm gonna deck her!
Wait a minute.
Dai-Gurren still can't move.
We need to buy
all the time we can.
Good point...
Okay, let's hand over Nia!
We can't do that!
Say what?! You got a problem with the
decisions of your mighty leader?!
I'm not sure why, but something tells me
that would be a risky move.
Don't give me that half-assed crap!
Come out and say it! Quit yammering!
I will go.
Hear that? She says
she's okay with it.
Yeah, but--
Don't worry. She might
be able to avoid a fight.
Thank you, Yoko.
This doesn't mean that I trust you.
I'll have this rifle
trained on your back.
If I see any funny business,
I won't hesitate, got it?!
Yes.
I see that you are well,
Princess Nia.
Tell me, Adiane.
Are you and the others making the
humans here on the surface suffer?
It is as you say. Our duty is to slaughter
every last human we find on the surface.
Were you ordered to do this
by my father?
Yes.
And you harbored no doubts
about these orders?
Doubts? Never.
Humans are as lowly as worms.
Their death and suffering
is beneath our notice.
"Worms," huh?
I cannot believe this!
I will discuss this with my father!
Adiane, take me
to my father at once!
You piss me off,
you flake!
If you wanna go, take your
own sorry ass there!
What did you say?
It hasn't sunk in yet?
You aren't a princess anymore!
The Spiral King has abandoned you!
Cut you off! Thrown you out!
I don't know what you did, but he said
to kill you along with the worms!
Abandoned me?
Kill me?
Father said for you
to kill me?
Abandoned her?
Lagann! Work!
Please work!
I was right! She didn't
come here to bring Nia back!
This cannot be true!
Father would never do such a thing!
He wouldn't, huh?
Think whatever you want!
I'm sending you to the next world
in a few seconds, missy!
Do you hate me, as well?
Hate you? I couldn't
care less about you.
I was told to kill you,
so that's what I'm going to do!
Whether I hate you or not
doesn't enter into it!
You would kill me simply because
you were ordered to do so?
Of course I would!
Then if my father told you to die,
would you do that, as well?!
You are wrong!
These people have done
nothing wrong!
Their only wish is to live
on the surface in peace!
It cannot be right to kill them
for no reason.
These people killed Thymilph.
They did?
That should be reason enough!
No. No, you're wrong.
That isn't right.
They themselves have lost
a man they call Bro.
This loss has left them
sorely wounded.
Yes, that is what happens
when someone dies.
People suffer,
and they hurt inside.
And yet here you are, saying that two
grieving parties should hurt each other!
Don't you think that there is
something wrong with that?
NO, I DON'T!
Fine, have it your way!
You piece of crap!
Nia!
You really know how
to piss people off!
Now I know why the Spiral King
got rid of you!
Yes, now I see!
You are a pissing-off person!
That's my line, missy!
- Nia!
- Simon!
Simon!
Nia!
He threw out his own daughter?!
That's one thing I won't stand for!
- Won't stand for it!
- Smash!
DIE!
You guys take it from here!
Stinking scum!
Zorthy!
You bitch!
Come on, you third-rate Gunmen!
Come at me all at once!
I'll tear you limb
from limb!
Come on, isn't this thing
working yet?!
I'm trying, I'm trying!
How about now?
What?!
Impossible...
It broke my spine!
- We got her!
- Yeah, got her!
Now! Squash her!
We'd like to, but we can't exactly
see where we're aiming!
No.3 Bridge!
- You've got her, you've got her!
- That's the way! Straight ahead!
Look out ahead!
What was that?
What happened?
Enkidu!
Is that you, Viral?
Forgive me for
disobeying orders, ma'am.
But I have my own honor
to uphold!
Not so fast.
I can't withdraw like this!
You can continue the fight as long as
you are still alive, General Adiane!
It's time for a strategic retreat.
You!
We're retreating for now,
...but when next we meet,
we'll settle matters once and for all!
What's he talking about?
They're gone!
They bugged out!
We did it!
We drove them off again!
Goodness gracious... All this stress
is murder on my skin.
Are you okay, Nia?
Yes, thank you.
But I must apologize.
You were put in danger because of me.
There's no need to thank us.
See? Look at that.
Nia!
They're all happy to see you
safe and sound.
Thank you...
Thank you!
You scum! Trash!
Vermin!
What's the big idea,
leaving without a victory?!
I can't return to the Capital
without my revenge!
Who do you think I am,
you worthless piece of trash?!
Well met,
my good pig-mole.
Is Simon inside?
Simon?
Simon, are you there?
I brought you some dinner.
Simon, everyone says they
are happy to see me safe.
Even though I am their enemy...
As I thought, the people
here are all very nice.
But I know.
I know that you were the first one
to run to my rescue, Simon.
Simon, thank you.
I can't do it...
I can never be like you, Bro...
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
Inside people's hearts, there is
a deep, dark, frightening hole.
This eventually becomes
a new tunnel.
Next time on Gurren Lagann,
"Simon, Hands-Off".
Simon, Hands-Off