Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
One Month Later
Bro...
I can never be you, but I'm going off
to do what only I can do.
The things that only
Simon the Digger can do.
It's almost time for them
to get started.
I'll come back to visit
once this is all over.
Welcome back.
Did you do what you needed to do?
Welcome back!
Simon, welcome back!
- Yeah.
- Welcome back.
Are you done with repairs
to Dai-Gurren's levi-sphere?
Just about. We'll be neck and neck
with their starting time.
Let's hurry. I have a feeling that they'll
be pulling out all the stops today.
You're right. If we don't end this soon,
we'll come apart at the seams.
Don't worry.
We'll win, count on it.
You mean it?
But look at how big
that is!
I mean it!
Who the hell do you
think we are?
Battle for Teppelin Day 6
It is said that the god who once created
the world in seven days...
...created man on the sixth day.
Sire?
Ah, that is from one of the
ancient holy scriptures.
This is the sixth day since that rabble
arrived here. A perfect sign, Sire.
Amusing. In that case, I ask that
I be given that task, Sire.
Dai-Gunten will take the lead.
It is all yours.
To a young pup
of 200 years,
...I see that this is still
just an exciting game.
I must say, they're
a tenacious bunch.
No matter how many times we stomp
on them, they sprout again like weeds.
That is what makes them
so terrifying.
And this in spite of the fact that I sealed
them in the depths of the earth...
...so they would never again
take root on the surface.
It must be the power
of the Spiral.
For crying out loud...
They don't even realize that this power
will lead to their destruction.
Ignorance... Even so, it is what
allows them to fight.
I pity them.
Episode 14:
Well Met, Everyone.
Flying Carrier Fortress Gunmen:
Dai-Gunten
Enemy battleship detected overhead!
It's Dai-Gunten!
Damn! They're here
sooner than usual!
- Levi-sphere status?
- Leeron! How's it coming?!
Leeron!
We are now inside
Dai-Gunten's firing range!
What's the holdup, Leeron?!
Okay, thanks for your patience!
Repairs are complete!
Rapid ascent!
Take us up!
They dodged them, eh?
Scramble bomber Gunmen squadrons!
Dai-Gunten has launched Gunmen!
Count, five! No, eight!
Um, twelve?
Um... Um...
Lots!
No prob! With big guns,
quantity counts more than precision!
We're not hitting 'em...
We'll send up our Gunmen, too!
- All right, that's our cue!
- Our cue...
You better keep up, Kittan!
Hey, who the hell
do you think I am?
The mighty Kittan, oldest brother
of the Black Siblings, right?
Kiyoh? What do you think
you're doing?
I'm here, too!
Kiyal? You, too?
Come on,
you're shorthanded, right?
You little twerp, this isn't
a training exercise!
That's a Four Generals
jumbo battleship out there!
There's no guarantee that any
of us will come back alive!
- That's exactly why we're going.
- Besides, we want to avenge Kamina.
You guys...
Kiyoh! Kiyal!
I'll watch over Dai-Gurren,
so go out there and give 'em hell!
All right, you got it! Let's go show 'em
what the Black Siblings are made of!
Yeah!
Throwing!
Sorry for the delay, Gurren Lagann.
Launch!
Simon, we're counting on you.
Let's get out there, Simon!
Right!
Let's do it!
Gunmen squadron, follow me!
Well, well, the amateur's turned into
a first-rate commander!
Listen up! We'll handle the cannon fodder!
You nail that battleship!
I'm on it!
- Okay, let's do it!
- Yeah!
- Okay, Kiyal, time to combine!
- Okay!
King Kittan Deluxe!
- Let's do it!
- Yeah!
Gunmen squadron has made contact
with enemy Gunmen!
Good. We'll let Simon and the others
take care of the airborne units.
How are things going?
We managed to evade their opening gambit,
but things are just getting started.
Enemies also detected
on the surface ahead!
Impregnable Fortress Gunmen:
Dai-Gundo
That's the other enemy battleship!
Dai-Gundo?
So, they've finally sent out
both battleships against us.
Have a good taste of my heavy
bombardment Gunmen squad.
Take evasive action!
Easier said than done!
It's a hail of bullets to either side!
Crap!
This is bad!
Dai-Gurren's taking a beating!
Can't a few of you
head back?!
Get real!
We don't have time to--
Simon?
Leave these guys to me!
You go help Dai-Gurren!
Quit screwing around! Are you trying
to grandstand or something?!
If we lose Dai-Gurren now, we won't be
able to take on that behemoth, Teppelin!
Then we should at least
split up the squadron!
That won't work! If we thin out
our offensive capabilities,
...we'd lose fights that
we could have won!
Okay, you win.
All right, we're all going!
Let's smash those surface Gunmen!
Yeah!
Simon, these guys
are all yours.
I'll handle 'em!
What a fool! What do you think you can
do with a single Gunmen, naked ape?
Just try me!
That was interesting, human,
I'll give you that!
Simon, are you all right?
You've got to pace yourself!
Yeah, I'll take a quick break.
You handle these.
He's willing to kill his own men?
Rossiu! Lob it back at them!
Right!
Not bad, human! But we're
just getting started!
You still have to face the mighty
Cytomander in his Shuzack!
Damn!
Simon!
That's a Four Generals
custom Gunmen!
And it looks like Gurren Lagann's
power levels are falling!
Aretenborough!
I've been firing and firing
for a while now!
Move it, you jerks!
You're in the way!
They're acting as shields
for the others...
It was a valiant effort, naked ape.
Crap!
It's no use! It looks like we used
too much power all at once!
Bro...
It's all over!
What the hell?!
It's fire from ship cannons!
What happened to my
shield Gunmen?!
Sir, the fire isn't coming
from just one ship!
What?!
Now!
Where's that fire coming from?
From the east!
On the eastern horizon, it's--
That's... It's Bro's flag!
Do you read me,
members of Team Gurren?
Who are you?
We saw those pictures that
were floating in the air!
Back in that trap?
I'm Bachown, and I've come running
from Dokkanai Village to the south!
I'm Basilia from Hatesai Village!
Good to meet you!
I'm Sawbow, and I've
come from the east!
We've been jacking
enemy battleships, too!
You mean you guys
are reinforcements?
That big-ass ship up there
is the head honcho, yeah?
All turrets, cut loose!
Reinforcements!
Reinforcements are here!
Listen up, people! We can't
let them have all the fun!
We'll smash all the ground units!
Make your shots calm,
quick, and clean!
C'mon, is that all you got?!
H-Humans?
They're humans?!
When did this horde
of humans get here?!
Direct hits to armor plating!
No. 3 ventral levi-sphere damaged!
Output is falling!
General Cytomander! I suggest
a temporary withdrawal!
All right, you've had your fun...
Now, allow me to show you
what Shuzack is made of!
A knife...?
Punch it!
Dai-Gunten is falling this way!
It's on a collision course!
No time to evade!
Cytomander, you were
a fool of a hatchling...
We did it... We did it!
We sent the two of 'em
straight to hell!
- All that's left...
- ...is Teppelin, the Capital!
No, not yet!
I'm still reading something!
Gurren Lagann
A huge explosion like that,
and there's not a scratch on it!
That thing's hard as a rock!
Dai-Gundo's running away!
Victory is ours!
It's too soon to celebrate, idiot!
Blow it to pieces right away!
With that armor, nothing
we throw at it will work.
I wonder what it's doing?
It's spinning!
Something came out!
Looks like it's time to tidy up.
This is just a last act of desperation!
It proves we have 'em on the ropes!
Continue the charge!
Spin, spin!
This is my and Dai-Gundo's
Carousel of Death!
Energy influx from Teppelin
holding steady!
- Conversion efficiency over 300%!
- Area of effect is expanding!
Growing from 4000 to 5000!
Keep this up and wipe all traces
of these humans from the surface!
So, Teppelin and Dai-Gundo combined,
and are generating a powerful energy barrier...
Huh? What?
It means that if we don't stop Dai-Gundo's
spinning, we'll never get close to Teppelin!
- Hold on tight!
- Sis!
Son of a bitch!
What the hell is this?!
Damn Beastmen!
Don't screw with us humans!
Bachown!
Simon!
It's no use. We have to do something
about that whirlwind!
We can't let Bachown's death
be for nothing!
- We have to go!
- We'll ram it, too!
Hey! What are you
people doing?
Are those guys morons?!
Hurry! Stop them!
I can't! Communications are down
because of that whirlwind!
If we don't hurry,
they'll be wiped out!
Please stop!
Well met, everyone.
I'm Nia, head cook
of Team Gurren.
Looks like they've stopped.
As you can see, Teppelin is surrounded by
a tornado-like barrier of light at the moment.
If we don't do something about it, you will
blow up just like those gentlemen just did.
Please be patient for a little while.
What good is waiting gonna do?!
The whirlwind will stop soon.
Simon will stop it for us.
I say this because
Simon's drill...
...is the drill that will
break through the heavens!
Brother, you moron!
Simon?
Now that you mention it, there's been
no sign of Gurren Lagann anywhere...
Hey, that's right!
Where did Gurren Lagann go?
Simon, this is a sneak attack, so we
have to get it right the first time!
I know!
Enemy unit closing in!
Beneath us! It's underground!
What?
It's not working! We're just lifting it up,
we're not penetrating the armor!
Give it time! My and Kamina's
Gurren Lagann can do more than that!
Please, Gurren Lagann! If you
have a mind, respond to me!
Have Dai-Gundo reverse thrust!
Reverse thrust, sir?
That's right! Flatten them!
Gurren Lagann, it's--
Been crushed?
My, my, what a disappointing
end to things...
Still, I suppose I should congratulate
these humans for a valiant effort...
Just a minute, sir!
I still hear something!
Hear what?
It's a rasping noise...
It's a drill!
Thanks, pal. That impact just now
drove the tip of my drill inside!
This is just a last act
of desperation.
He can't possibly beat my
Dai-Gundo's spinning.
We'll see about that!
S-Stop! Dai-Gundo mustn't be
spun around the other way!
Round and round...
Are you watching, Lordgenome?
Your humble servant Guame
is still spinning!
That crazy S.O.B. Simon
actually did it!
The whirlwind has disappeared!
You did it, Simon...
Okay, people! All that's left now
is to level Teppelin, so--
Huge buildings are falling this way!
What's going on?
- Teppelin, it's...
- It's crumbling on its own?
It's huge...
What in the world is going on?
I-I don't believe it!
It's a--
A huge face...?
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
I've come all this way,
just to tell him this.
That the other humans and I have
just as much right to be on this world.
Next time on Gurren Lagann,
"I Will Head Towards Tomorrow".
I Will Head Towards Tomorrow