Gurren Lagann
Sugita kisetsu wo nageku hima ha nai
I don't have the time to lament the seasons that have passed
Nido to mayotte shimawanu you ni
So that I won't ever waver again
Kazoekirenai hon no sasayaka na
With countless, tiny little
Sonna koukai kakaeta mama
Regrets carried in my arms
Sono senaka dake oikakete koko made kitanda
I've come this far, having chased only after your back
Sagashite ita boku dake ni dekiru koto
It's something only I, who sought you, can do
Ano hi kureta kotoba ga ima demo
Those words you gave me that day, even now,
Kono mune ni tashika ni todoite iru kara
Definitely reach my heart
Kinou yori mo kyou ha bu ha boku no
I've realized my reason for having been born
Umarete kita wake ni kidzuite yuku
Today more than I did yesterday
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
Seven years since the fall of Teppelin
Kamina City, the New Capital
(Human capital built on its ruins)
With Lordgenome's defeat,
humanity was free to come up to the surface.
What are Lagann, the Core Drill,
and Spiral Power?
Why did Lordgenome try to drive
humanity underground?
All those mysteries and more
remain unsolved.
But we are intent on building
new lives for ourselves,
...so we focus on tomorrow's hopes,
not yesterday's lingering questions.
One of the few riddles we DID solve
is Old Coco's true identity.
Apparently, he was a Beastman created
to serve as Nia's butler,
...and he had always
looked after her.
Is it because we're at peace that we've
only solved such trivial mysteries?
Yes, we have luxuriated in
this peace for seven years.
Pretending all the while
not to notice...
...Lordgenome's dying words gnawing
away at us from the inside.
Come on, Rossiu,
have a heart!
These are all citizen complaints.
The sewers are backed up.
Taxes are too high.
The neighbors are too noisy.
It's all self-centered nonsense.
They've all completely forgotten
what life was like in the cellars.
- I think that's great.
- But is it?
Something bothering you?
No, sir.
Well met, you two!
Nia! What brings you here?
I made you some lunch!
Oh, I'm sorry, Rossiu. I forgot
to make any for you!
I'll rush out and
make something!
No, that's quite
all right.
There is an Executive Council
meeting in 15 minutes.
Please finish lunch by then,
all right?
Episode 17:
You Don't Know Anything
This is your Leeron,
Science Bureau Chief!
Our moon probe Gunrocket
was launched successfully.
It'll arrive at the moon
in one day.
Understood.
Submit your report later.
Will do!
This has been the one
and only Leeron! Ciao!
Come on, do you really think you'll
find something on the moon, Simon?
Address him as Supreme Commander,
Legal Affairs Bureau Chief Kittan.
Yeah, yeah...
One million apes...
When the land comes to overflow
with one million apes,
...the moon shall become Hell's messenger
and destroy the world of the Spiral.
Those were Lordgenome's
dying words.
Thinking about it hasn't
gotten us anywhere.
We have to go there
and see firsthand.
If we don't find anything there,
no harm done.
It's pretty amazing.
Seven years ago, we didn't even
know the moon was a satellite,
...and now we're capable
of sending probes there.
Citizen Affairs Secretary Jorgun,
how is the census proceeding?
Uh, about that...
The "million apes" refers
to us human beings.
It is vital that we determine when the
planet's population will reach one million.
And we must do it
as soon as possible.
Aw, don't talk like that. It's a mistake
to have these two count anything.
No one is suggesting they do it themselves.
Use your organization to do it.
Look, I'm just sayin' that these two
can't handle a delicate job like that.
Then what are you people
still doing in the government?
During every council meeting, all you do
is kick back and relax! Is that your job?!
Those who said they couldn't handle the job
and left are better men by far than you!
- Say what?
- What?!
Give it a rest!
Would if be all right if I issued orders
to the Citizen Affairs Bureau?
Sure.
Relax, you two. There won't be
any change in your status.
Let's let Rossiu oversee this.
That's all.
Who does he think he is?!
We got somethin' to offer!
We got somethin' to offer, too!
My goodness! Look at these two fine
notables of the New Government!
No one eats
quite like you do!
Please, feel free
to eat all you like!
After all, Kamina and Simon,
the heroes of the revolution,
...grew up eating my
pig-mole steaks!
I raised those boys
as if they were my own!
With him around, you wouldn't need to be
Kamina to want to get to the surface.
What's the matter?
You look kinda bummed out.
A million apes...
The Spiral King was just
messing with our heads.
You gotta take that with
a big grain of salt.
Dumbass, Dayakka's worried
about his kid.
Oh, right.
It's about due.
How can you be so relaxed, Kittan?
You're about to be an uncle, man.
It just hasn't sunk in yet....
Come try the pig-mole steak loved
by the heroic Gurren Lagann,
...it made Kamina and
Simon's mouths water!
Hey, sis!
Does the laundry go over here?
...it made Kamina and
Simon's mouths water!
That's fine.
Thanks.
Chief Shak's Steakhouse's pig-mole steaks
come straight from Giha Village!
That's fine.
Thanks.
Chief Shak's Steakhouse's pig-mole steaks
come straight from Giha Village!
Coming!
I've got it!
You sit down, sis.
I'll throw one on the
grill just for you!
I've got it!
You sit down, sis.
- He proposed?!
Yes.
Well, well. Simon finally
took the plunge, did he?
That's why I was hoping
to get your advice.
Tell us! What did he say?
I have to know!
It's beautiful, isn't it?
This city.
Yes.
Everyone is living happy lives
under the sun.
You're right.
Maybe the time is
finally right to get out.
To be regular people, not a princess
or the leader of Team Gurren.
To see the same things, hear the
same sounds, and to laugh together.
Maybe it might be nice to
have that kind of life now.
My eyes would be your eyes,
and your ears would be my ears.
Maybe something like that
would be nice.
What's this?
Let's get married, Nia.
No way!
You turned him down?!
Yes.
Why did you turn
him down?!
Well, I thought that maybe two people
couldn't really become the same person.
Um...
Well, that's true, but, well, that's
basically what married couples are.
Anyway, he only meant it
as a figure of speech!
Sis! Be careful with the baby!
Simon, that boy who's only good at digging
tunnels and fighting in Gurren Lagann...
...spent seven years trying
to get those words out!
How about you?
How did they make you feel?
How did I feel?
Yes! It isn't the meaning of the words that's
important, it's how they made you feel!
Looks like we have
an answer.
You're the same old naive,
pampered princess as ever...
Well, I'd say that's
what makes Nia Nia.
It's the woman's turn
this time.
Don't tell him in words,
tell him how you feel.
It's huge!
Well, it's the Kamina City
monument, after all.
He would have appreciated
the overkill of it.
Yoko!
We can't talk you out
of going?
Nah... I'm not cut out for all this
council and politics stuff.
That's not true! I'm sure you would do
just fine if you set your mind to it!
No, no. You guys
can do it.
See ya.
You better keep Nia safe. You hear,
Supreme Commander Simon?
That pampered princess isn't going
to deign to let me protect her.
Hello?
Nia?
Um... I think you and I
are different people.
Very, very different people.
But since we're the same in being different,
I think living together would work out.
Thank you for this ring.
I really like it.
Yeah!
I did it!
Bro, I did it!
You seem awfully happy.
Supreme Commander.
A-Ah, Rossiu.
What can I do for you?
There's been an attack by anti-government
guerillas in southern Henpeena Sector.
What?!
The Grapearl Squadron has already been
scrambled, but you should see this.
Viral?
Okay, I'll join them
in Gurren Lagann!
No. You are Supreme Commander
of the New Government.
It is not your job
to go into combat.
That's Viral out there!
If I don't settle things with him, he'll--
Please focus on doing your own job!
Supreme Commander Simon!
You cheap Gurren Lagann knock-offs
are no match for me!
Where is Simon?!
The Supreme Commander
isn't gonna dirty his hands with you!
Gimmy, be careful!
Your shooting's as sharp as ever!
Thanks for the save, Darry!
Viral!
My shield!
It won't hold...?!
You're screaming,
aren't you, Enkidudu?
Hang in there for just
a little longer!
You're down for good, huh?
Thanks for putting up with my selfish
demands on you for so long. I'm sorry.
Viral.
What's with that look?
You are one persistent guy.
Why do you insist on opposing us?
The war is over.
I don't want to hear that from the man
who's taken over Teppelin's throne.
What's that supposed
to mean?
Look at that. I was trying
to protect them.
- They're humans?
- That's right.
They told me that they wanted
to live underground.
There are some humans
who feel that way.
They believe that their true
home lies underground.
That's why I decided
to assist them.
The only difference is where
they're forced to live.
Isn't what you're doing exactly the
same as what the Spiral King did?
Right, Simon?
Stop this self-justification. Anti-government
activities will be punished in a court of law.
You will have your say
at your trial.
My "trial"?
What's that?
A new piece of wisdom
that humanity has acquired.
Gimmy, take him away.
Rossiu. Why didn't you
tell me about this?
Did I issue any orders to find
and drag to the surface...
...people who want to
live underground?
You mustn't rise
to Viral's bait.
He's a holdout of
Lordgenome's old order.
Then is what he said
a lie?
No, it's the truth.
- Why, then?!
- It is for population verification.
If people live out of sight, we won't be
able to maintain an accurate census.
They could bring us over one million
without our knowing.
It is the government's responsibility
to prevent that!
If you will excuse me.
What would you
do then?!
If you found a millionth person,
would you exile him from the planet?!
That would be no different than what
went on back in Adai village!
You understand NOTHING.
Chief Advisor, we've been contacted
by the Spiral Power Research Institute.
Apparently, they were successful
in activating the bio-computer.
- I see.
- Congratulations, sir.
Your dream is finally
about to come true.
Yes. With this, we will be able
to learn this world's secrets.
Commander Simon, the council, the
citizens, they've all grown complacent!
You are the only thing keeping the
government running, Chief Advisor.
It's not just me.
There is also you,
the younger generation.
Gurren Lagann
Boota!
That's a good boy. You're one thing
that never changes around here.
Hello?
Kiyoh had her baby?!
That's right! A girl!
It's a girl!
Her name is Anne. It seems Dayakka had
been giving it some thought for a long time.
Sure.
That's wonderful.
I'll stop by the hospital later.
It's fine.
What's that?!
I'm sorry, Nia,
I'll call back later!
Hello? Simon?
Simon?
Huh? What's this?
Nia!
Huh?
Nia?
You didn't detect
the enemy's approach?
It appeared without warning
over Kamina City!
Almost as if it tore
a hole in the sky!
Grapearl Squadron status?
- Already launched!
- We'll engage the enemy momentarily.
It hasn't got a face...
I've never seen a mecha like this before.
Some new anti-government
guerilla weapon?
We are currently running a match
on the enemy machine's model.
Grapearl Squadron, prevent the
destruction of the city.
- Roger that!
- Roger!
All units, scatter! Attack simultaneously
from all directions!
- It absorbed them?
- I can't believe it...
In that case,
Grapearl Blade!
Contact lost with
Korza's Grapearl.
Handguns and blades
have no effect?
What're you doing, Rossiu?!
Gimmy!
I'm okay!
It's still working!
But we're down to just two
functioning units now...
Damn, it's tough...
If only we had our Gunmen...
...that thing would be a pushover!
Gunmen are relics of
the Spiral King's time.
They didn't fit in with the new era,
so we disposed of all of them.
The Grapearls are mass-produced,
combat-specialized units...
...based on our
Gurren Lagann research.
If the Grapearls are
no match for it,
...your old Gunmen couldn't
so much as scratch it.
Kinon? Um, your personality
has done a 180...
Darry! Don't be crazy!
I can still fight!
Darry!
Gurren Lagann...
We've been waiting
for ya, Simon!
It's too dangerous, Commander!
It is not your job to go out
and fight on the front lines!
How many times
do I have to tell you?!
Dumbass!
Protecting the city and the lives of
the citizens! THAT is our #1 job!
Has all this peace made
you soft, Rossiu?
But, sir--
Yeah, this is the one place
I can really be me.
Let's go,
you faceless bastard!
- GIGA DRILL BREAK!
- Why must you keep taking the easy way?
Is that model analysis
done yet?!
Team Dai-Gurren Resistance, Lordgenome
Army, New Government units...
There are no matches in
any of our databases!
Then where in the world
did it come from?
Commander! Give top priority
to identification!
- It didn't work!
- If possible, capture it!
Quit bugging me!
Like I have time to do that!
- Simon!
- Your drill, it's building up energy?
Here goes! I'm sick of you
and your light show!
I'm gonna take this crappy beam of yours
and shove it down your throat!
- Awesome!
- Did he do it?
No way...!
The city!
Dispatch fire and rescue crews to the city!
Keep the fire damage to a minimum!
What the hell
just happened?
He didn't know what it was, and yet he
charged in and counterattacked blindly,
...and he destroyed
the whole thing!
"Rash" doesn't even begin to describe
the Supreme Commander's actions!
Nia?
Is that Nia?
Attention, humans of Earth.
We Anti-Spiral races have
determined that humanity...
...has achieved Spiral Power
danger level two.
We hereby activate the
Humanity Extermination System.
To Be Continued...
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Nariyamanai kodou ga itsumo itazura ni kokoro ni tane wo maku
My ever-sounding heartbeat always idly sows a seed in my heart
Sono tane ga kibou no hana wo sakasu ka mo shirenai
That seed might bloom into a flower of hope
Dakara kou shite yume wo egaku koto ga dekirunda
That's how I can sketch my dreams like this
Bunansou na nukemichi ga ukande ha kieteku
A loophole that seems safe comes to mind, but then disappears
Sou yatte boku ha tamesarete dou yatte omoi todokeyou?
By doing that, I'm tested; how can I get my feelings across?
Mayowazu ni mae he susunde
Let's advance forward without hesitating
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Dakara kakko tsukenaide kitto hana ha saku hazu sa
So don't try to look cool; I'm sure our flowers have gotta bloom
Bokura ha kagayaku yo Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
We're gonna shine! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Next Time
When I was young, I had a dream. A dream
to know everything about the world.
When that dream comes true,
Simon, I will take you and--
Tell Me The Secrets of This World
Next time on
Gurren Lagann,
..."Tell Me The Secrets
of This World."