Gurren Lagann
Sugita kisetsu wo nageku hima ha nai
I don't have the time to lament the seasons that have passed
Nido to mayotte shimawanu you ni
So that I won't ever waver again
Kazoekirenai hon no sasayaka na
With countless, tiny little
Sonna koukai kakaeta mama
Regrets carried in my arms
Sono senaka dake oikakete koko made kitanda
I've come this far, having chased only after your back
Sagashite ita boku dake ni dekiru koto
It's something only I, who sought you, can do
Ano hi kureta kotoba ga ima demo
Those words you gave me that day, even now,
Kono mune ni tashika ni todoite iru kara
Definitely reach my heart
Kinou yori mo kyou ha bu ha boku no
I've realized my reason for having been born
Umarete kita wake ni kidzuite yuku
Today more than I did yesterday
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who blows
a hole in the fate of a universe...
...that is ruled by the endless
cycle of violence.
The Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren had
been swallowed up by a dark sea.
What saved them from being crushed
in this graveyard of Spiral warriors...
...was the flash of light given off
by the end of Kittan's life.
Kittan... I accept your last wish!
Our friend's hopes and dreams
are etched into its body...
Transforming the infinite darkness
into light!
Unmatched in heaven and Earth...
One machine, equal to the gods!
Super Galaxy Gurren Lagann!
We're gonna show you
the power...
...of the human race!
Episode 26:
Let's Go, Buddy
What's happening?
A powerful Spiral field is completely
neutralizing the enemy attacks!
Of course it is!
As if little pebbles like those
will work on us!
Gurren Boomerang!
Super Galaxy Mega Cutter!
That's Simon's power...?
Incredible...
Weren't you listening?
Those little things won't--
What happened?!
Unknown! Spiral field
is holding steady!
According to my monitor, the attack
is being blocked completely!
But they're hitting us!
Probability Alteration Missiles.
They are negating the probability
of us blocking their attack.
They can manipulate probability, too?
But that's God's domain...
What's that?
You would sacrifice one of your own
in order to go forward?
Such is the past karma
of the people of the Spiral.
And it is precisely because of that karma
that you must be destroyed.
Get real! As if we'd accept extinction
over a bunch of gibberish like that!
Then watch.
Watch where this universe
is headed.
See the universe destroyed
by the power of the Spiral,
...which thinks only
of evolving.
Spiral Power is the force which binds
together lifeforms and the universe.
The growth of galaxies is proportional
to the growth of life.
Life developed in search of forms
that would help it acquire...
...even more power
of the Spiral.
This is evolution.
But the end result would be a loss
of control over their Spiral Power,
...and all life becoming
its own galaxy.
These mega galaxies would then devour
each other, forming a black hole,
...and then this universe
would return to nothingness.
This is the Spiral Nemesis.
I don't believe it...
It can't be.
What's the matter, Simon?
He's bluffing!
How can you swallow
that garbage?!
Unfortunately, what he says
is the truth, Viral.
Those who use the power of the Spiral
know this better than anyone.
Simon has realized this
on an intuitive level.
He knows that the Anti-Spiral
speaks the truth.
However, there is
one other truth.
And that truth is that Nia is
out there waiting for you.
That she is hanging on so that the Spiral
races and Earth won't be annihilated.
Yeah. That's right.
You're exactly right!
What foolishness.
You would risk destroying the universe
for the sake of a fleeting emotion?
You're wrong!
I'll protect them both!
The girl! The universe!
Both of them!
I don't want fear of a tomorrow that might
never be to keep me from acting right now.
That's how Team Dai-Gurren rolls!
Enemy reading has disappeared!
Be careful. They will use a Random
Schrödinger Warp to sneak up on us.
Have a heart! Would you please talk
using words we can understand?!
They are manipulating multidimensional
probability fluctuations.
They will attack as they shift
up and down the time axis.
How is that any clearer?!
Who cares?!
Just cut loose!
Understood.
Preparing barrage against all possible
points along space and time axes.
I am tracing the enemy.
You mean the time range
can also be broadened?
Probability space where
enemy units exist:
Near past, -10.
Near future, +8.
Enemy units detected!
Count, off the charts!
Will the main cannon work?
Leave that to us!
I don't care about all
that probability stuff,
...I say we teach 'em a lesson in
how stubborn Team Dai-Gurren is!
The lady's right!
Maelstrom Cannon,
ready to fire!
Mega Vortex Cannon,
standing by!
The gauge is saying something
about a "Planck Time Coefficient"...
Ignore it! Just lock
onto the targets!
It means it's determined the probability
change and will get a bulls-eye!
All right, let's do it! Let's punch holes
in the past and future all at once!
Well, how about that?
There's so much power in our engine
that it's like a galaxy's about to be born!
They can't run or hide
from us anymore.
Simon, I know you've been
hanging in there for a long time.
So don't worry about us, and
cut loose as much as you want!
I'll take you up
on that!
SUPER GALAXY...
...GIGA DRILL BREAK!
- Nia!
- The interference from the fake is gone.
We can jump straight to where
the real Nia is this time.
Right.
I see her!
Simon...
What the--?
You see beauty in struggling
to the bitter end.
This must be instinctive to those
bewitched by the power of the Spiral...
Nevertheless, that is an act which has
been repeated time and time again.
Now, follow the same fate as
all those Spiral warriors...
...who came before you!
What the--?
Gurren Lagann
Digging tunnels.
Day after day, that's my job.
When yesterday was, or where tomorrow is,
it's got nothing to do with me.
How's it coming, Simon?
Just a little further, Bro.
I'm counting on ya, Simon.
Your drill is the only thing I CAN count on.
This is awesome!
That went off without
a hitch, Simon!
Can you believe this?
With this much loot, we'll be able
to live the high life for a while!
Here ya go!
C'mon, don't be shy!
This is your cut,
blood brother!
Sure.
Well? Wasn't it a good idea
to get out of Giha Village?
We're still underground, but we can
live like kings here under the Capital!
Yeah!
We'll never have it as good as the Beastmen,
but stealing their valuables in secret...
...sure makes our lives here
pretty comfy.
You dig, I steal.
Here's to a long partnership, Simon!
Sure thing, Bro!
- I will go down with the ship.
- Captain!
You are worth far more
than jewels to me--
Dishes get clean and--
Have a taste of our ray guns!
We interrupt our regular programming to
bring you news of a crime in progress.
A bank robber is on the run in Siton
Region, firing wildly as he goes.
I want money!
I want food!
Hurry it up!
We now have footage
from the scene!
Why, that's... It's that mysterious,
elusive bounty hunter!
She calls herself Yoko Littner!
Come on!
Everything's okay now.
- Thank you!
- Thanks a lot, lady!
Don't mention it.
What's this?
What in the world is happening?
- It can't be!
- Oh, but it is.
It is exactly as you suspect,
Lordgenome.
They are all being held prisoner
in extradimensional space.
They are trapped in
a series of universes...
...that are created instant to instant
as they are perceived.
So long as they have intelligence,
they will never be able to break free.
So, you are the Anti-Spiral?
Yes. I am.
So, a man once renowned throughout
the galaxy as a Spiral warrior...
...is now reduced
to a biocomputer?
I see that your companions
will also take any action...
...they deem necessary
to achieve their aims.
Even so, I was defeated
by you.
I failed to protect
the galaxy.
If it weren't for them, I wouldn't have
been able to face you directly in battle.
You came all the way here
to the space between...
...the 10th and 11th dimensions
so that we could finish you?
So, that is what
this is about.
I must say, you are being
oddly considerate.
TOO considerate, one might say.
Why in the world would you employ
such elaborate, indirect methods?
If you fought with all your might,
exterminating us Spiral races...
...would be a trivial matter.
We detected an unknown
source of Spiral Power.
Gaps in our analysis could
potentially ruin everything.
What?
The unusual Spiral Power source
we detected, it was you?
It took humanoid form?
Ah, I see...
You converted your individual growth
energy into species evolution energy?
But it should not be possible
for an individual...
...to undergo such an
extreme transformation.
It's all because of your
Spiral Power, Lordgenome.
My power... did this?
Get back, Anti-Spiral!
I won't let you lay
a hand on Simon!
You have shown me a most
interesting phenomenon.
But evolving was a mistake.
Wait a minute, this is--
The instant extradimensional space
is perceived, it is made real.
Taking human form
means that you have...
...trapped yourself in the labyrinth
of extradimensional space.
Simon...
The last of the gaps
have now been filled in.
You will never generate
Spiral Power again.
You are finished.
We're sorry! What we did was wrong!
Forgive us!
Okay? Look, I'm on
my knees!
Have mercy on us!
What we did was wrong!
We'll do whatever you say! If you say
to bow a million times, we'll do it!
We're sorry, we're sorry,
we're sorry, we're sorry!
So please, don't kill us!
Just spare our lives!
What's the matter, Simon?
You lose your drill?
There's another Bro...
Dumbass!
The bad reputation of Team Gurren
echoes far and wide in Giha Village!
Its badass leader is a man of indomitable
spirit, a paragon of masculinity!
As if there could be more than one
of the mighty Kamina!
But there's two of you here.
Exactly! Pick the one
you prefer.
But that's crazy!
Don't you remember? You were the one
who was the method to my madness!
The one who made my big talk
more than words!
Your drill oughta be totally different
from that pebble over there.
I'm sorry! Forgive me!
Your drill is right here.
You can't keep wasting time
in here forever!
What's that drill of yours
meant to do?
Bro?
Is it really you?
Hey, what are you doing?!
Start bowing, too!
Bow and beg and scrape...
...and pretend to apologize to
get them to turn a blind eye!
...and we'll
get through this!
My...
...and we'll
get through this!
My...
If they let us go, we can always
come up with something else!
Look, just keep your
head down and apologize!
My drill is...
My drill...
...is the drill that's gonna
pierce the heavens!
My drill is my soul.
Get going, Simon.
Don't let the what-if's, maybe's
and if-only's distract you.
The one thing that you chose yourself,
THAT is the truth of your universe.
Yeah. You're right.
That's exactly right.
Don't forget. My universe is
the universe that's in here.
Bro...
It's not just me.
It's these bozos, too.
Whoa, when the hell did
you get taller than me?
Wow, you're right!
Time for me to leave, Bro.
Yeah.
This time it's really goodbye.
Get going, blood brother.
This isn't goodbye.
You're always with me, right?
Yeah!
Let's go, buddy!
- Teach!
- Thanks, Teach!
- Miss Yomako!
I-I'm not...
Your teacher is a much
finer lady than her.
The winner of this year's
Miss Littner pageant is Yoko!
It's time for Yoko, the best shot
in the galaxy, to take her turn!
She demonstrated absolutely flawless
technique in the preliminary round!
That dress looks
wonderful on you.
Thanks.
Well, I'm off.
Here, Daddy...
Oh, now I get it.
I was having
a sappy dream, too.
Your actions are baffling, Irregular.
Why do you resist me so?
He will come.
You can be sure of that.
You appear to have been tainted
by the power of the Spiral...
...and given a strange sort
of self-awareness.
However, the time left to you
has now run out.
Simon!
Sorry I kept you waiting, Nia!
To Be Continued...
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Nariyamanai kodou ga itsumo itazura ni kokoro ni tane wo maku
My ever-sounding heartbeat always idly sows a seed in my heart
Sono tane ga kibou no hana wo sakasu ka mo shirenai
That seed might bloom into a flower of hope
Dakara kou shite yume wo egaku koto ga dekirunda
That's how I can sketch my dreams like this
Bunansou na nukemichi ga ukande ha kieteku
A loophole that seems safe comes to mind, but then disappears
Sou yatte boku ha tamesarete dou yatte omoi todokeyou?
By doing that, I'm tested; how can I get my feelings across?
Mayowazu ni mae he susunde
Let's advance forward without hesitating
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Dakara kakko tsukenaide kitto hana ha saku hazu sa
So don't try to look cool; I'm sure our flowers have gotta bloom
Bokura ha kagayaku yo Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
We're gonna shine! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Next Time
This is the enormous tale
of a tiny man...
...from a tiny blue planet
on the edge of a whirling galaxy.
If you were to tell it in full,
the sun would rise before you finish.
The Lights In The Sky Are Stars
Next week,
the series finale.
"The Lights In The Sky
Are Stars."