Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who continues
to fight against fate.
This man lived a life of desire,
loyalty, and extravagance,
...he loved his companions,
and he strove for freedom.
And then, abruptly, he died.
But even so, Simon lives on.
He must go on living.
Teppelin, Royal Capital
Audience Chamber
Spiral King Lordgenome
Thymilph has died, has he?
Yes, Majesty. Reports also say
that Dai-Gunzan was stolen.
Cytomander, the Swift
One of the Four Generals, killed...
He must have gotten careless.
Guame, the Immovable
Let us not forget the saying
that even an armadillo...
...will turn and fight when cornered.
In other words, one must never
underestimate one's opponent.
Adiane, the Elegant
What nonsense.
If a lowly armadillo did turn and fight,
all one need do is crush it.
You don't understand the finer
subtleties of this world, I see.
You forget that we are in the
presence of the Spiral King.
Spiral King.
I ask that the honor of retaking Dai-Gunzan
be given to me, Cytomander, the Swift.
No, that mission
must surely go to me.
Thymilph was a dear friend to me.
Grant me the opportunity to
avenge his death, Spiral King.
A dear friend, eh?
Indeed. There is such a thing as
friendship that knows no gender.
In other words, he was useful
to your ends.
Hold your tongue, anteater.
I created you,
yet you suggest...
...that you know a friendship
that I am unaware of?
As you wish.
Go, Adiane.
Thank you, Sire.
Adiane, the Elegant, shall give
these humans a lesson...
...in the power and terror
of the Spiral King.
You do not approve, Cytomander?
Spiral King, you are the immortal
creator of this world,
...and the monarch who rules
over all within it.
I haven't the slightest intention
of defying your decisions.
In that case, leave me.
Yes, Sire.
Sire.
They seek out the light, even
though only death awaits them.
It is enough to
make me despair...
...at the nature of these
creatures called humans.
Okay, let's end this!
- Back off.
- What?
I'll do it.
Episode 9:
What, Exactly, Is A Human?
Boy, it's really pouring...
It's been seven days now.
I still can't believe it.
Yeah...
What's wrong?
There's not enough engine output.
It refuses to stabilize.
That hurt!
Are you all right?
I'm fine, I'm fine.
That was a good hit, Rossiu.
I'm really sorry! I can't seem to get
the hang of power distribution.
That was impressive, Rossiu!
Dayakka? Leeron?
Are you going to the
engine room again?
Dai-Gurren here is a
temperamental fellow.
Dai-Gurren, huh?
Yoko insisted that we
give it that name.
I see.
It has a repair factory, and its living
quarters are fully equipped.
Now, if only we could get the
main engine stabilized...
Even Gurren is as good as new
after that pounding it took.
It's one hell of a facility,
that's for sure.
Simon, get your act together!
The only thing it can't mend
is a broken human heart.
You're not the only one aboard, you know!
Gurren Lagann is all about teamwork!
Nobody asked you to pilot it.
Say what? So, you're saying that you
can pilot it all by yourself?
I'll do it by myself.
That's a good idea.
Actually, that's for the best.
Don't get too full
of yourself, kid!
If you'd have held it together,
Kamina wouldn't be dead now!
Big brother!
I'm sorry, Simon.
It's okay.
What Kittan said is true.
I killed Kamina.
So I'll get tougher.
I HAVE to get tough.
I'll fight hard enough
for both me AND Kamina.
Rossiu, why didn't that god of yours
save Kamina?
That's right, I forgot. The god
you pray to is a Gunmen.
No wonder he died. After all,
it was a god that killed him!
Simon.
I'm sorry.
That was uncalled for.
Sorry, Boota.
I'm exhausted.
Bro...
It's gotta be Kittan or nobody.
Yeah, he's the one who called us
all together in the first place.
Simon's just too unreliable.
He's too damn mopey.
Just because he can pilot Lagann
doesn't mean he should be leader.
If an obnoxious kid like him is made
leader, Team Gurren is history.
DAI-Gurren.
It's not Team Gurren.
It's Team DAI-Gurren now!
Don't eat yourself sick.
I need to keep up my energy. I can't
even use a rifle properly, remember?
The Four Generals, the Spiral King,
we've still got lots of enemies out there.
The war goes on.
Yeah, you have a point.
So does this rain...
Even with the rain, I can have a hot meal
right after target practice now.
Seven days ago, I never
would have imagined it.
And it's all thanks to him.
Look, about Simon...
He seems like he's
getting worn down.
Oh.
Aren't you worried
about him?
Keda. Kaia.
Mycee. Nashika.
We sure lost a lot of people
defending Littner, didn't we?
Yeah.
Sacrifices are necessary
for survival.
And we survivors work even harder
to make sure they weren't in vain.
I've always accepted that
as part of what we do.
But this time,
I don't think I can.
I'm sorry, it's all I can do
to keep myself together.
You said you'd repay that kiss
ten times over.
What's the big idea, leaving a hole
in my heart that's ten times bigger?
Kamina, you jerk...
Gunmen detected! They're closing in
from off the starboard bow!
I despise persistent types...
Leeron!
I'll combine Lagann with Gurren and
head out. I'll be fine on my own.
I'll pilot Gurren.
Rossiu?
I mean, you can't do it by yourself, right?
Go on, combine.
Yeah, all right...
Simon!
This is overkill!
He who strikes first wins!
It's what Kamina would have done!
Power output is unstable!
Bastard! Bastard! Bastard!
Bastard! Bastard! Bast--
Keep it together!
Kamina never screamed, not once!
Simon, you have to calm down!
If you keep fighting like this,
YOU will die this time!
Kamina wouldn't run away!
Not Kamina! Not ever!
What's wrong, Simon?
The energy is feeding back?
T-The drill!
Come back here, damn you!
Rossiu!
Are you all right?
What happened, Rossiu?
Lagann suddenly separated,
and then it--
It fell down this?
He abandoned you and ran
in the face of the enemy?
It seemed like Lagann
had gone berserk.
Gone berserk?
Seriously?
I think.
Simon...
Gurren Lagann
Why did the controls
stop responding?
It started!
Hail fellow well met!
H-Hail fellow...?
Who are you, good sir?
"Good sir"? Um, I'm nobody important
enough to be called that.
Oh! This is the outside,
isn't it?
This is rain!
It is cold.
What is this?
Um, that's dirt.
Are you okay without any shoes?
It's cold and wet and squishy...
It feels wonderful!
Really? It does?
Why are you the same as I am?
You have no tail,
nor fangs or scales.
Your skin is soft, as well.
Well, that's only natural.
I'm a human being.
"Human being"?
Right. A human being.
A human. A person.
And what, exactly,
is a human?
Huh? Well, a human is...
Well, like you and me.
We look like this, we have
a head, stuff like that.
There are others like us?
Sure. There are more.
Really? And all of them
are the same as you?
They have the same face?
No, we're not all identical. It would be
creepy if everyone had the same face.
It would?
Oh, the rain has stopped!
Hey, you're right.
I wonder why I am outside?
Um, I don't really know.
First things first, though,
we need to get out of here.
Here.
You can't walk like that.
Here, put these on.
All right.
My name is Nia.
What is yours?
Who, me?
I'm Simon.
Simon...
What a fine name.
Thanks.
Tell me, Simon.
What?
What is that?
Hurry! This way!
Simon, what is that?
It's a Gunmen! Humans on the surface
are at war against them!
At war?
If we don't fight them,
they'll kill us!
Please, Lagann!
It worked!
Simon, are you all right?
Damn it, not again!
Why? Why won't you do
as I tell you, Lagann?!
Run, Nia!
Once you start, keep running
and don't look back.
I'll keep the Gunmen
busy here.
But you--
I'm sick of it! I'm sick
of watching people die!
I don't care what happens to me,
just so long as no one else dies!
Do you really want to die?
If you are frightened, you should run.
You mustn't die.
No, I'm not scared.
You mustn't lie, either.
Come, let's escape.
Together.
I'm not gonna let anyone else die!
I'm here, too!
Kittan Stinger!
Hell's Headsplitter!!
I finally got a chance to use it!
First he deserts, and now he's
got a woman on his arm?
Some are slender,
some are fat,
...some are rounded,
and some are angular.
Human beings certainly come in all
shapes and sizes, don't they?
So you've never seen another
human being before, have you?
No. Only my honorable father.
Honorable father, she says...
Thank you.
What's Old Coco doing here?
It's delicious!
So when you woke up, you'd been
locked in that container...
...and thrown into that gorge
for some reason?
Yes.
Do you remember any details
about where your village is?
Village?
Where your house is.
I have no idea.
I've never been outside before.
Father always said that
the outside world was dangerous.
Well, he was right about that.
I bet your father is worried about you.
I'm not so sure.
Well, I believe I may
have angered him.
Why's that?
I asked him a question.
"Why was I born?" I asked.
As soon as I said it,
Father closed his heart to me.
I don't get it.
Your father sounds like
an odd man.
Lagann... Are you going
to abandon me, too?
What the hell do you
want me to do, damn it?!
Can't I even avenge
Kamina's death?!
Yoko.
Don't do it. Nothing you say
can help him right now.
You'll only make the hole
in his heart bigger.
What happened?!
What's going on?
Where's this water coming from?!
Wait a minute, something's coming!
What is it?
It's huge...
Simon! Where's Simon?!
Where's Gurren Lagann?
There's no escape, human scum.
I know that voice...
Fire main cannon!
They're still being calibrated!
Rossiu!
I know!
I'll go out in Gurren!
Nia?
Wha--? That idiot, is she trying
to get herself killed?
Stop this, Adiane!
What?
Wait, is that--?
First Princess Nia, daughter of
Spiral King Lordgenome, orders you!
Leave us, Adiane, the Elegant!
Are you aware of who I am?
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
Precious memories...
Do they tie people down?
Or are they what saves them?
Next time on Gurren Lagann,
Who Is This Bro?
..."Who Is This Bro?"