Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who has yet
to realize what his destiny is.
Simon and Kamina live in
an underground village.
But with the sudden appearance
of a Gunmen, a gigantic mecha,
...and Yoko, a beautiful woman who
fires wildly with a superconducting rifle,
...their daily routine is shattered.
They attack and destroy
the enemy robot.
The momentum of the attack carries
the trio up to the surface, but then...
Episode 2:
I Said I'm Gonna Pilot That Thing!!
Ambushing people
is playing dirty!
Sorry, I forgot to tell you!
These guys were up here
this whole time!
Say what?
Three of them jumped me
at once!
The one that fell into your village
was one of them!
So what you're saying is, there's
lots of these things up here?!
That's for sure, the place
is crawling with them!
- Glad to hear it!
- I hate this!
What do you think
you're doing, Simon?
I'm leaving! I'm going back down!
I'm going back to our village!
Don't lose your
nerve now, Simon!
You did such a great job fighting
them earlier, remember?
That was just a fluke!
I'll handle it, then!
Open the hatch!
Listen up, you walking faces!
Having left his homeland, he never yields,
never retreats, and never regrets!
Never retreat! Never look back!
Male tenacity is all about the never's!
The great Kamina of Team Gurren
is gonna take you on!
You have been warned!
Huh?
You could've been killed, seriously!
How long are you gonna
keep running, Simon?
We finally made it
to the surface.
Now's the time to cast off
the boy you used to be.
It's now or never.
Hold us steady, Simon!
This is terrifying, Bro!
Hold us steady, I said!
Sheesh!
Um, hello?
We're falling.
What's wrong, Simon?
It's not working!
Why not?
I don't know!
I can't do this anymore!
You do it, Bro!
Simon! You--
Save the family squabbles
for later!
You okay, Yoko?
Dayakka!
Friends of yours?
Yeah!
Concentrate your fire
on the one in front!
Something jumped out!
Keep your heads down!
Aw, my Gunmen...
It's almost sunset.
We're pulling out.
I'll remember this, you stinking humans!
We'll pick this up tomorrow!
Show no mercy!
FIRE!
Hot, hot, hot!
You'll rue this day!
That's what was inside
those things?
Beastmen. They're what
pilot the Gunmen.
Every day, they show up
when the sun rises...
...and leave again
when the sun sets.
How come?
I have no idea!
You've been fighting those things
your whole life?
That's right!
I'll fill you in on
all the details later.
You did good today, Simon.
It's hopeless...
I can't do this.
Whenever my ass is in trouble,
you're always the one who saves it.
Thanks a lot.
Oh, my!
What's this darling little fellow?
He's a handsome devil, isn't he?
I didn't mean you,
I meant this mecha.
Mecha?
You know, this one
is just my type!
What're you doing, Leeron?
Hurry up and help me strip this thing.
Sure, I'm coming!
See you later, hon.
They've got all kinds up here
on the surface, looks like.
I finally made it, Dad.
Never mind. This sight is
something else, ain't it?
The surface sure is different,
isn't it?
That huge, round light,
and all them itty bitty lights...
This place is full of lights
even at night.
This is way better than the
pitch-black nights down in the pit.
Yep. Coming up here
was the right call.
The big light is the moon.
The "itty bitty" ones are called stars.
That's what people called them,
way back in the past.
The moon and stars, huh?
Pretty simple names, ain't they?
I wonder why they had names?
If they have names, maybe that means
that people in the past...
...used to look up at the lights
in the sky all the time.
My goodness, you're not just
a pretty face, are you, hon?
This mecha is fascinating!
It may be small, but it's
packing a lot of power.
What're you doing?
Running some numbers.
Are you interested?
A machine that makes
squiggly lines?
Oh, you don't know
how to read?
Read? Do you know how
to do that, Bro?
Nope.
Wow, what bumpkins...
You aren't exactly a bookworm
yourself, missy.
I can read just fine,
thank you very much!
This one is "stars,"
and this one is "moon"!
It's possible that long, long ago,
people used to live on the surface.
Really?
Some records say they did,
and others say that they didn't.
Which is it?
It's like how I'm both and
neither a man nor a woman.
Who cares?
Who ARE you, anyway?
I'm Leeron, but you
can call me Ron.
- Or "Beautiful Queen," if you like.
- I'd rather die!
You'd never guess it, but Ron here
knows just about everything.
He also handles all of our
weapons-related maintenance.
- YOU do that?
- You find that strange?
Fine, put my dexterity to the test.
Who knows, you might enjoy it.
You die.
Now, now...
So anyway, there's a favor
that I'd like to ask you.
Would you mind carrying
that for me?
But...
What do you have there?
It's kinda pretty.
See, it works after all!
Over here!
What, it responds
to male spirit?
Fascinating...
Keep your mitts off
of Simon, got it?
How about you, then?
You die!
Ladies don't care much for
men who can't take a joke.
I'm really sorry about this.
Your village was damaged
because we screwed up,
...and now we're making you
carry stuff.
It's because resources are scarce.
We have to use every scrap we find.
What's wrong?
What the hell is that?
Someone who was killed
by Gunmen.
Around here, it's not exactly
a rare occurrence.
That should do it.
Yeah, we couldn't leave
his bones lying there.
Pathetic.
It's a waste of time to dig graves for
people who die out in this empty dump.
Look, there's no telling when
we'll be the ones lying there.
Never!
Our journey will continue until we pierce
the heavens! As far as it takes!
Huh?
This place isn't the happy wonderland
you seem to think it is.
We ourselves don't
live here by choice.
You don't?
Our Littner was once an
underground village like yours.
But there was an accident,
and it became uninhabitable.
We had no choice but
to come to surface,
...and when we did, those
Gunmen were waiting for us.
We have nowhere to return to,
so our only choice is to fight.
Sounds nice! That's exactly the
sort of world I was looking for.
It's no wonder they're exhausted.
It's been a day full of firsts for them.
Gurren Lagann
Look at that, kiddo! This is "up"!
This is the surface!
There's nothing here...
Nope, not a thing.
That's why I like it.
There are no walls and no ceiling.
This is truly a man's world.
Ready to go?
I see...
When you're ready,
come up and join me.
Until then!
Goodbye for now, Kamina!
What the hell?
- C'mon, Simon!
- Hey, wait for me, Bro!
- What was that?!
- What just happened?!
Good morning.
What the hell was that?!
Mornings on the surface
start with Gunmen.
Care for some morning coffee?
What's that? Dirty water?
Here comes another one.
Ow, that's hot!
That's--
Two days in a row,
that's pretty rough.
There's usually a longer gap
between raids.
Maybe this is payback
for yesterday.
Whatever the reason,
we gotta fight 'em!
Keep your opinions to yourself, please.
Can you use a gun?
Don't look down on me, missy!
Who the hell do you think I am?
Bro...
Simon, you're in Lagann.
No, you pilot it, Bro. I bet
you'd do a better job than--
No, that thing belongs to you.
But I'm not--
We're counting on you!
Don't let them get near the camp!
Split into two teams and hold them off!
Come on, your place
is over here!
This is--
I was up all night polishing it.
What do we say?
Um... Thank you.
All right, hop in!
Give the Spin On order
to your Core Drill.
What's "Spin On"?
When you screw it in!
Give it a hard, manly twist!
O-Okay...
Uh-oh.
Problems again, dear?
All right, you uppity
human filth!
We're gonna take out
the trash this morning!
Listen to 'em talk...
Let's get started, people.
- Another one's coming?
- Another?
You might want to
cover your ears.
One, two, one, two,
one, two...
W-What the hell?
These tremors!
One, two, one, two,
one, two...
It was them!
They caused them!
All those earthquakes
were their fault!
It's because of them that
my mom and dad are--
That's a big one...
I haven't seen
that one before.
I like the face on that one.
Now!
What was that?
We lined the top of the cliff
with explosives.
That worked beautifully.
Geez, those things
are tough!
That's fine by me!
That thing is giving me chills!
That settles it!
I'm gonna take that Gunmen!
What in the world are
you talking about?
I SAID, I'm gonna pilot
that thing!
Hello? You listening?
Those Beastmen or whatever
are piloting them now, right?
There's no way in hell
that I can't do it, too!
I have no idea where his
confidence comes from.
Screw you! For a man, what matters
is deeds, not words!
I'm a woman!
Bro!
You got here just in time,
blood brother!
What is that guy thinking?
Bro, it was them!
The tremors they cause up here
end up as earthquakes down below!
Oh, that's what they were!
These guys killed
my mom and dad!
Simon, I'm glad to see you worked up!
But don't be impatient.
To win a fight, it's vital to have
burning passion, but a cool head!
Listen up, I'm gonna help myself
to that pointy one.
I'm betting that I can get inside
through the face in its belly.
I need you to
force it open for me.
But can you operate it?
How did you know how
to operate Lagann?
It's like the knowledge came flowing
into me when I grabbed these.
That's what I'll do, then!
It means that fighting spirit
is the important thing!
Um, I think there might
be more than that...
Whatever, just take us in!
I'm not sensing
a cool head here!
S-Sorry!
Good grief, why do I have to keep
providing backup for that moron?
Oopsie daisy!
That body gives me chills
every time I look at it!
What the--?
Get off his head, human!
Simon!
You won't lay a hand
on my brother!
Give me a minute, Bro!
Get out, I'm taking over.
Oh, yeah! It's all about
the fighting spirit!
Commander Guzack
has been killed!
Stinking humans!
You'll pay for this!
I'm not dead yet,
you two idiots!
How dare you kill
Squad Leader Guzack!
This is for
the commander!
Bro!
I'm sending you to the afterlife,
too, pipsqueak!
Crap, what's slowing you down, Kamina?
Let's see some more spirit!
Don't screw with me,
you Gunmen bastards!
Who the hell do you
think I am?!
It's all over for you, runt!
"Who The Hell Do You
Think I Am" Kick!
"Hands Off My Beloved
Little Brother" Punch!
Simon!
Pull it together, Simon!
B-Bro...?
Sorry 'bout that. Got a little
held up back there.
Let's take 'em down together!
Wait, what?
You deliver the final blow!
Put some backbone into it, Simon!
Chew on this!
Finishing move!
Perfect Combustion of Manly Souls!
Cannonball Attack!
This is so messed up!
Ha! You missed!
Oh? Did we?
I guess I have to do it!
Neener neen--
T-They've all
been destroyed!
Talk about overkill...
But you have to admit,
it was pretty cool.
You have a weakness
for his type, huh?
How long have you been
standing there?
I must admit, I'm surprised.
Hijacking a Gunmen isn't something
that ever occurred to us.
Those two certainly are amusing.
Give me a break, Bro...
I've decided.
I'm naming this Gurren.
No matter how unforgiving this place
may be, we'll fight our way through!
Me in my Gurren,
and you in your Lagann!
Wait for me, Dad...
Sorry, I didn't mean to wake
you up from your sleep.
I guess I got a little wild this afternoon,
but don't hold it against me, okay?
No way...
It can't be!
It isn't possible!
Dad...
You bought it out here?
You didn't wait...
You died too soon...
Dad!
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
This face I show to the world
is the only billboard I need!
What sort of face has the gall to pick a fight
with a man of such a noble sentiment?!
Who Do You Think You Are,
Having Two Faces!!
Next time on
Gurren Lagann,
..."Who Do You Think You Are,
Having Two Faces!!"