Gurren Lagann
Sugita kisetsu wo nageku hima ha nai
I don't have the time to lament the seasons that have passed
Nido to mayotte shimawanu you ni
So that I won't ever waver again
Kazoekirenai hon no sasayaka na
With countless, tiny little
Sonna koukai kakaeta mama
Regrets carried in my arms
Sono senaka dake oikakete koko made kitanda
I've come this far, having chased only after your back
Sagashite ita boku dake ni dekiru koto
It's something only I, who sought you, can do
Ano hi kureta kotoba ga ima demo
Those words you gave me that day, even now,
Kono mune ni tashika ni todoite iru kara
Definitely reach my heart
Kinou yori mo kyou ha bu ha boku no
I've realized my reason for having been born
Umarete kita wake ni kidzuite yuku
Today more than I did yesterday
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who continues
to look for his own path,
...even while he is being
betrayed by fate.
Simon is thrown into prison
as a war criminal.
What he finds waiting for him there
is Viral, his former enemy.
Elsewhere, Rossiu is informed
that the moon's impact...
...will deal a fatal blow
to the Earth.
Amidst the battle, the Arc-Gurren abandons
a great many people as it lifts off.
But Nia, who has become the Anti-Spiral's
messenger, says the following:
Even if they do escape into space,
all that awaits them there is despair.
What?
I don't see you for a while, and you
go and turn into a boring bitch...
...Nia.
Surrender to the inevitable.
Humanity has no future.
Hey, wait!
How many were we able
to bring aboard?
We have confirmation
of 176,800 people.
Less than half of what
we'd planned...
Enemies detected!
Two Mugann! Huge ones!
No!
This was a trap all along?
Episode 21:
You Are Someone Who Ought To Survive
One Year Earlier
- Give it back!
- If you don't like it, take it back!
You're such a baby, Nakim!
- Let's go!
- We're late, we're late!
You're hopeless, Nakim.
C'mon, get up.
Wait.
You can get up
by yourself, right?
That's better, young man.
I'd like to introduce your
new teacher to you.
I hear she's from the mainland!
She's a babe!
Really? I don't think
she's all that pretty.
She's our teacher...
I'm Yomako. I hope we all
become good friends.
I'm terribly sorry about
all the junk in here.
It used to be a night guard hut,
so at least it's livable.
Thank you for everything.
We call this a school,
but I'm the only staffer,
...so it's a big relief to have
some new blood hereabouts.
I see.
Still, why would someone as famous as you
want to come to our little island?
Are you sure that you don't have
me mistaken for someone else?
I'm just Yomako, an ordinary
new teacher.
Yes, yes, of course.
We old-timers tend to blurt things out.
'Bye, Teach!
Goodbye!
Those children are the first
to be born on the surface.
I want to make sure that someone
watches over them.
Yes, I don't want them to have
a life without the sky.
What?
Let me have a look!
Forget it!
Here we go!
One, two, three, four!
Quit being so fussy!
Miss Yomako!
Until six years ago, human beings
lived their whole lives underground.
The two who set us all free
were Kamina... and Simon.
The two great heroes.
Hey, that's--
This is the Teach!
Come on, that's not--
No chatting in class.
You know that.
How come I'm being
punished, too?
Good morning!
Good morning, every--
Just ignore it. If you let them get to you,
it'll just make it worse.
This is a lie!
A big, fat lie!
My bag! Who the heck
put it up there?!
Quit your bawling!
It's just a stupid bag!
I got that bag from my late dad!
It's all I have to remember him by!
Go get it yourself!
No, don't!
I'll get it for--
Fine, then!
I'll go get it!
- What're you saying?
- Don't! It's too dangerous!
Maosha?
Teach!
It's Nakim, he's--
- Nakim!
- Don't call out to him!
He'll be in even greater danger
if he loses his concentration.
But why in the world is he--
That bag is a memento
from his father.
Three years ago, Nakim came here to
this island, where his mother was born,
...but he's never really fit in.
Got it!
Don't look down!
Would you look at that!
Teach...
Boy, that was crazy.
I know, but my dad
gave me this.
I hate this island because
Dad isn't here.
But I DO think this view
is really pretty.
You know, I saw a view
like this once before.
I was with a boy who
was a lot like you.
Like me?
I also made a whole bunch
of new friends.
We did all kinds of things, always
working hard for a better tomorrow.
There were also some people
who died, though.
I think you should remember
your father as best you can.
Hold onto him tight
in your heart.
Hey!
Hey, Nakim!
You okay up there?
Do you hate everyone here?
Nakim!
That was awesome, man!
You climbed this huge tree
all by yourself!
We can't just call you Nakim now!
You're Nakim the Tree-climber!
Nakim the Tree-climber!
Thanks.
The Spiral Nemesis will bring about
this universe's destruction.
We Anti-Spiral exist to
prevent that event.
Having passed one million,
...humans will become a power
that will be a threat to our own.
And so, we will destroy you
before that can happen.
That's what the Humanity Annihilation
System is? That mecha earlier?
In three weeks' time, the moon will
leave its orbit and impact the Earth.
And that will be
the end of it.
In response, the New Government pressed
charges against former Commander Simon.
As a result of his trial today,
he was sentenced to death.
Citizens will be evacuated to 36 giant
underground shelters around the world.
- Teach!
- It's all right.
Residents in the Kamina city area,
which has no shelter,
Let's believe in the
New Government.
Residents in the Kamina city area,
which has no shelter,
...will temporarily leave the stratosphere
in the Superdreadnought Space Dai-Gun.
What are those
guys doing?!
...will temporarily leave the stratosphere
in the Superdreadnought Space Dai-Gun.
Listen, everyone! A Gun-boat will
be here in an hour to evacuate us.
Make sure you haven't
forgotten anything.
Miss Yomako!
It's our Maosha!
We can't find our
Maosha anywhere!
I'll go look for her, Teach!
No, you stay here.
I bet Maosha's up
in the lighthouse!
Whenever anything bad happens,
she runs up there and cries.
I can't go...
I'm a big, fat liar...
I can't go with Nakim!
Those footsteps sound like a--
Listen up, islanders!
Can you hear me?
If this kid's life means anything to you,
hand over all the food on the island!
Maosha!
What good will this do you?
If you don't run and hide,
the moon will fall on you!
We're already wanted men!
We'd just get arrested
if we went to a shelter,
...so it'd be smarter to load up our Gunmen
with supplies and hide out someplace!
Do you care what happens
to this kid?
You're dead meat!
Stop it!
They'll pay.
Gurren Lagann
What's the matter?
If you don't hand over your food,
this kid is a goner!
Maosha!
Maosha's gonna get eaten!
What's that?
What's going on?
Maosha!
- Oh, Maosha!
- Maosha!
Miss... Yomako?
Stay back, kids.
I knew it! She's the same as
this picture in our textbook!
Who the hell are you?
I'm a teacher.
Don't make me laugh!
Look at what you did to my bro!
This will be on the test,
so pay close attention.
You don't wreck buildings.
You don't take children hostage.
You don't threaten people
with violence.
Here endeth the lesson.
You fail.
I'm sorry, I was the one
who put your bag up there...
I'm a really good
tree climber,
...so I thought I'd blame it on Kunpa and
his friends, and if I got it for you, you'd--
Maosha...
I didn't know how much
the bag meant to you...
Nakim, I'm sorry...
Let's all run away
together, Maosha.
Nakim...
I have a message?
Yoko, I'd like you to return to Kamina City
as soon as you hear this.
Please come aboard the Arc-Gurren.
The surface is going to be destroyed.
You are someone who
ought to survive!
Please!
Contact me immediately!
- Please! Contact me immediately!
- So, this is your "politics," huh?
What a joke!
- Teach!
- Miss Yomako!
Are you leaving, Miss Yomako?
I knew it,
you're really Yoko!
No, I'll always be
your Miss Yomako.
Yeah! You're Korehana Island's
Miss Yomako!
- Teach!
- Miss Yomako!
I'll go get it back for you. The pure
blue sky you kids love so much.
As soon as I get back, I'll need to
hand out your report cards, won't I?
We'll be waiting for you!
That's a promise, Teach!
Goodbye!
Teach!
Crap, there's no end
to these things!
Working hard as usual, Kittan!
What? Yoko?
Yoko, is that you?
Where's Simon?
He's still in that
prison down there!
Then I'll leave our "friends"
back there to you!
Hey, wait a minute!
Bitch! You show up out of nowhere
and steal the rescue for yourself?!
Aw, crap...
There's still a few left, huh?
You guys!
What, you were just gonna sit quietly
and rot away in here?
Yoko! Where have you been?
I'll tell you all about it
some other time.
If what Nia said is true,
we're in big trouble.
The moon is falling. The surface and
underground will both be destroyed.
There's nowhere to run.
Yeah, and it sounds like there's an
ambush waiting for them in space.
Our back's against the wall.
Maybe, but finding a way out
of these no-win situations...
...is Team Gurren's stock
in trade, remember?
Yeah. That's right.
I see you still have as much
spunk as ever, woman.
Viral?!
Yoko, give me your gun.
What are you up to?
You heard the lady.
Team Gurren is gonna save
every living thing on the surface.
Oh? And how do you
intend to do that?
How else?
We'll stop the moon.
Are you serious?
You should know better than anyone
that I'm ALWAYS serious.
Who the hell do you
think I am?
I know exactly who you are.
You're that big fool from Team Gurren.
Guys?
Your debt to society
has been paid.
Well, well, here's a bunch
of familiar faces.
- Hey, that's--
- What's HE doing here?!
Right now, we need every good
Gunmen pilot we can get.
- We gonna do it?
- Yeah.
If we don't stop that thing,
Earth has no future.
Oh, you know about that?
That'll save us a lot of time, then.
Listen up, you bozos! We're gonna smash
that big-ass ceiling up there!
YEAH!
Boota! You're still alive?
That means the gang's
all here.
Boy, Boota, you're as tiny
as ever.
It's a present from Leeron.
We've boosted its output, too.
I'll launch the rest of 'em into space
on that rocket Gunmen.
You're persistent, I'll give you that.
Both you and this.
- Care to pilot it, Viral?
- What?
You said you were supposed to
observe the fate of humanity, right?
You'll have a front-row seat
there in Gurren's cockpit.
Gurren Lagann, eh?
Even after all the humiliation
I've suffered at its hands...
My body is telling me
what it wants.
All right, you're on.
You better prepare yourself.
This baby packs a serious punch.
I know that better
than anyone.
We're in a hurry, you two.
Are you getting in or not?
It fall apart!
Don't sweat it!
Those Dan-Gunmen configurations...
...seem to have been designed to
be used for atmospheric re-entry.
- "Atmosphere"? What that?
- Can you eat it?
Look, it just means that your
Gunmen can fight in space.
All right!
We do that!
We're counting on you.
We'll get it back.
A world where kids can live under the sun
without a care in the world.
Damn it! We're not even
denting those things!
Gimmy, calm down!
We have to stay focused!
Damage?
Severe damage to Block 357.
Now closing bulkheads.
Grapearl Squadron strength
down to 53%.
Damn these monsters!
The moon's rate of descent
is increasing!
Estimated time to impact
is now 20 hours!
Hold out, no matter what!
If this ship is destroyed here,
all that we've done will have been for--
- What happened?!
- Spiral Power falling.
Spiral lifeform readings
are rapidly weakening.
They're what?!
The people are worried.
The people aboard the ship are
worried because of the attack.
No, so are we.
It can't be... How could a machine
be influenced by human emotions?
No, that might be the case...
If that's true,
is this my limit?
Don't give up, Rossiu!
It can't be!
Simon?!
The instant you give up,
it's all over!
Don't you remember? This drill is the
drill that will pierce the heavens!
Viral, let's do the
you-know-what!
That? Sure, that might
be entertaining.
The Spiral Path, in which the twin paths
of man and beast wind and intersect!
Join with yesterday's enemy
to smash fate!
And grab hold of tomorrow's path
with our own hands!
Destiny Combining!
Gurren Lagann!
Who the hell do you
think I am?!
To Be Continued...
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Nariyamanai kodou ga itsumo itazura ni kokoro ni tane wo maku
My ever-sounding heartbeat always idly sows a seed in my heart
Sono tane ga kibou no hana wo sakasu ka mo shirenai
That seed might bloom into a flower of hope
Dakara kou shite yume wo egaku koto ga dekirunda
That's how I can sketch my dreams like this
Bunansou na nukemichi ga ukande ha kieteku
A loophole that seems safe comes to mind, but then disappears
Sou yatte boku ha tamesarete dou yatte omoi todokeyou?
By doing that, I'm tested; how can I get my feelings across?
Mayowazu ni mae he susunde
Let's advance forward without hesitating
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Dakara kakko tsukenaide kitto hana ha saku hazu sa
So don't try to look cool; I'm sure our flowers have gotta bloom
Bokura ha kagayaku yo Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
We're gonna shine! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Next Time
When humanity is battered into
subjugation by absolute despair,
...humanity finds a miracle.
And the name of that miracle
is Arch-Gurren Lagann.
This is My Final Duty
Next time on
Gurren Lagann,
..."This is My Final Duty."