Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
Screening shield, class 8!
Mirror armor plating
is detaching!
Hit taken in block 3865!
Damage?
Minimal. But our thruster flame
sticks out like a sore thumb now!
Stand fast, men.
Let's teach them something.
Teach them exactly
who they are facing.
Enemy fleet size
is off the charts!
So, all the lights in the heavens
are our enemy, eh?
They're worthy opponents.
I'll take the fabric of space-time itself
and wring them out of existence!
Prepare to fire
Maelstrom Cannon!
Target the Great
Dimensional Waterfall!
Gurren Lagann, spin on!
Who the hell do you
think I am?
Gurren Lagann
Episode 1:
Bust Through the Heavens With Your Drill!
Digging tunnels.
Day after day, that's my job.
The more we dig, the more
the village can expand.
When the village chief is happy,
he feeds us pig-mole steaks.
Is that why I dig?
For the steaks?
No, not exactly.
I also do it so I can
dig up treasure.
C'mon, now!
Keep on digging!
Hey, why can't you dig
like him?!
Don't you want those steaks?!
Ew, it's Simon the Digger.
What's the fun of getting covered
in dirt day after day?
He's carrying
something weird, too.
He's so gross...
And he smells.
He's looking this way!
If we're not careful, he might
drill a hole in us, too!
Walk with your head
held high, Simon.
Kamina?
Don't call me Kamina,
call me "Bro"!
Um, I don't have any siblings,
so that's kind of...
It's not about blood! We're soul
brothers, siblings of the spirit!
Don't worry about what
those fugly chicks say.
This looks good
on you, kid.
Drills are your soul!
Come with me.
Gentlemen! Sorry for the delay!
Is everything ready?!
Yeah!
What are you doing?
Listen up, Simon. That drill
doesn't belong to the chief.
That drill is who you are!
Yours is the drill that will break
through the vault of heaven!
Why?
I have it all figured out!
Don't ask for a reason!
Meaning that you
can't explain.
Okay, you bozos!
Are we ready?!
Yeah!
We're the invincible Team Gurren!
Nobody can stand in our way!
Y-Yeah!
We're sick of being cooped up
in this little town!
It's the youth who are
gonna break out!
Youth of this town,
aim for the surface!
Yahoo!
Step aside! Make way!
Team Gurren is coming through!
W-What now?!
Listen up, Simon! We're gonna use
your drill to bust through the ceiling!
Bust through that, and the
next stop is the surface!
We're gonna make a break
for the surface!
This is insane!
You can do it!
When did you--
Charge! Keep going
straight ahead!
Fly, piggies!
Kamina! You again!
Step aside, Chief!
You little moron!
Would you people PLEASE
come to your senses?
This "surface" of yours
doesn't exist!
Like hell it doesn't!
I've seen it!
Up on the surface,
there's no walls! No ceiling!
Instead, all you see around you
is a bright, blue sky!
A liar's son is a liar,
too, I see.
What?!
Your old man did nothing but
spout crap like that, too.
And what did it get him? Dead! Buried
under a pile of rocks somewhere!
You're wrong! My dad made it to
the surface! I was there with him!
Then what are you doing
down here, smart guy?
Um, well...
Get this through your thick skulls!
This village is all we have!
For untold generations, we've been
warned to never unseal the canopy.
People who don't understand
that rule don't get to eat!
Into the stockade with you!
Without food!
We're so sorry, sir!
You weasels!
Sorry about that, Bro!
But no dinner is
a high price to pay...
C'mon, Bro, swallow your
pride and apologize, too.
You don't get to call me Bro.
I don't ever wanna be called Bro
by the likes of you three!
Hmph!
The bonds of loyalty don't run too deep
in this Team Gurren of yours, I see.
Simon, you come, too.
I know that Kamina
roped you into helping him.
You have an important job
here in Giha Village...
...digging tunnels to
expand the village.
You don't have to stay with
that idiot, so come along.
- But I...
- Go ahead.
Don't sweat it.
Go on.
I-It's an earthquake!
Everybody take cover!
Kamina! Let's get out of here!
Kamina!
No way.
But--
I don't run from anything!
If we don't run, we're gonna
get crushed here!
Oh, right. I forgot what
happened to you.
Don't worry, it's already
settling down.
Are you people gonna keep living in
fear of earthquakes day after day?!
Up on the surface,
there ain't no ceiling!
Would you give it
a rest?!
I didn't look after you orphaned kids
out of the goodness of my heart!
It's because I'm
the chief!
I have a duty to look out for the welfare
of this village and its citizens!
But if you can't do as I tell you,
there's no place for you here!
What are you doing
in here, too?
That's a good boy.
I guess I have myself some
emergency rations now.
My parents died in an earthquake.
It happened when I was seven.
No matter how many
holes I dig,
...the ceiling is eventually gonna
fall in and crush me, the chief,
...and everybody in the village,
and we're all gonna die.
That's a given.
That's a fact of life.
Or is it?
Lights out!
Put out the lights!
It's now nighttime hours!
Go to sleep, everyone!
Don't waste precious electricity!
Grow up big and plump...
Grow into a big,
juicy steak for me...
What the hell?
Kamina!
Simon? What's up?
Come with me! There's something
you've got to see!
Hurry!
Uh, that would be
a jailbreak.
If the chief finds out,
there'll be hell to pay, Simon.
I was so preoccupied
that didn't even occur to me.
Well, if we get back by morning,
he'll be none the wiser.
So, what's so important that I have
to bust out ofjail to see it?
It's a face! It's this awesome,
humungous face!
You've got some nerve, Kamina,
breaking out of jail!
Simon, is this the humongous face
you were talkin' about?
Don't you underestimate me, youngster!
I'm the chief, so that means
I also stand guard!
Simon, that goes
for you, too!
I know all about those extra tunnels
you've been digging in secret!
Leave him alone. He hasn't done anything.
I'm the guilty party here.
Oh, I'm perfectly aware
of how guilty you are!
So, Simon. This thing
you wanted to show me...
Is THIS it?
Gurren Lagann
Look up!
That's the surface!
What did I tell you?
There's a surface, all right!
This big mug fell from the surface!
It fell from above!
Ain't that right, Mr. Chief?
- It's a monster!
- Run, it's a monster!
What are you
waiting for, Chief?
I thought you said it was your duty
to protect the village.
Gosh, it's hard to tell which of us
is the liar now, ain't it?
Bro, this way!
Bro?
You've got guts,
plowing into my village...
...with this big ugly mug
of yours, you know that?
R-Run!
But that ends here! I won't stand
for any more of your shenanigans!
Wha--?
Who the hell are you?
It talked!
I'm gonna tell you, so dig the wax outta
those huge ears and listen close!
The bad reputation of Team Gurren
echoes far and wide in Giha Village!
When they talk about
its badass leader,
...that man of indomitable spirit,
that paragon of masculinity,
...they're talking about ME,
the mighty Kamina!
Idiot.
- What a dunce.
- Total dumbass.
The mighty Kamina will not countenance
any further lawlessness in his village!
What can a puny human like you
do to stop me?
All right, you two!
Get back!
Something else
from the surface?
Yeah, it's a girl
this time.
I only knocked it on its backside.
It'll get up again soon.
Hey, baby, how ya doin'?
You sluggin' it out with that thing?
Let me give you a hand.
What?
You came from
the surface, right?
Pretty much.
That's awesome. So, that's a weapon
they use on the surface, huh?
Not exactly.
But something like that.
Damn, you got a fine body!
Surface chicks are a breed apart!
Do I need to tell you again to run?
Do you have a death wish?
Thanks, Simon!
Nice save!
Hurry, this way!
- Where am I?
- Giha Village.
Oh, this is the pit
next door.
Next door?
I'm from Littner Village,
the pit next to this one.
What the hell? You said you're from the
surface, but you were raised in a pit?
I came down from the surface just now,
but I originally hail from Littner.
Geez, you're a pit chick?
Move it, thunder thighs!
What's with the change
in attitude?
This way.
Where, exactly, are we going?
- The face.
- The face?
A humongous face!
Do you mean a Gunmen?
What the hell is a "Gunmen"?
That is.
Give me a minute. From here,
I can target its power conduits.
If I can take those out,
it'll stop him in his tracks.
Gotcha!
Hey, you with the big mug!
We're about to take you down with
one shot, so say your prayers!
What did you do that for?!
A man looks his opponent in the eye
when he lets him have it!
I'm a woman,
thank you very much!
A woman has no place meddling
in a fight between two men!
I'm the one who's doing
all the fighting here!
You've got spunk, lady!
I like your style!
This is it? The face you
wanted to show me?
Yep.
This is TWO awesome things
you've dug up now, kid.
I wonder if this is a friend
of the Gunmen up there?
It's smaller than the thing up there,
but I like this thing's face.
But look at this.
People ride in it?
But that's impossible...
Can you pilot it?
Bro, let's use this to take out that
thing up there! That big face!
Let's waste it.
With this, huh?
Yeah, Bro!
You can use this to--
Huh?
It looks like it's running!
Really?
C'mon, Bro!
You do it, Simon.
You're the one who dug this up.
That makes it yours.
But I--
What, you think the great Kamina could
steal stuff from his blood brother?
What?
Come on, I can't do this!
Dumbass!
Reject common sense to make
the impossible possible!
That's the way
Team Gurren rolls, right?
But...
Just pilot the damn thing!
Do it. If anyone can
do it, it's you.
B-But...
Listen, Simon.
Don't believe in yourself.
Believe in ME! Believe in the
Kamina who believes in you!
What's that supposed
to mean?
I'll see what I can do.
It worked!
You did it, Simon!
Yeah, Bro!
Here we go!
Why, that's--
Kamina and Simon?
You weren't expecting THIS,
were ya, you Gunmen S.O.B.?
Even if heaven itself tolerates your
brutality, the mighty Lagann doesn't!
What's "Lagann"?
This fella's name.
I just came up with it.
Simon! Why are you dodging?
Quit running!
But it's gonna kill us!
A man never walks away
from a fight!
We're on top of its head?!
Bro!
Stay away!
R-Reject common sense to make
the impossible possible!
That's the way
Team Gurren rolls!
I'm coming, Bro!
Simon! That was pretty slick!
C'mon, jump!
Make it jump!
Hey, quit wasting time!
Hurry!
N-Nice work with
the canopy, Simon!
It's a little cramped, though...
Looks like we took it down.
I guess this thing's head
is hard as a rock.
I have you now!
We're done for...
It's so cramped!
Don't moan over a little
thing like this!
Damn it... I need power...
If only I had more power!
- A drill?
- It just sorta popped out.
That's your kind of weapon!
It's a perfect match!
Bro! I think I'll be able
to do the job with this!
All right, then! Smash us
into that big mug!
Give it a taste of the power
of Team Gurren's mighty drill!
Yeah!
Get going, Simon! Bust through
the heavens with your drill!
Farewell, Giha Village!
We're off to the surface!
Off to the surface
I saw as a kid!
This is the surface?
It's so beautiful...
It's Yoko.
That's my name.
I never introduced myself, did I?
Come to think of it...
I'm Kamina,
and this is Simon.
Nice to meet you.
Um, what's this furry thing that's
hiding out in my cleavage?
Behave yourself, Boota!
Whoa, breast meat
hiding among the breast meat...
Is it just me,
or are we falling?
Hey, the thrusters turned off!
Do something, Simon!
I was caught up in the moment
earlier, I don't know how!
- It's no use!
- You're sure quick to give up.
We're falling!
Hold on tight!
Talk about a rough reception...
You can say that again...
I-I'm sorry!
Out of the frying pan,
into the fire, looks like...
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
If you're doing it, then so am I!
If I don't do it, will you?
If you don't do it, I will!
I'm doing it, so you
do it, too, damn it!
I Said I'm Gonna Pilot That Thing!!
Next time on Gurren Lagann!
"I Said I'm Gonna Pilot That Thing!!"