Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who continues
to fight against fate.
Simon and the others emerge victorious
from their battle with Adiane, the Elegant.
During the battle, Yoko learns of Nia's
trust in both her and Team Dai-Gurren.
Any hard feelings that Yoko harbored
against Nia are now dispelled.
Team Dai-Gurren's bonds of loyalty
have been made even stronger.
Ah, so THIS is where you've been, Simon.
Is something the matter?
N-No, it's just that you've
really changed your image.
- I knew it, I look odd.
- No, you don't! Not one bit!
You mean it?
I sure do!
That's a relief...
By the way, Simon... There's something
that I need to discuss with you.
What is it?
The thing is, I...
I want to be put to work!
Everyone else is
toiling away at their tasks.
I can't bear to be the
only one doing nothing!
I want to do something!
To make myself useful!
Well, you're a princess, Nia,
so seeing you smile is enough for--
I'm no longer a princess.
Oh, right. Um...
Simon!
What's this I hear about you
going without a meal all day?
It's no big deal.
I grab a bite when I get hungry.
Unacceptable!
You're the only one
who can pilot Lagann!
What would we do if you passed out
or something when we needed you?
Eating properly
is part of your job!
Eating properly...
is part of his job?
Oh, I'm sorry.
Did I interrupt something?
No, I have my answer now!
Oh, you do?
Uh, you do?
Anyway... I'm gonna borrow
Simon for a while.
I swear, you never
grow up...
I've found it.
I've found my job.
Episode 13:
Eat Up, Everyone
What's wrong with Rossiu?
I can't pinpoint the cause,
but nothing seems physically wrong.
It might be stress from overwork.
Well, he's going out to fight in Gurren
day after day even though he's still a kid.
It's hardly surprising
that he's collapsed.
I don't really think that you're
in a position to talk here.
What are you getting at?
My point is, don't you think you've been
pushing yourself too hard lately?
Not really. I'm just doing
what needs to be done.
Awesome... Looks like we're gonna
get a taste of "palace food".
Nia's so cute when she's
working hard...
I've been fasting since yesterday
to get ready!
That's going a little
too far, dude...
Wow, I'm impressed.
Nia said she wanted
to work, too.
It's nearly ready, everybody!
- Enemy forces?
- That's what's strange.
Judging from the size,
I'd say it's a battleship,
...but these coordinates
indicate that it's in the air.
- The air?
- Come on, that's impossible.
The radar is working properly.
But if it really is an airborne enemy,
how do we go about attacking them?
Flying Carrier Fortress Gunmen:
Dai-Gunten
The time has finally come...
...to demonstrate my power.
Cytomander, the Swift
Spiral King Lordgenome, watch closely!
All units, advance!
- Yoko!
- I'm taking over for Rossiu!
I'll pilot Gurren.
I can do it fine by myself!
You don't think I'm up to it?
I've been practicing!
I didn't mean it like that!
That settles it, then!
Boota!
Boota?
You'll go with me, huh?
All right, come get some!
What's the matter?
Come down here!
Fight me, damn it!
Fight me!
- Second wave closing in!
- Come and get it!
I'll remember this!
It ain't gonna happen again!
Bastards!
Chew on this!
Weaklings...
Such weaklings!
They dispatched Thymilph and Adiane
and gave even Guame a hard time,
...so I was unsure how formidable
they would be.
It's not that they are weak, but perhaps
rather that I am too powerful!
Dayakka! We're going out
in Gurren Lagann!
If you go out now,
you'll be sitting ducks!
No! Throw us again, Leeron!
- Are you sure about this?
- We don't have time to argue!
Don't say I didn't warn you!
Do it!
Throwing!
Damn it!
Bastard!
Simon, look at this!
Hey, right!
Maybe we can integrate it!
It worked!
All right!
Now we can attack
that flying battleship!
Damn, that was cool...
- Brother!
- Outta the way!
Kiyoh and Kiyal?
Hey, now!
All right, let's pay 'em back
ten times over!
Not so fast!
We want a piece
of this action, too!
If this keeps up, we won't
get to eat Nia's cooking.
- Her cooking, her cooking!
Okay, let's show those bastards
what Team Dai-Gurren is made of!
Commence counterattack!
- We'll fly right down their throats!
- Okay!
Enemy Gunmen closing in fast!
What? Impossible!
I didn't expect
to get to face him.
It's been a while, naked ape!
Is that you, Viral?
Do you have any idea...
...of the depths of my shame?!
Of the humiliation of being
the sole survivor?!
How it felt for me to beg and plead
to take part in this battle...
...so that I might have
the chance to face you?!
Crap! I haven't got the
hang of flying yet!
I'll clear us a path!
Are you kidding me?!
Yoko!
You're not getting away!
Viral and the enemy Gunmen have crashed
into the levi-sphere control room!
They've what?!
Yoko?
Why the worried look?
Don't worry,
it's nothing serious.
Yoko!
What happened to Kamina?
Why is there only a woman
and a child here?
WHERE DID KAMINA GO?!
My Bro is...
If you're looking for my Bro,
he's dead.
He's what?
Gurren Lagann
He... died back then?
Kamina is dead?
You're saying that I've been
losing to you?
To a mere child?
You, boy.
What is your name?
It's Simon.
Simon, you can't do it alone!
I'll be fine.
Don't worry, Yoko,
I'll protect you.
That's a fine attitude.
I wouldn't want you to say you lost because
you had a wounded woman on board.
An insult done to me by a Gunmen
will be repaid in my Gunmen!
That's the way I do things!
No. 2 levi-sphere output falling!
Unable to maintain altitude!
What?!
Putting up a visual now.
What do you think you're doing, Viral?!
Hey, they're on fire up there!
I see that!
Now's our chance!
Hit 'em hard!
We've taken a pounding, too!
Our main guns are gone, and the engine room
is seconds away from shutting down!
This is so frustrating!
Simon and Yoko are in the belly of the beast!
What's the big idea, not backing 'em up?!
I'll nail 'em with a flying kick
if that's all we got!
I'll borrow that idea of yours.
How can this be?! How can I be
losing to a mere human cub?!
I'm putting an end to
this here, Viral!
Well, I'll be. He really CAN
fight on his own...
Cytomander's Custom Gunmen:
Shuzack
You in the Gunmen, stay where you are!
Otherwise, I'll crush this she-ape flat!
General Cytomander!
How long are you going
to keep fooling around, Viral?
Forgive me, sir.
I'm not interested in hearing
your excuses. Finish him!
Yes, sir...
No, don't!
Simon, keep fighting!
Keep quiet!
You're playing dirty, Viral!
This happens every single time!
Is this how you do things, Viral?!
Leeron, are you SURE
you want to do this?
Just this once!
Hold it together!
You can count on me!
Dai-Gurren!
Full speed ahead!
Damn you, what are you
playing at?
I mustn't settle things with
the human in this manner.
Have you lost your mind, Viral?
I see you've forgotten your debt
to me for discovering you...
...Viral!
- It's a flying kick!
- Dodge it, dodge it!
It didn't work,
we just clipped them!
We ain't done yet!
Viral, you bastard!
Yoko, are you okay?
Yeah, somehow.
Boota protected me.
What about the guys?
Why, that looks like a flying device!
Perfect timing! Grab it!
Yoink!
What the hell is going on?!
We lost No. 1 levi-sphere!
We can't maintain level flight!
Do whatever it takes
to keep us level!
Y-Yes, sir!
Viral, you will pay dearly for this.
Yes, sir...
- The enemy ship?
- It's retreating.
Looks like we managed
to drive them off.
Say, Simon, did you know?
I kinda had a thing for Kamina.
Yeah, I knew.
You did, huh?
Your bones and organs
seem okay.
A little bed rest,
and you'll be good as new.
It can be a pain, being this tough.
Yoko, are you all right?
I'm fine, I'm fine!
Leeron's overreacting, that's all.
Don't worry.
Thank goodness...
If you're hungry, let's all eat
the dinner I made earlier!
Weren't you listening?
Eating properly is part of your job!
Go on, shoo!
- I'll come by later.
- I'll come visit, too.
- Rossiu?
The thing is...
It all started yesterday.
I was walking by, and Nia asked me
to be her taste tester.
Its taste was not of this world.
However, Nia looked so happy
as she was cooking...
...that I could not bring myself
to come out and say it was awful.
And so, I sampled every last dish...
Ah, that's what caused it.
- Oh, no!
There is plenty to go around!
Eat up, everyone!
It's great!
The operation's failure rests entirely
on this man's insubordination.
In addition to being incompetent,
he is defiant, as well!
A fool beyond any hope
of redemption!
I ask that you sentence him
to death!
Majesty!
If you order me to die,
I will gladly obey.
But before then, there is something
that I must know!
Restrain yourself, Viral!
Very well.
Ask your question.
Are the humans truly creatures
that are inferior to Beastmen?
These humans...
what the hell are they?!
- Cytomander, leave us.
- Sire?
I will see to this man.
Y-Yes, sire.
Beastmen are
imperfect creatures, indeed...
To maintain their powerful bodies,
it is absolutely essential for them...
...to go into a deathlike sleep,
during which time their cells rejuvenate.
If one were to stay awake,
every cell in his body would die.
Spiral King, it is you
who gave us Beastmen life.
Why would you give us
such flawed bodies?
What are humans?
Do you really wish
to know the answer?
Do you, Viral?
Yes!
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
No matter how thick the wall,
it will eventually crumble.
With that belief in our hearts, we continue
to pound away at it together.
Well Met, Everyone
Next time on Gurren Lagann,
"Well Met, Everyone".