Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the story of a man who has yet
to realize what his destiny is.
Days of constant fighting continue
as they search for the enemy base.
Just when they thought that a new
journey was about to begin...
...after they foiled the underhanded
trap set by the bathhouse Gunmen,
...an enormous figure
suddenly appeared.
This was the beginning
of a new set of trials.
It's been a long time, hasn't it,
you naked ape?!
Wait, you're--
I see that you've had your fun lately,
but that is at an end today.
I've come to settle this
once and for all!
Viral!
Now... You will return
my helmet to me!
Or so I'd like to say...
But first things first.
Put some clothes on!
Episode 7:
You're Gonna Do It!
You're being awfully understanding,
giving us time to get dressed like this!
Defeating a NAKED naked ape
will win me no honors.
Warriors of the Capital
prize decorum above all else!
The Capital?
That must be their base, Bro!
Our "base"? It is nothing
so unimportant as a mere base!
The Capital is unique,
and it is eternal!
It is the sole example of civilization on
the surface, ruled by the Spiral King!
Spiral King?
Civilization, huh?
Damn you, return my helmet
this instant!
After all that speechifying,
THAT'S all you want?!
You seem determined to utterly and
completely make an enemy of the Capital.
Very well, learn now the
power of the Capital!
A mountain?
A mountain? Since when do
mountains shoot at you?!
It's moving!
What?!
Who is that?!
What has this kind of firepower?
Do you now know the power
of the Capital?
Yikes.
Surrender and return
my helmet to me!
No, YOU give up and be happy
with that freaky bird crest doohickey!
That's enough of your impudence.
It's huge!
Enormous!
- Incredible...
- Massive!
It's so gigantic!
Goodness, I'm blushing...
Do you see? This is Dai-Gunzan,
the mobile fortress Gunmen!
Bro, that thing is
way too big for us.
This oughta be good.
This isn't good. This is the point!
It's the recall point!
It overlaps perfectly with the Gunmen
point of origin we've been searching for!
It makes sense that
their base is mobile.
It's a Gunmen, too!
You seem to be having
some trouble, Viral.
Sir. My apologies, sir.
There's a Beastman piloting
that one, too?
Kamina! Get back!
It's too dangerous!
That guy seems to be
the Gunmen's boss!
This looks like it'll be fun.
Nobody's cast such a big
shadow over me before.
Don't think you're going home
unscathed, buddy!
Look, Bro, maybe we're the
ones who should be leaving.
W-We're no match for
something this big!
We're gonna knock him on his ass
BECAUSE he's big!
What's the matter?
Lost your nerve?
Butt out, cannon fodder!
You puny humans have gotten
too big for your britches.
You have incurred the wrath
of the Spiral King.
I, one of the Spiral King's Four Generals,
have come to put you in your place!
I see you up there!
- Kamina!
Kamina!
We're getting out of here!
Hurry!
- Son of a bitch!
- Hey!
Did you see that, human?
You can try to steal as many
Gunmen from us as you want,
...but they are ineffective before
the might of my Dai-Gunzan!
Kamina!
Who's the ineffective one here?
That didn't hurt, it didn't even tingle.
Don't mess with Gurren Lagann!
It's no use, our left leg
is damaged!
What's the matter, have you
run out of fight already?
Would you give it a rest already?!
There's a time to give up, and this is it!
Kamina, I suggest we withdraw for now
and formulate a proper strategy!
I think we're in
big trouble this time.
Are you kidding me?!
Never retreat, never surrender,
never look back!
That's how me and Simon
see the world!
Kamina!
No more talk!
What is this,
a guy never says die?
Huh? It's... It's fixed!
Fighting spirit!
You never get anywhere
by running away!
Fine! See if I care!
You blockhead!
Who asked you!
Get back!
Look out! Look out!
Damn it! Isn't there any way
we can get on top of this thing?!
There's just too much cannon fire!
It's hopeless!
All right, then...
What's the matter? Have you
finally given up, human?
For humans, your tenacity
was admirable.
Your resistance was brave,
but doomed to fail.
Dai-Gunzan's concentrated cannon
fire will smash you to charred scrap!
Impossible!
Fire! Fire!
Fire!
Man on Fire!
Blazing Chariot Kick!
Something doesn't
seem right over there.
Did Kamina die?
I don't know.
No way would Kamina buy it!
But there was that
huge explosion...
Something's coming!
What is?
G-Gunmen!
Run away!
I won't let a single one of
you filthy humans escape me.
General Thymilph!
Look at the Gunmen
on our deck!
Viral's status?
Unconscious!
Worthless!
If only I had my rifle!
We're surrounded!
Amazing! It took out
three of them at once!
It doesn't seem to
be an enemy...
The gold plating on that Gunmen
looks rather haphazard.
If you're not an enemy, go to Kamina!
Save him! Help us!
What's that bozo Kamina
gotten himself into now?
Gurren Lagann
Now, then...
You're the head honcho, huh?
So, I finally get to
see your face!
I am one of the Spiral King's
Four Generals...
...Thymilph, the Raging Wave.
Yeah, whatever! Dig the wax
outta your ears and listen up!
He takes the blazing sun in his
bare hands and endures the heat!
He's a man's man who is sustained
by strength of will!
When you hear of the great Kamina,
they're talkin' about ME!
You'd best remember it!
I'm really scared here, Bro...
Relax, Simon! As long as we stay
up here, they won't risk shooting!
Are you sure about that?
I won't tolerate your big mouth,
not here atop my own Dai-Gunzan!
When it comes to big mouths,
Dai-Gunzan's is by far the biggest! Splat!
I'll tear you limb from limb!
W-We're coming apart!
It's about to tear!
Rip apart!
Split asunder!
Ow!
Who's there?
General Thymilph! Over there!
A Gunmen!
A Gunmen saved us?
- Get clear while we keep them busy!
- I know that voice!
That's right, it's Dayakka
from Littner!
Kittan of the Black Siblings
is here, too!
Sorry to keep you waiting, Kamina!
Who are you?
It's me! Kittan!
Did you forget already?!
What the hell are you guys
doing with Gunmen?
Because of you.
Me?
You got your hands on Gurren,
so now everybody is copying you.
I'm not copying anybody!
"Everybody"?
That's right. From what I hear,
more of our friends will be here soon.
Our friends?
Filthy humans...
Scheming vermin!
Shoot! Shoot them!
Attack!
Geez, nothing but cannon fodder again.
I wish they'd send some--
This is bad! They're ganging up
on Kamina and Simon!
Um, hello? Kamina?
Do you read me?
The shape it's in now, you don't have
a chance of winning in Gurren Lagann!
If you're defeated now, who's
going to lead our new allies?
If you die here,
who's going to lead us?!
Get off my case!
Like I said, you'll never get
anywhere by running away!
Bro!
Yeah, what?!
Yoko's right! Let's retreat
just this once!
What the hell? Have you
lost your nerve?
Yes! My nerve is done and gone!
Chicken!
If means getting you home in one piece,
I'll lose my nerve if that's what it takes!
I mean, everyone's waiting for you!
Bro!
We can't.
Take a look, Simon. If we turn our back
on these guys, we'll be sitting ducks.
Either way, unless we pin this thing down,
we don't have a hope of winning our fight!
That's true, but how do we--
Bro! I have an idea!
Say what?
Let me handle this!
All right.
I'll leave this fight to you.
You won't escape!
What the hell?
What's he trying to do?
There's nowhere left to run!
Their back is to a cliff...
Were those kids really
that foolish?
It's all over!
Yeah, for you!
What?!
Stinking humans...
What are you up to?
I'll crush you underfoot!
Kamina, you bastard!
Hey, don't look at me, pal.
Mark my words, naked ape!
Don't think this means you've won!
Dai-Gunzan is the merest fraction
of the Capital's military might!
And you have just made an enemy
of that might!
Mark my words! We will
be back tomorrow!
Say your prayers!
That's our Simon the Digger!
Way to go!
Bro!
Whaddya think?
This is a bunch of people from all over
who have been resisting the Gunmen!
They heard rumors about a couple morons
fighting in a stolen Gunmen,
...and they gathered together
to join the fight!
We all caught your stupidity bug.
Fighting spirit repaired
the armor, did it?
Yeah, but it disappeared as soon
as I separated from Lagann.
I thought as much.
Come to think of it, what did you do with
your village's women and children?
Oh, them. We left them
in the care of Giha Village.
I'm surprised
our chief agreed.
Gurren Lagann is a symbol of hope
for humanity, more so than you know.
Still, you should be careful.
Good intentions can sometimes tempt
people down the wrong path.
Just as it did in my village.
Forehead Boy!
There you go again,
talking like you know it all!
Smarty-pants.
I'm Zorthy.
I'm Kid.
Me, I'm Iraak.
I'm J-J-Jorgun.
I'm B-B-Balinbow.
Okay, fine, whatever.
Nice to meet you.
But for now...
Okay, you bozos!
I'm glad you could make it!
About that huge Gunmen
from this afternoon...
You can be sure that it'll
come back tomorrow!
In which case... I say we steal
that big-ass Gunmen from them!
We're gonna help ourselves to it!
And after tomorrow, it's gonna
be our headquarters!
Pretty sweet, huh?!
We've come this far by stealing
Gunmen from the Beastmen!
There's nothing to be afraid of!
Yeah, but how are we
gonna do that, Bro?
That's easy!
YOU'RE gonna do it.
Huh? M-Me?!
Listen, when Gurren Lagann combines,
...it's accomplished by Lagann
taking over Gurren's systems.
That's Gurren Lagann's strength.
That means that if Lagann
can combine with Dai-Gunzan,
...it will be able to take over
its systems.
It'll be okay.
You can do it, Simon.
Lagann's power is also linked to Simon's mental energy.
Depending on your spirit, it--
Are you paying attention, Simon?
What a beautiful moon.
Just being able to see this
makes me glad I came up to the surface.
We have to win. We can't afford
to be slowed down, not now.
We'll keep stealing and stealing
and stealing their weapons.
We have to keep winning until they
give up on the idea of attacking us.
And besides, I wanna give Simon and
Forehead Boy and Gimmy and Darry...
...a world where kids can look up at
the sun without a care in the world.
Kamina.
Yeah, what?
You have more brains than
I gave you credit for.
Who the hell do you
think I am?
Kamina! Badass leader of the
indomitable Team Gurren, that's who.
You're wrong.
We're not Team Gurren.
We're now Team DAI-Gurren!
Even so, I don't want you to do
anything crazy like you did today.
Up until now, there was always
a method to your madness.
I could always tell myself,
"If anybody can pull it off, it's Kamina."
But this afternoon was different.
That wasn't reckless or even crazy.
That was plain stupid!
You rushed in there
without thinking it through,
...and if Simon hadn't been there,
you might have been killed.
I... I guess that frightened me.
Kamina.
Simon! Don't be scared!
Simon, if anybody can
do it, it's you!
Yeah, I guess you're right.
Flames are coming from
that mountain!
The mountain is belching up fire
and setting the earth ablaze...
Talk about a fitting setting for
a once-in-a-lifetime fight!
Now I'm psyched!
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
Listen, Simon.
Never forget this.
Believe in yourself. Not in the
Simon that I have faith in.
Not in the Kamina that
you believe in, either.
Later, Buddy
Believe in the Simon
who believes in you!