Gurren Lagann
Sugita kisetsu wo nageku hima ha nai
I don't have the time to lament the seasons that have passed
Nido to mayotte shimawanu you ni
So that I won't ever waver again
Kazoekirenai hon no sasayaka na
With countless, tiny little
Sonna koukai kakaeta mama
Regrets carried in my arms
Sono senaka dake oikakete koko made kitanda
I've come this far, having chased only after your back
Sagashite ita boku dake ni dekiru koto
It's something only I, who sought you, can do
Ano hi kureta kotoba ga ima demo
Those words you gave me that day, even now,
Kono mune ni tashika ni todoite iru kara
Definitely reach my heart
Kinou yori mo kyou ha bu ha boku no
I've realized my reason for having been born
Umarete kita wake ni kidzuite yuku
Today more than I did yesterday
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who blows
a hole in the fate of a universe...
...that is ruled by the endless
cycle of violence.
As the Earth's destruction
looms ever closer,
...the reborn Gurren Lagann
combines with the Arc-Gurren,
...and, with the moon Gunmen now under
his control, Simon saves the Earth.
However, Nia, the
Anti-Spiral's messenger,
...is recalled to the
enemy homeworld.
Episode 23:
Let's Go, This is the Final Battle
One Week Since Prevention of Moonfall
This is Viral, who has been made Gurren's main pilot.
Arc-Gurren Council Chamber
I'm going to have him attend our mission
planning sessions from now on.
I don't expect you to simply
let bygones be bygones.
But I DO want you to understand
that it isn't just humans...
...who want to protect
the Earth.
Well, well! Listen to you,
bein' all modest!
You don't have to beg and scrape.
You were hand-picked by Simon.
That makes you the same
as the rest of us.
We're about to launch a frontal assault
on the enemy's stronghold.
We can't waste time worrying
about the little things.
And there are some of us who
haven't changed one bit...
...after showing up again
after six years.
Goodness, whoever do you mean?
I thought you said we weren't
sweating the details.
Yeah! Nobody's better than humans
at being rough and ready!
You humans are...
That reminds me,
has anyone seen Rossiu?
Huh?
Hey, Rossiu, where
are you headed?
Aretenborough, don't be in
such a rush all the time.
He's hammering out the
Surface Restoration Plan.
He said he'll leave all further
mission planning up to us.
All right, let's get down
to business.
This is the result of collating
all data thus far.
The Earth Spiral race flagship currently
in lunar orbit, the Cathedral Terra.
It was stolen by the Anti-Spiral
and disguised as our moon.
Gurren Lagann. Arc-Gurren.
Cathedral Terra.
The thing that brings out the potential
of each is Spiral Power.
That refers to the power of evolution
present in us lifeforms...
...that possess a double-helix
genetic structure.
To put it in simple terms,
it's fighting spirit.
- Oh, that!
- Makes perfect sense!
It appears that the Anti-Spiral were
originally Spiral lifeforms just like us.
However, they believed that
continued use of this power...
...would lead to the destruction
of the universe.
The Spiral Nemesis will bring about
this universe's destruction.
We Anti-Spiral exist
to prevent that event.
By "Spiral Nemesis," she probably
means the destruction of the universe.
Anyway, the Spirals failed to put down the
Anti-Spiral rebellion and were defeated.
Why did that happen,
you ask?
It was because they hid their
stronghold somewhere...
...in a universe with a different
set of dimensional axes.
Having emerged victorious, the Anti-Spiral
built Spiral lifeform annihilation systems...
...on each Spiral race's homeworld.
To survive, the Spiral races were forced to
eke out a meager existence underground.
What's the story with
the Beastmen, then?
Or all the animals
on the surface?
We're all beings that were
created by the Spiral King.
Our reproduction is done
entirely through cloning.
What does that mean?
They don't have Spiral Power,
so they can't have children.
It's the genetic diversity resulting from
gamogenesis that is the key to evolution.
It's in this that the upwardly-mobile
Power of the Spiral resides.
In other words, it means that
love changes the universe!
At the same time...
The Moon Battleship...
On the Cathedral Terra, they're focusing
all their efforts as we speak...
...Cathedral Terra.
...on the construction of
a scanning system.
Great Spiral Computer Room
We'll find the Anti-Spiral's stronghold, no matter what.
And that's also where
we'll find Nia, right?
Y-Yeah, I guess...
Come on, don't be embarrassed.
Love changes the universe, remember?
So I say let's change it.
We'll force it to.
Yeah! Love and spirit!
Let's do this!
It doesn't sound as good
coming from you.
Kiss my ass.
I think I understand where your
strength comes from now.
We're just getting started. We'll get
a lot stronger before we're done.
So you can win?
Sort of.
But not just for that.
Who's there?
Father Magin!
Rossiu?
What's the matter, Kinon?
Simon...
Rossiu sent me an e-mail with
the Surface Restoration Plan.
That's Rossiu for you.
He finished it already?
The thing is, there was a message
to me written on the last page.
So, what are you doing
all the way out here?
I could ask the same
of you, Father Magin.
It's the strangest thing.
This place is hardly full
of happy memories for me,
...and yet, it seems to be
the anchor of my soul.
It must have been hard for you.
No, sir.
Here.
Why, that's--
It's our holy book!
You kept it all this time?
I'm returning it to you.
I'm not the right man to hold it.
Have you read it?
No. That book can't be read.
I compared the writing to every
known form of ancient writing,
But there was no such
writing anywhere.
What is it, then?
Someone probably made it
as a practical joke.
A joke? Our holy book
was just nonsense?
Yes.
So, I was preaching God's word with
someone's practical joke in my hand?
That's rich!
You learn that something you thought was
a precious treasure was nothing but junk.
I wonder if that qualifies
as evolution, too?
Yes, it's possible.
What a strange thing.
But you know, Rossiu, that's exactly
what makes humans so fascinating.
Don't you think so, too?
No, I don't. I don't see it
that way at all.
Aretenborough says that
he saw Rossiu.
He said he flew off somewhere
in a Gun-spinner.
Never think that you
can go it alone.
I want you to get the job done
with the people around you.
I know you can do it.
That is all I can tell you.
Thank you for everything.
Kinon, I am grateful
for your friendship.
He's been acting funny
for a long time.
Ever since we returned to the surface.
Like he was haunted by something.
Stay calm, Kinon.
Do you think you can track
his Gun-spinner's signature?
Huh? Oh. Yes!
It's faint, but I'm getting something
to the east-northeast.
Roger.
Hey, where are you going?
The ground was distorted by
the approach of the moon.
I don't want my hometown to be destroyed,
so I'll go check it over.
- Then allow me to--
- No.
It's dangerous, so please
wait up here.
Rossiu!
I think you did a fine job.
You did a fine job. Not everyone
could have done what you did.
The reading is close!
That's it?
Come in, pilot!
State your destination!
Is that you, Commander?
We're returning the animals
to their habitats.
Sorry to bother you.
Continue doing your job.
We were chasing the
wrong heat source...
Don't panic, Kinon.
Rossiu didn't... He didn't overthrow you
for personal gain.
After the trial, I saw him--
I know he didn't, Kinon.
That's it! Simon, what about
the village where he was born?
He used to talk about it
all the time!
He used to say that half of his soul
was still there in that village.
Adai Village? Hey, you're right!
That has to be where he is!
- I'm gonna punch it, Kinon!
- Right!
Once, this impoverished village could
support no more than 50 people.
Back then, survival always meant
that someone must be sacrificed.
On the surface, there is a world
where everyone can live.
That's what I believed
as I fought.
But I was wrong.
In the end, I almost sacrificed
more lives than ever before.
That sin must be atoned for.
Gurren Lagann
What the--?
What's happening?
All Spiral systems
are starting up!
The main engine
is powering up, too!
But why?! We're not done with
the system build yet!
Spiral transference signal detected
moving at high speed.
- Rossiu...
- Rossiu!
Sins must be judged.
I will atone for my own sin
at my own hand.
- Rossiu!
Spiral Realm Perceptual
Teleportation System engaged.
Wait for us, Rossiu!
Please, don't die!
- Rossiu!
Gurren Lagann!
Stay away!
Don't!
Rossiu!
Grit those teeth!
Have you come back to
your senses, Rossiu?
I was belted like that, too.
Everybody makes mistakes.
It's to be expected.
But when you do make a mistake, you
should be slugged by someone else.
There's no need
to punish yourself.
At the time, you might think that
it's a mistake you can never undo.
Even if it is, if we kick and struggle and fight
like hell, we'll move forward a little bit.
I got knocked flat on my ass, and I was told
to believe in the me that believes in myself.
That's probably how it should be.
At least that's what I think.
You tried to do something that
I never could have done.
What's wrong with that?
Simon...
Come on, Rossiu.
I need you.
Actually, I guess there's someone else
who needs you even more than I do.
I'm sorry, Kinon.
What do you think, Rossiu? How does it
feel to be back in the cockpit again?
- It really takes me back.
- It does, huh?
Um, I'm not heavy, am I?
Yes. You are.
You're very heavy.
I-I'll climb down, then.
No, this is fine.
Right now, I want to feel it.
I want to feel what the weight
of a single human life is like.
Jerk.
Human beings are fascinating indeed,
aren't they, Rossiu?
How could we have been so blind?
They eluded our super-Spiral
scan sweeps by creating...
...an imaginary oscillating time-space
located between the membranes...
...of the dimensional universes we
call the 10th and 11th dimensions.
I'm sorry, boys. I can't make
heads or tails of it, either.
But this is definitely the
Anti-Spiral homeworld.
How can you tell?
That's... her ring!
But why?
What we call the universe
is constructed on ambiguity.
It only becomes a fixed reality
when observed.
That is a fundamental law
of the universe.
Even in a pocket universe,
...an object that has been observed at one time
can be picked up on a Spiral scan.
Maybe this is related to the
quantum universe theory...
Rossiu, are you a monster
or something?
This isn't like you people.
Who cares about the explanation.
We know where it is, so we're going.
Yes, what he said! It sounds like you
can reach it if you know where it is.
With a fixed set of perceptual
dimensional coordinates,
...instantaneous teleportation
is possible.
That is how the Spiral Realm Perceptual
Teleportation System works.
If you think of someone, it will
send you straight into their arms!
Thinking of them
gives you wings!
If you think of me,
you die.
That's what
that warp was?
In that case, we've already tested it.
Basically, spirit lets you fly anywhere.
But we should also assume that the
enemy has warp capability, too.
Good point.
In which case, I'm not sure
if it's a good idea...
...for Gurren Lagann to
leave Earth right now.
- Feel free to go, Simon.
- Rossiu?
While you're away,
I'll come up with something.
So please, go.
He's right, Simon! If you don't go after
all this, all that macho will go to waste!
We've found the enemy's stronghold,
so we smash it.
It's worked for us this far.
Am I right?
Guys...
We ain't doing this for you.
We want to put an end to this. We're tired of
all that rattling and rumbling on the surface.
Okay, Anne? I'm heading off to the
edge of the galaxy for a bit, okay?
Look forward to all the cool stories
I'll have when I get back.
- Kiyoh, I need to talk to--
- You can go.
That's what you wanted
to talk about, right?
Are you sure?
This is Team Dai-Gurren's
last big fight, right?
How can Littner Village's Dayakka
sit on the sidelines?
I'm so lucky to have you!
I'm so lucky I married you!
You big lug. But make sure you
protect the Earth, okay?
And make sure you
come home to me.
I will! I promise!
Oh, come on, quit crying!
Guys sure are idiots,
aren't they?
Dimensional anchors have penetrated
imaginary space.
They've latched onto
the moon.
Dayakka! Give the word!
Engine output, 50%!
All ahead slow!
Wow, it actually came out.
So, that's the real moon.
With this here, the
Cathedral Terra can leave...
...without worrying about
it affecting Earth.
Anything could happen now,
and I wouldn't be surprised.
M-Me, neither.
Sorry. I know how
big a job this is.
You can count on us.
Even if you don't return,
I'll see to it that humanity survives.
We'll kick and scream
and fight like hell.
You bet.
- Old Coco?
- What are you doing here?
What's the matter?
Hey, this is--
Thanks, Old Coco.
I'll bring Nia back,
count on it.
It's Team Dai-Gurren's flag!
Yes. And it's also the same flag
we flew when we took Teppelin.
This is the actual flag?
- Guinble.
- Sir?
I hope I can count on
your continued support.
Yes, sir!
I'll be back, Bro.
Sorry to keep you waiting, guys.
Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren, launch!
Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren?
That's right! She's the
Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren!
It works. It's a much better fit for
you people than Cathedral Terra.
It sure does.
Kittan. Leeron. Dayakka.
Zorthy. Kid. Iraak.
Jorgun. Balinbow. Makken.
Tetukan. Gabal.
Aretenborough.
Gimmy. Darry.
Cybela. Leyte.
Yoko. Viral.
Lordgenome.
And Boota.
As long as Team Dai-Gurren stands united,
we have nothing to fear!
Engines to full!
Spiral Realm Perceptual
Teleportation System, activate!
Let's go.
This is our final battle.
To Be Continued...
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Nariyamanai kodou ga itsumo itazura ni kokoro ni tane wo maku
My ever-sounding heartbeat always idly sows a seed in my heart
Sono tane ga kibou no hana wo sakasu ka mo shirenai
That seed might bloom into a flower of hope
Dakara kou shite yume wo egaku koto ga dekirunda
That's how I can sketch my dreams like this
Bunansou na nukemichi ga ukande ha kieteku
A loophole that seems safe comes to mind, but then disappears
Sou yatte boku ha tamesarete dou yatte omoi todokeyou?
By doing that, I'm tested; how can I get my feelings across?
Mayowazu ni mae he susunde
Let's advance forward without hesitating
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Dakara kakko tsukenaide kitto hana ha saku hazu sa
So don't try to look cool; I'm sure our flowers have gotta bloom
Bokura ha kagayaku yo Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
We're gonna shine! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Next Time
Even if an infinite number
of enemies appear,
...we indomitable outlaws
will not give way!
I'll Never Forget This Minute, This Second
Next time on
Gurren Lagann,
..."I'll Never Forget This Minute,
This Second."