Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who has yet
to realize what his destiny is.
Adai, a village that worships
an ancient Gunmen as a god.
That place had a cruel rule meant to
ensure the survival of their people.
Still harboring resentment in their hearts,
Simon and Kamina's journey continues,
...having acquired still more
new companions.
Episode 6:
There are Some Things I Just Have to See!!
I don't see anything around here
that seems like a likely candidate.
No doubt about it.
Judging from this map, the recall
point ought to be right here.
Are you sure
we didn't pass it?
It's hard to believe that we could overlook
a facility large enough to launch Gunmen.
I suppose I need to look over
Gurren's data one more time.
Huh?
What's wrong?
It's moving.
- Moving?
- How is that possible?
Beats me. But judging
from the data,
...it would mean that the recall
point itself is moving.
Is that even possible?
I haven't the slightest. It might mean
that this data isn't reliable.
Damn thing is useless!
Huh? What're you doing?
Point your face
somewhere else!
Huh? What? I can't hear
a word you're saying!
What's the matter?
Are you feeling ill?
It stinks!
Stinks?
What stinks?
Where?
You guys reek to high heaven!
Try brushing your teeth and washing up
every once in a while, damn it!
It's some Gunmen!
You out there in the Gunmen!
Listen and be amazed!
Look and be amazed!
My angry flames burn to ash any Gunmen
brazen enough to cross my path!
You face the mighty Kamina, indomitable
leader of the invincible Team Gurren!
Geez, can't he fight without
running his mouth off?
Come at me
however you want!
They hardly put up
a fight at all!
Is it just me, or are these
Gunmen getting weaker?
Awesome! Awesome!
I think it means that
we're getting tougher.
Right, Simon?
Y-You really think so?
Wait a minute.
One of them is getting away.
Yeah, let's kill 'em all!
Kamina, do you suppose we might
arrive at the recall point...
...if we follow that
fleeing Gunmen?
That's it!
Come back here, you long-eared
Gunmen varmint!
Crap, where did it go?!
It's hopeless in this fog.
Hey! Bro!
Something's out there!
A Gunmen?
No, it's too small.
What're you doing
out here, Gramps?
Do you think he can
understand us?
I wonder if there's a village
somewhere around here.
You want us
to go that way?
Hey, pops! What's out here
in the mountains?
Huh? I can see something
up ahead, Bro.
This building is blatantly suspicious.
The air is warm.
And it's giving off steam.
Everyone, we've delivered the old man
safely, so we should leave, and--
You are going inside?
Well, he seems to want us
to follow him!
Maybe he's gonna give us
a reward or something.
Welcome!
This is getting more
and more suspicious.
Something fishy is going on!
Trust me!
Well, well, if it isn't
the mighty Kamina.
"How do you know who I am?"
you are about to ask?
There isn't a single human on the surface
who hasn't heard of Team Gurren.
Not a one!
Your many exploits have given hope
and courage to villagers far and wide,
...prompting them to take
to the surface themselves.
You are the hero of the
entire human race!
You're our hero!
Moron.
Gimmy, you too?
You ladies and gentlemen
by the door, please, join us.
Come in, come in!
This is so fishy!
It may look delicious in one sense,
but in another,
...it might contain poison so deadly
it can kill with a single--
Hey, Rossiu!
You've already eaten
9/10ths of it...
Yeah, and if you don't hurry up,
I'm gonna eat the tenth that's left!
A man's stomach knows no limits!
Keep it coming!
How manly!
Is this safe?
Oh, my!
Kamina!
I knew it, it's Kamina!
- I missed you so!
- Um, who are you?
Don't you remember? We're the three
sisters of the Black Siblings.
Friends of yours?
Yeah.
Yoko, when did you
have kids?
No way!
Did you and Kamina--
As if!
Come to think of it,
where's Kittan?
He had some things to take care of.
We're on our own today.
Actually, we were waiting for him near here,
but then some Gunmen showed up.
Yes, that's right! And then while
we were chasing them,
...this odd haze sprang up,
and just when we got lost--
You were guided here by
a mysterious old man?
Right!
So... Who are you?
Ladies and gentlemen,
once you have eaten your fill,
...feel free to soak away your battle
fatigue in our prized hot spring.
Hot spring?!
Hot spring?
What the hell is that?
You see, hon, a hot spring
is a place where--
This is awesome...
Totally awesome!
Take your time
and enjoy yourselves!
- This hits the spot!
- This feels so wonderful!
Bro, where are Rossiu and Ron?
Don't know, don't care.
Gurren Lagann
This hot spring is great...
Right, Bro?
Hey, Simon?
Yeah, what?
One of these days, you and me
need to try to go to the moon.
Moon?
You mean this?
No, THAT!
I don't think any amount of wishful
thinking will make that happen.
Moron!
Reject common sense to make
the impossible possible!
We made it up here
to the surface, didn't we?
It can't be impossible
to go to the moon!
When you say it, I feel
like we really could.
Come on, stop trying
to feel me up!
Come on, Yoko, your breasts
look so touchable!
Breasts?
Mine are nowhere near
as big as Kiyoh's.
But yours are
shaped better, Yoko.
Shape?
I'm jealous of you two.
Mine are just like THIS.
Like what?
What about me?
Don't worry, Darry. Yours will
get nice and bouncy soon.
Bouncy?
Yeah, they'll fill out, and they might get
so big and bouncy that they'll burst!
W-We shouldn't
be doing this, Bro...
Don't worry, I'll let you see 'em
after I'm done!
See anything, Bro?
Hey, Gimmy!
Find a hole!
Hole?
A hole! Look around
for a hole!
Hole... Hole...
A hole?
A hole!
OW!
Gimmy!
Coming!
Ouch...
Did you see anything, Simon?
See what?
Quit screwing around!
You saw something, DIDN'T you?
Well...
I could see from the
shoulders up...
C'mon, Gimmy!
Poke me in the butt!
Huh? He's gone.
It's so cute!
Come on, let's get those
important bits washed!
Feels so good...
Simon! Your drill!
I'm gonna drill this wall!
Drill it hard!
Please, let's just call it quits!
Do you know what a man's path
is all about, Simon?
It must have mountains,
valleys, and adventure!
You've never seen REAL mountains, have you?
Not if you only saw from the shoulders up.
Don't you want to see them?
Those lovely peaks
and treacherous valleys?
They're so big! And soft!
And they smell so nice!
O-Oh, boy...
I sure do.
Great! You handle this,
and I'll try another approach!
No luck...
I can't see a thing.
Drill, drill, drill...
Bro! I'm through!
Gross! I'm not the least bit
interested in Kamina!
What, really?
I might make a move
on him, then.
F-Feel free,
don't let me stop you!
What about Simon, then?
Pass.
I know what you mean.
Simon's still such a little kid.
He's always latched onto Kamina.
He has no identity of his own.
- He's so unreliable.
- And he's wishy-washy.
He sure is!
But if he worked at it a little harder,
he could become a good man.
What makes you say that?
He might be a mess most of the time,
but he comes through when it counts.
I guess I have a lot
of faith in him.
Well, I'll be! There's something
going on here, all right!
Cut it out!
It's not like that at--
What's the deal?
Did you give up?
Yep.
This is fishy...
Very fishy...
Too suspicious by half...
At long last...
Finally, I've made it!
I have scaled these
lofty heights!
Ready or not, here I come
to where no man has gone--
Damn it, I was so close...
T-This bathhouse was a Gunmen?!
Now, I believe it's time
to begin our human hunt!
Hey, you're a Beastman! Coming out
at night is against the rules!
Sorry, but my kind is nocturnal!
This way! I set them up so they
could be used at a moment's notice!
Thank you!
So warm...
Let's do it, Simon!
Yeah!
I think not!
Look at this!
Damn it, Kamina, hurry up
and rescue us!
She has Yoko and the girls!
That's dirty!
What's this stuff that
makes it so I can...
...sorta make out what's
behind it, but not really?
If you want me to remove
the mosaic filter,
...step out of your Gunmen
this instant!
What?!
Is she kidding? Team Gurren
would never fall for that trick!
Can you... remove those blocks?
Bro?
Forgive me.
Okay, I'm out!
Now, keep your end
of the deal!
M-Moron!
Very well.
DON'T SCREW WITH ME!
Let's combine, Simon!
Bro, look!
You Gurren-nappers!
That was horrible...
The whole bathhouse started
moving all of a sudden.
Where in the world did Kamina
and the others get to?
Why, this is Gurren!
What're we gonna do, Bro?
- Save us, Kamina!
Right! Jump up and latch
onto its face, Simon!
What were you thinking,
you pinhead?!
It was obviously a trap!
What kind of idiot would agree
to get out of his mecha for that?!
Your brains must be rotted out,
you big pervert!
I am so dead, Bro!
Suck it up!
Crap!
Get outta my way, toadies!
Wow! Kamina!
You're safe!
Yoko!
Kamina, you complete moron!
How could you fall for
such a stupid stunt?!
How are you supposed to fight
without Gurren?!
I'm sorry!
There are some things
I just have see!
T-Then you should have
just said so!
If you want to see them that badly,
I can show them to you any time!
That didn't come out
the way I meant it!
L-Look, we need to deal
with this Gunmen!
You're history!
What happened?!
Engine room here! Those women
that escaped are--
Damn them!
Right! Ready to go?
I think not!
W-What?
What's going on?
What the--?
Stay right where you are.
If you try anything else,
...I can easily crush
a few of their ribs.
But you needn't worry.
I won't kill them.
The women will all be sent to
the Spiral King as tributes!
"Spiral King"?
Indeed.
The Spiral King is the mighty god of
this world who resides in the Capital!
Now I understand. He's the final boss...
Meaning he's the root of all evil.
I won't stand for any insults
to the Spiral King.
I see that you need to be
housebroken right away.
Way to go, Gimmy!
Toss it to me!
We have no need of men!
The next time you move, you die!
Now, give that back!
Gimmy, turn the dial!
The other way!
Huh?
Turn it some more!
Give that back!
What're you doing?!
Hurry! Turn it!
Give that back!
Now!
Prove that you're a man!
Turn it, turn it, turn it!
Now!
At long last!
The moment has come!
Wha--?
What the hell?
They lent these to us, saying they
were for use in the outdoor bath.
It's a special service for our customers!
Is there some sort of problem, sir?
A problem? Do I have
a problem?!
You took the heights of the
human spirit, of the male soul,
...and you stomped it into the dirt,
smacked it around, and smashed it!
I'll follow all of you bastards down
to the deepest pits of hell...
...and kill you a million
times over!
Simon!
Bro!
Pile in, everybody!
- We can't all fit!
- I'm falling out!
Close the canopy,
and we'll fit!
It's so cramped...
Won't this make it
too heavy to move?
No, it'll work!
Look! It's Gurren!
Just like you said, Kamina, I was able
to power it with fighting spirit.
Way to go, Forehead Boy!
Okay, let's combine!
Um, shall I get out?
There's no time!
Man's Wrath...
What?!
...Explosive Slash!
We did it! We did it!
We did it!
Good mornin', sunshine...
W-What was that?!
It's been a long time, naked ape!
Um, who's this guy again?
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
There are times when a man's gotta do
what a man's gotta do.
Sometime, somewhere,
maybe here, maybe there,
...you might come across
a golden opportunity.
Whether you live or die
is up to your ability!
You're Gonna Do It!
Next time on Gurren Lagann,
"You're Gonna Do It!"