Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
Their powerful enemy Viral returns, and
Thymilph of the Four Generals appears.
Comrades gather together.
Amidst this suddenly
intensifying battle,
...Kamina and Simon learn of the
existence of the Spiral King.
To confront this
as-yet unseen enemy,
...Kamina resolves to capture the gigantic
land battleship Dai-Gunzan.
Volcanoes belch fire and rip
the heavens and earth asunder.
The stage is set
for the final showdown.
And the man will learn
his destiny.
Y-Yoko!
Ah, so this is
where you went.
I couldn't get to sleep.
You're under a lot of pressure. After all,
you're the key to today's operation.
Well, that's part of it...
Yoko...
The thing is, I...
Those are called volcanoes.
Those fire-breathing mountains.
There's molten magma bubbling
away inside the Earth's crust,
...and it comes shooting out
from the center of the earth.
Ron told me about them.
They're just like Kamina, then.
It burns underground until it can't be
contained anymore, and then it explodes.
Sounds just like him,
don't you think?
What?
Kamina said exactly
the same thing.
"That's exactly like me!"
he said.
Is that the old "male bond"
at work, or what?
No, not exactly.
Here.
This is hot, too,
so be careful.
If you go into battle hungry, Lagann won't
be running at full power, either.
Thanks.
Say, Simon...
It's nothing, forget it.
Good luck.
Here, sorry to
keep you waiting.
I knew you could do it, Leeron.
I don't think I'll be missing with this.
It's rare for you to let someone
else do maintenance on your gun.
Because failure isn't an option today.
You understand, I see.
Gurren Lagann is far more powerful
than Gurren on its own.
It's defensive ability, too.
If Kamina rushes in like he usually does,
there's no telling what will happen.
He's not the sort of man who will stop now,
no matter what we say to him.
I'll try to keep him safe.
Honestly, that man
is such a pain.
You're quite a pain in
the patootie, yourself.
Here.
If you eat too much,
won't that slow you down?
I need power.
Especially today.
Yoko, watch my back.
I'll crush anything that comes
at me from up ahead.
So I need you to deal with
anything from behind.
Kamina.
Your back is one big
blind spot, isn't it?
What are you--
I'll pay that back ten times over.
When we get back,
I'll repay that ten times over.
Mark my words.
What's with you?
Don't you think you could phrase
that a little more romantically?
Now, let's head out there
and raise a little hell!
Kamina. I'm looking forward
to being repaid.
Sure!
What the hell?
Must be a case of nerves.
It's none of my business!
What she does is none
of my damn business!
W-What's wrong?!
Uh, it's nothing.
It's only natural
at a time like this.
Don't worry about it.
I know you can do this.
S-Sure...
Let's get out there,
blood brother!
All right, listen up!
This plan is straightforward!
First off, we Gunmen pilots will attack
to draw out the enemy's Gunmen.
In the meantime, Simon will
use Lagann to combine...
...with that behemoth's head
to take control of it from them!
Then, we'll use the captured behemoth
to crush the enemy Gunmen!
At that point, the fight is ours!
Are we clear?!
Yeah!
We get it! We hit 'em,
and hit 'em hard!
I made arrangements for the Gunmen pilots
to be able to speak to one another.
Of course, I don't think they're the
sort who listen to what they're told,
...but if you want to live, I suggest
that you remain in contact.
Um... Yeah!
We make contact!
Then we smash!
All right, you bozos!
Let's get to it!
Team Dai-Gurren, move out!
Yeah!
You guys are in charge of
keeping this place safe!
Leave it to us, big brother!
You can do it!
Thanks for the lift.
It's always an honor to
have a lady on board.
Yoko, no fair!
Simon, good luck!
Good luck.
Isn't this awesome, Simon?
When we left the village,
Team Gurren was just us two.
And now, we're heading out to pick a fight
with the Beastmen with all these buddies.
This is so damn awesome...
Boota says he was there, too.
Hey, you're right. I forgot.
Sorry about that.
Team Gurren was two guys
and one pig-mole.
I was there, too,
if you recall.
When you left your village,
I was there, too.
Oh, you were?
You don't remember?
Well, either way, you weren't in
Team Gurren back then, Yoko.
How can you say that?
We can hear every word, Yoko!
All comm channels are open.
I just explained, remember?
If we're this relaxed, we'll do fine.
We can win this fight, right, Kamina?
Of course we can!
Who the hell do you think I am?!
Keep everything else out of your mind.
Concentrate, Simon!
Gurren Lagann
It's in your hands now, everyone.
What are those?
One is connected to Lagann's systems,
and the other to Gurren's.
Care to help?
Sure.
Me, too! Me, too!
Now, now! If you touch that,
I'm gonna gobble you up!
Okay!
- Let's do it!
- Yeah!
We've been waiting!
We knew that you would
try to sneak up on us!
We were counting on it!
Boulders?
Suck rocks, furballs!
Damn! Barbaric humans!
Can't you meet us fist to fist?
This rock IS my fist!
A rock is a rock!
It's not a fist!
Stating the obvious is your idea
of a defiant speech? Dumbass!
You dare mock me?!
Just a moment, Viral.
It's unbecoming to get riled up over
every foolish thing these humans say.
Such paltry attacks won't so much
as dent Dai-Gunzan!
Laugh THIS off!
How dare you stinking humans!
Dai-Gunzan, activate!
Open all gun ports!
Send them flying!
Catapult Arm, stand by!
Throw!
Not a chance!
Kamina! This time, I'm getting
my helmet back!
You're STILL whining about that?
I never pegged you for the stingy type.
Its face is missing!
Damn you, where is your head?!
Now!
Get going, Simon!
Enemy detected overhead!
Twelve o'clock high!
Shoot him down!
There's a blind spot overhead. Our flak
curtain doesn't completely cover us.
Try to do something
using fighting spirit!
We have the edge in spirit, too!
Get in there, Simon!
Lagann Impact!
That was close!
General Thymilph,
you're in danger here!
What are you trying to do?!
We merged 'em! We merged our
Lagann with your Dai-Gunzan!
You've what?!
That behemoth is now ours!
Damn you, Kamina,
you set us up!
Yeah, that I did!
I put our luck and our
mettle to the test!
How did he get so good
so quickly?!
Nice shooting, Yoko!
I gave you my word! I've got your back,
so you can fight Viral without worrying.
I'm gonna run!
Hold on!
Those two are good!
I'm not gonna let 'em win, either!
Hey! What's the
big idea, Simon?
Sorry, it wasn't on purpose!
I can't control it very well, that's all!
Sounds like the combining
isn't going smoothly.
He can't completely synch up with
the enemy's control systems.
I wonder if he's worried
about something?
Lagann's power is tied in to
Simon's mental state, right?
Can't you regain control?
I'm sorry, sir.
It's still unresponsive.
This must be the work of that
Gunmen that's only a face.
Are they seriously trying to
take over my Dai-Gunzan?
I'll go tear him loose myself!
In my Byakou!
What's the matter, Simon?
What's the holdup?
I'm trying! I'm trying,
but it's not working!
Why?! Why is that keeping me
from concentrating?! Damn it!
You blew it during
your endgame, Kamina.
Ignore the small fry! Everyone return
to Dai-Gunzan at once!
You're not going anywhere!
You guys keep the Gunmen pinned down!
I'll see what I can do about Simon!
Yeah!
Open the hatch, Simon!
Let's see you grit those teeth!
Bro?
Have you snapped out of it?
If you ever start to doubt yourself,
I'll always come to belt you one.
So don't worry,
I'm here at your side.
Believe in yourself.
Believe in the Simon
that I have faith in.
You got it!
Amazing!
You're doing well, Simon!
Very well, indeed!
You're synchronizing steadily!
Just a little more!
See, you can do it if you--
Bro?
Kamina?!
I won't hand over
my Dai-Gunzan so easily!
Thymilph?!
Damn, I didn't--
You forgot this.
You can have it back.
You son of a...
Alkaid Glaive!
You're a tenacious man,
I'll give you that.
But this is the end
of the line for you!
It can't be...
I don't believe it...
Bro!
What's happened?!
General Thymilph, look out!
Viral!
What the hell happened?!
Dai-Gunzan has gone berserk!
If it stays on course, it'll fall into
the mouth of the volcano!
Pull yourself together, Simon!
Do you read me?!
Can't a guy get a little sleep
around here?
Simon, stop!
Simon!
It's no use...
I can't do anything...
There's nothing I can do now.
Simon! Let's see you
grit those teeth!
Bro? You're alive!
Simon, who the hell do
you think you are?
Your drill is the drill that's gonna
bore through heaven and earth,
...and even tomorrow!
What're you sitting here dawdling for?
We've won, kid!
That behemoth belongs
to you now.
You don't have to worry
about anything now.
Bro... You're right!
Everybody! Everything's okay now!
Dai-Gunzan is ours!
Come on aboard!
You damn dirty humans...
I received that as a gift from
the Spiral King himself!
I'd sooner destroy it than see it
fall into your hands!
That old furball doesn't know
when to give up, does he?
Come on, Simon.
Let's send these clowns packing.
Combine. We'll use Gurren Lagann
to do this last mission!
You got it, Bro!
Let's do it!
We brawlers are sustained by willpower
even when mocked as crazy and reckless!
If there's a wall in our way,
we smash it down!
If there isn't a path,
we carve one out ourselves!
The magma of our souls
burns with a mighty flame!
Super Ultra Combining,
Gurren Lagann!
Who...
...the hell...
--do you think we are?!
There's nobody else like them.
Stand your ground!
Kill them! Kill them!
Make tracks, cannon fodder!
Damn you...
Condemn Blaze!
You'll have to do better
than that!
I-Impossible!
Listen close, Simon.
Never forget.
Believe in yourself.
Not in the Simon that I believe in.
Not in the Kamina that you believe in.
Have faith in the Simon
that believes in you.
Bro?
Finishing move!
Giga Drill Break!
Later, buddy...
Bro?
That day, we lost something
that could never be replaced.
Episode 8:
Later, Buddy
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
Dark, sunken eyes.
Feelings that can't be suppressed.
This wetness striking my cheek,
is this "rain"?
Next time on Gurren Lagann,
"What, Exactly, Is A Human?"
What, Exactly, Is A Human?