Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who has yet
to realize what his destiny is.
Simon's Lagann and Kamina's Gurren
perfect their combination technique,
...and the result is named
Gurren Lagann.
Their journey in search of the enemy's
headquarters continues. However...
You know, we haven't seen
any Gunmen lately.
You have a point. I don't want
my skills to get rusty.
What're you doing
in here, anyway?
We built you guys a place
out of wreckage, didn't we?
This is the best place to be
while we're underway.
That thing bounces around so much,
it's murder on my butt.
You sure it's not 'cause
your ass is too big?
What did you say?!
Ah, this is so comfy!
Geez, you're heavy!
You sure your brains haven't settled
into your ass, you dumb broad?
Oh, you don't say?
Sounds to me like you want a taste
of one of my meatball bullets.
No, not those!
The surface around here seems to have
been made comparatively recently.
How recent is "recently"?
Oh, about four or five
hundred years, I'd say.
Ow! Don't shoot, you crazy bitch!
You'll kill me!
These little things won't
kill you, you big baby!
They never get tired
of fighting, do they?
Kamina and Yoko
fell through.
What an enormous cavern!
I've never seen anything like it!
How far down
does this thing go?!
Episode 5:
I Don't Get it, Not One Bit!
Good thing I came
around first...
People have come from
the Face God!
Messengers from the
Celestial Lands!
Face God?
That's a--
That's a Gunmen!
- What a wreck...
- Please don't touch that!
That is our village's
guardian deity.
Yo, Forehead Boy! Don't you have
more to throw on the fire?
My name is Rossiu.
This is all we have here.
This place is a barrel
of laughs, ain't it?
Hey! Don't be rude!
Hey! Did you guys really come from
the Celestial Lands?
Are you messengers
of the Face God?
What's the deal with these kids?
Stop bothering our guests,
Gimmy, Darry.
Go somewhere else.
Okay...
I'm terribly sorry. Those children have
no parents, so everyone spoils them.
Who cares about that?
More importantly, what's that
Gunmen doing there?
Gunmen? You mean
the Face God?
Wait, you don't know
what that is?
Hah, you weren't any different
not too long ago.
What the hell?! What did I do to
deserve all this grief from you?
Oh, shut up!
Um, Yoko?
Yes?
I'm sorry, but would you
mind putting this on?
Why?
Well, um... Perhaps you
could cover up?
Your manner of dress is...
Well, it is indecent!
I'm not crazy about outfits like this
that restrict my movements.
What now?
Boy, take away the bare midriff,
and you got nothing left, do ya?
Scum! Thug!
Stinking louse!
You are one hopeless pervert
of a man, you know that?
Don't pick up his habits,
okay, Simon?
Please stop this
violent behavior!
I would expect Celestians to refrain from
such lewd conduct in front of our villagers.
Celestians?
These people are Celestians?
Yes, they travel in the
company of Face Gods.
Please show them
all due respect.
Rossiu!
Yes, what is it?
T-There's a problem!
Ucom's wife just gave birth!
But that is good news!
I was about to suggest to our guests
that we visit the High Priest.
The thing is, one child is a girl,
and the second is a boy.
As is the third!
What?!
Huh? Why are they
freaking out?
Triplets?
To Ucom and his wife?
Yes.
So, that brings the village's
population to 52.
We must choose two, then.
Must we go through
with this, Father Magin?
Rossiu, do you not understand?
This rite bestows a great blessing.
We will celebrate the chosen,
just as we did with your mother.
Man, this place is depressing.
Old Giha Village was nothing like this.
Is it time to eat yet?
Isn't that what this is?
This ain't enough!
I need me some meat...
I wanna have meat!
I suspect that this is
a grand welcome for us.
They have no electricity.
No herds of livestock.
All they have here is a tiny pond
and a broken Gunmen.
Which means that even a meal
like this is precious.
My apologies. Was the meal
not to your liking?
If it is not too much trouble, might I impose
on you to tell me of the Celestial Lands?
Really, Forehead Boy?
Does that mean you want more
than the life of a celler dweller?
Then let me get this out of the way!
Gunmen are no gods!
But that has been our belief
since long before I was born.
Your people have always
lived like this?
No, they say that our lot has improved
considerably since the High Priest...
...took over the administration
of the village.
This High Priest guy,
who is he?
Celestians, please do not test
this boy's piety any further.
Your words are too much
for our people to accept.
You're the High Priest?
I apologize for neglecting
to introduce myself.
I am called Magin,
and I govern this village.
Is that a fact? You're the head honcho
of this little dump, huh?
Rossiu, we have an important
ceremony tomorrow. Go to bed.
Yes, Father.
You and your friends should
turn in for the night, as well.
If you will excuse me...
Bro?!
Are you some kind of moron?!
I don't like that guy.
Not his ugly mug, and definitely not
that holier-than-thou attitude.
Gurren Lagann
Wow, the thing still works!
Good morning.
Take it for a spin, Forehead Boy.
The key to making it work is spirit!
I had no intention of doing so...
Put everything else out of your head!
Just do what feels natural!
It's a great feeling.
Rossiu!
F-Father Magin!
There he is again.
What are you doing, Rossiu?
Who told you that you may
touch the Face God?
I-I apologize.
Hang on a minute, old-timer!
It finally came to me.
Bro...
I was trying to figure out why your
ugly mug pisses me off so much,
...and I realized that you look like
the chief of our old village.
Right, Simon?
Hm, maybe he does...
You and your friends...
Oh, you wanna fight?
...ought to leave this village if you
have no further business here.
Say what?!
Huh?
Father Magin, surely it does
not need to be held now.
All three of these children
might not survive.
Please do not misunderstand, Ucom.
Those chosen during this rite
receive the gods' blessing.
Now, please draw.
T-Then I'll draw for my wife
and children, too.
Next, please.
Yes, Father.
Is there anyone who
has not drawn a lot yet?
Gimmy hasn't gone yet!
Neither has Darry!
Oh, my apologies.
You two are the last, then.
Now, open your hands.
If your lot has a mark, you have
been chosen by the gods.
She won!
Darry won!
So did you, Gimmy!
Hey, you're right!
We both won!
- Yay, we won!
- We won!
We won, we won!
What are you saying?
What do you mean,
take these kids with us?
Whenever the village's
population exceeds 50,
...some are chosen to be the gods' children
and are sent up to the Celestial Lands.
Celestial Lands?
You mean the surface?!
But that's crazy!
You can't send these kids there!
That is your answer, then?
You handle rejection better
than I expected, old-timer.
I don't think that's
what he means, Bro.
You leave us with
no choice, then.
We will conduct our ceremony
in the usual manner.
Wait just a damn minute! What's one
or two more kids running around?
You don't have to
throw them out!
To be sent up to the Celestial Lands
means to be released...
...from all the sorrows of this life
and to live together with the gods.
It is the ultimate happiness.
Why does it have to be this way?
I don't get it, not one bit!
Hasn't anybody ever considered going up
to see what it's really like up there?
C'mon, take us there!
What're the
Celestial Lands like?
It ain't exactly paradise up there!
We can't drag two kids around with us!
Why not?!
- You're mean!
- Meanie!
Would you please stop berating our ways
every chance you get?
Excuse me?!
Look, old-timer, don't try
to play the victim here!
How dare you!
Mind your tone when speaking
to the High Priest!
Let it go, Bro. It's their law
here in this village.
It's not like they're doing it
because they want to.
If you don't WANT to do it, all they
have to do is STOP doing it!
Who the hell do you
think I am?
I'm Kamina, who would rather die than
do something he doesn't wanna do!
Listen up, people! This guy's a fraud
who's been feeding you a load of crap!
Don't fall for it!
Please stop this! What do you
know of life in our village?
Ah, you're finally starting
to speak my language.
Stop this, Rossiu!
Don't resort to violence!
I don't understand! How can these people
be messengers of the gods?
Endure this trial.
The gods are testing us.
C'mon, kiddo!
Stop it this instant, Rossiu!
The mighty Kamina is ready
to take you on!
Yo, Forehead Boy!
What are you, man or mouse?
Man or mouse?!
What the hell?!
It's another Face God!
Gurren Lagann, I found you!
Get moving, Kamina!
Simon!
Thanks, Yoko!
What do you think you're
doing to the Face God?
The gods will smite you!
This is getting old...
Bro!
Ready!
Let's do this with style!
Brotherly Combining!
Gurren Lagann!
One Face God is fighting
another Face God!
How can this be?!
You guys down there!
What're you standing around for?!
You're in the way!
Get clear! Hurry!
These things are no gods!
They're the enemy!
They're the enemy
we fight against!
Bro, it's no use!
These people have believed that Gunmen
are gods their whole lives!
In that case, we're gonna kick this
thing's ass right in front of them!
That'll make 'em see sense
whether they want to or not!
Bro, you're overdoing it!
Butt out!
W-What the--?
The idol!
What are you doing?
Don't interfere, you piece ofjunk!
What the hell?
What is going on here,
Father Magin?
Father Magin!
I don't like you.
I don't like you at all, old-timer.
If you had that much spirit
all along, why didn't you--
I mimicked what I saw
you do, that's all.
I myself do not understand
what I was doing.
I beg you, it is time
for you to leave.
Don't disturb our village any more
than you already have.
Say what?!
Let it go, Bro!
What he says is right. We don't
belong here in this village.
I don't get it. I don't get it,
not one damn bit.
Perhaps we should
tell everyone the truth.
What is the truth, Rossiu?
If the truth would destroy this village,
do they need to know it?
This village does not have the resources
to sustain a large population.
The first thing I did when I became
leader of the village...
...was to set a limit of 50 on
the people who may live here.
We must not exceed that number,
not even by one.
If we succumb to sentimentality
or emotion, the village is lost.
For me, that is the
one and only truth.
My religion is nothing more
than a tool to that end.
Did you also arrange it so that Gimmy
and Darry would be chosen?
Yes, because those children
have no family.
That way, few would
truly grieve for them.
You're joking! If that's true,
then what about my mother?
Any regrets I once had,
I made my peace with long ago.
Take these, too.
But we can't eat
this much!
You mustn't eat it all at once.
Eat it a little at a time and make it last.
Okay!
Rossiu! You mean to go
through with this?
Yes. I will go with
those children.
Once we reclaim the surface
as a home for humanity,
...there will no longer be any need
to be bound by such painful laws.
Besides, won't it be easier for you if no one
else in the village knows the truth?
I understand.
In that case, would you like to take the
holy scriptures with you on your journey?
Thank you but I...
I no longer believe.
And besides, I thought you knew!
I cannot read.
Oh, is that all? You needn't
worry about that, Rossiu.
I can't read, either!
This may be no more than
dead weight to you now,
...but I would like you
to take it with you.
Please, accept it.
Yes, Father.
To Be Continued...
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
If it's invisible,
you want to see it!
If you're told not to look,
you can't resist peeking!
If it's hidden,
you want to see it!
That's what a man's adventure
is all about!
Next time on
Gurren Lagann,
There Are Some Things
I Just Have to See!!
..."There Are Some Things
I Just Have to See!!"