Gurren Lagann
Sugita kisetsu wo nageku hima ha nai
I don't have the time to lament the seasons that have passed
Nido to mayotte shimawanu you ni
So that I won't ever waver again
Kazoekirenai hon no sasayaka na
With countless, tiny little
Sonna koukai kakaeta mama
Regrets carried in my arms
Sono senaka dake oikakete koko made kitanda
I've come this far, having chased only after your back
Sagashite ita boku dake ni dekiru koto
It's something only I, who sought you, can do
Ano hi kureta kotoba ga ima demo
Those words you gave me that day, even now,
Kono mune ni tashika ni todoite iru kara
Definitely reach my heart
Kinou yori mo kyou ha bu ha boku no
I've realized my reason for having been born
Umarete kita wake ni kidzuite yuku
Today more than I did yesterday
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who blows
a hole in the fate of a universe...
...that is ruled by the endless
cycle of violence.
At long last, the location of the Anti-Spiral's
home planet has been discovered.
The ring that Simon gave to Nia
was picked up by their Spiral scan.
Indeed, if they travel there,
he will see Nia.
To save the woman he loves,
Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren
to save the Earth on which his friends live,
...and to put an end to the conflict once and for all,
...the Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren sets sail,
with Simon on board.
No. 1 Bridge
Spiral Monitor activated.
Spiral Real Perceptual Teleportation System,
...dimensional coordinates verified.
Simon, focus your perception
on Nia.
I still can't believe it...
The place where Nia is being held
is incredibly far away, right?
Can we really use that thing
to jump to her?
All their talk goes way
over my head, too.
But I guess I can understand it
if it boils down to...
...Simon and Nia being connected by
feelings that transcend time and space.
If you say so...
I have confirmation.
Coordinate lock achieved.
Okay, Simon! We're ready
to jump at any time!
Listen up, everyone!
Space Grapearl Squadron Hangar
We're about to jump to the Anti-Spiral's stronghold.
I don't know what we'll find
waiting for us there,
...but no matter what happens,
we can't afford to lose.
No matter what it takes,
Space Gunmen Squadron Hangar
we'll win and we'll keep our Earth safe.
Can you believe this?
How far are we gonna go?
- That's easy.
- As far as it takes.
As far as it takes!
Yeah, we go wherever
we have to go!
Y'know?
Let's go. This is Team Dai-Gurren's
last fight!
Engines at full!
Spiral Real Perceptual
Teleportation System, activate!
Episode 24:
I Will Never Forget This Minute, This Second
What the hell?
We're there already?
This is where their
big boss is?
There's a giant, naked lady
out there in space!
Idiot, what are you talking--
Nia!
You came for me!
Sure. I gave you my word,
didn't I?
I had faith that you would.
Hang on,
I'll rescue you soon.
So is that the real Nia?
I don't see how. It looks like a holographic
projection or something like that.
Be careful, Simon. The Anti-Spiral
are more powerful than you think.
Don't worry about us.
I'll win, no matter what.
We'll win, and we'll all go
back to Earth together.
Nia!
- What's happening to her body?
- It's being analyzed.
Being analyzed?
Nia was born on Earth
and grew up among humans.
Knowledge regarding Earth's humanity
is stored within her body.
However...
Why now? What need do they have to
analyze that information at this point?
If what we're seeing is a projection,
where is the real Nia being kept?
Let's try jumping again.
This time, we'll go to
where the real Nia is!
What the hell is this?
It's just like last time!
Ah, now I understand. That fake Nia
is actively interfering with our jumps.
Crap! One more time!
Foolish people of the Spiral.
- Who's there?!
- Anti-Spiral...
That voice is them?
Where is the voice
coming from?
It's coming from
all directions simultaneously!
How can that be?
This is a malleable universe. They can
control it according to their every whim.
It is no exaggeration to say that
our enemy is the universe itself.
The universe itself...?
You cling to the faintest
slivers of hope,
...climbing up time and time again
from the precipice of despair.
The foolishness of it all...
But that is now at an end.
Your last ember of hope will flicker
and go out when this girl vanishes.
If Nia disappears, it will no longer
be possible to track their homeworld.
No way am I gonna
let them do that!
It's huge...!
Behold.
And learn.
These are your absolute despair
given form.
We don't know the meaning
of the word despair!
Aretenborough!
You got it!
What was that?!
An energy barrier.
Just like the Mugann have.
Or even more powerful!
Then we know what
we have to do!
We're going out in
Arch-Gurren Lagann!
Right.
Geez, Leyte, when did you have time
to make these monsters?
Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren's production
capacity is downright terrifying.
You guys don't really
need me anymore.
As if!
Nobody but you could've come up with
fighting something big with something big.
Anyway, it's in your hands now.
- Sure!
- Count on us.
I'm counting on you,
too, darling.
Activity detected
from enemy ships!
Enemy ships are launching fighters!
There's a huge number of them!
Ship count is... off the charts!
Check it out! Enemy fighters
as far as the eye can see!
Simon, we'll clear a path for you!
You can take it from there!
Understood!
Okay, bozos, one last brawl! And I don't
wanna see anybody holding back!
Of course not!
I have kids waiting for me back home,
so I'm gonna give it everything I have!
Y-You have kids?!
Hey, when the hell
did you have kids?!
A lady has to have
a few secrets, you know?
S-Secrets?
Contact with enemy formation
in 10 seconds!
Right!
Let's do it!
There's a ton of these guys,
but they ain't so tough!
We'll keep whittling them down.
Focus on attacking the enemy!
Right!
Now, Simon!
Hit it!
This is bad! We can't
take much more of this!
Hang in there!
We've almost got it!
Crap!
- Simon! Are you okay?!
- Yeah.
Viral, let's give it
another shot!
We were damaged pretty badly.
And that thing is just too big.
This thing's drill
isn't enough!
You mean we need an
even bigger drill?
But where can we find
something like that?
I know where there's one!
Leyte?
If you transform the Super Galaxy
Dai-Gurren into humanoid mode,
...you'll be able to use its drills!
Transform?
Indeed.
The human form is the one in which Spiral
Power is manifested most powerfully.
If you transform Super Galaxy
Dai-Gurren into humanoid mode,
...it will amplify our Spiral Power
tens of times over,
...becoming a being which possesses
power rivaling that of a micro cosmos.
In other words, Super Galaxy
Gurren Lagann, huh?
It is not that simple.
To transform so vast a vessel, it is necessary
to funnel similarly vast quantities...
...of Spiral Power directly
into the main engine.
At the moment, the only person
possessing sufficient Spiral Power--
Is me, huh?
Looks like we have
no other options.
Looks that way.
Simon, leave these guys to us,
...and you go transform Super Galaxy
Gurren Lagann ASAP.
But are you guys gonna be okay
without Arch-Gurren Lagann?
Kittan!
Hey, now... Who the hell
do you think we are?
We wanna do a little
grandstanding, too.
We'll buy you the time
you need.
You're gonna owe us one
for this, Simon.
- Yeah! You owe us!
- You repay us soon!
I'll be right back with a huge drill.
I'm counting on you, guys.
Okay, it's time for Team Dai-Gurren
to take center stage!
Listen up, bozos! Let's take 'em down
in serious style!
Yeah!
Wait for me, everybody...
Gurren Lagann
Space Sunbeam!
Damn it, they're having
all the fun!
Gimmy, you're drifting in
too far.
You're part of the
Grapearl Squadron!
Aw, man...
Rear guard duty stinks.
Maybe, but that's the job
we were assigned.
Enemy battleship
has begun to move.
It's advancing,
heading right for us.
Now that she mentions it, it worries me
that those big things haven't attacked us.
I wonder if they're part
of some kind of trap?
Fall back! For the time being,
maintain our distance!
Inside Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren,
Ultra Spiral Powerplant
Concentrate on charging up our Spiral energy!
Inside Arch-Gurren Lagann,
Ultra Spiral Powerplant
Inside Gurren Lagann,
Ultra Spiral Powerplant (Simon)
Leyte, how much longer?
Transformation will be possible with another 48%.
Another ten minutes
or so.
I'll make sure everything is ready
on this end before then.
Understood.
Keep your cool.
But even I can see now that your
Spiral Power is off the charts.
You're one impressive specimen.
Still, I have a bad feeling
about this somehow.
What's this vibe I'm getting?
Kittan!
Hey, Kittan!
What's up, Yoko?
Doesn't this seem strange to you?
These guys are just too weak!
Come on, it just means that
WE are just too badass!
Splash number 108!
What's this?
Form up?
Gimmy! There's the rally signal!
Let's head back to the Dai-Gurren.
Form up, huh?
Damn, things were just getting good...
What the hell?!
What?!
What's up with these guys?
They got fast and agile all of a sudden--
They were faking it!
Those Grapearls can't handle 'em!
We'll provide cover!
Grapearl Squadron, return to
the Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren!
Kittan! Zorthy's gotten
himself into trouble.
Kid and I are gonna
go rescue him.
Dumbass! Weren't you listening?!
We're supposed to fall back!
You want us to abandon him?!
All right, I'll come with you!
Wait a minute, Kittan!
Hey, now.
This is OUR job.
Yours is to look after
the rookies, right?
Iraak!
You heard the man.
We'll leave you to it.
- See ya!
- Kid!
Crap! You better come back,
you hear me?!
'Cuz if you don't,
I'm gonna kick your ass!
Yoko! Makken!
Jorgun, Balinbow!
We'll follow the Grapearls
and cover their backs!
Damn it...
Get off me, bastard!
Son of a bitch!
Zorthy! We're on our way!
Hold out for a little bit longer!
Kid!
I'm in trouble here. My ejection
system ain't working, either.
I came a long way,
didn't I?
Zorthy!
You bastards!
Multiple high-temp thermal signatures have
been launched from the enemy battleships.
Predicted target is this vessel!
How many?!
Thirteen in total!
Lordgenome! Do we have any
interceptor missiles?
Of course.
Aretenborough!
You got it!
All missiles, fire!
Missiles?!
Darry! We're gonna shoot down anything
that gets through our flak curtain!
Roger!
Thermal signatures now making
contact with interceptor missiles!
How many did we get?
Half of them!
Six are left!
Leave the rest to us!
Four left!
Sorry, Kid.
I'm outta ammo over here.
Yeah, same here. Guess we're
in sync right to the very end...
Simon!
There's a lady waiting for you,
so don't break her heart.
That you, Iraak?
Simon.
Get Nia back, you hear?
Kid...
One last fight, partner.
Let's show 'em...
...that Team Gurren
never gives in!
Kid! Iraak!
Selfish bastards went and
bought it without us...
Giant missile reading detected
coming through a warp gate!
We're not gonna let 'em have
things their way anymore.
- Oh, no!
- It's too close!
Second missile inbound!
Darry! You're too close
to take the shot!
But I have to take it down!
Darry!
Another gate reading,
this time from the port stern!
From the opposite side this time?!
Take evasive action!
There's not enough time!
We made it?
By our defensive shield?
Yes. But it could not have
handled a direct hit.
Someone must have
rammed the missile.
It was Makken.
I picked up Mo-Shogun's signal
at the very last second.
Makken...
Darling...
Spiral energy charge is at 95%!
Get ready, everybody!
- Darry, are you okay?
- Gimmy?
We're going back to the
Dai-Gurren together!
Gimmy, you'll never make it back
if you're towing me!
Run by yourself!
Dumbass! I can't do that,
and you know it!
Damn it...
- Gimmy! Darry!
- You okay?!
Jorgun! Balinbow!
Okay, now we go home!
This isn't good...
We won't last all the way back!
It all right, our Twinboekun
is as tough as it gets!
I see ship!
You're right!
What do you think
you're doing?!
Gimmy! You protect Darry!
You live well!
Enough for us, too!
Jorgun! Balinbow!
I'll never forget.
I will never forget
this minute, this second...
Threshold achieved.
That did it, Simon!
Begin transformation!
Gravity field emanating
off the port side!
- What in the world is that wall?
- I'm not picking up anything on radar!
- How can there be a sea in space?!
- How can this be?
Our energy!
Simon, we're in trouble!
Get us out of it!
Dayakka, hurry!
It's no use!
We don't have enough power!
The Spiral gauge
is falling steadily!
What?!
It is a trap.
We walked right into it?
To Be Continued...
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Nariyamanai kodou ga itsumo itazura ni kokoro ni tane wo maku
My ever-sounding heartbeat always idly sows a seed in my heart
Sono tane ga kibou no hana wo sakasu ka mo shirenai
That seed might bloom into a flower of hope
Dakara kou shite yume wo egaku koto ga dekirunda
That's how I can sketch my dreams like this
Bunansou na nukemichi ga ukande ha kieteku
A loophole that seems safe comes to mind, but then disappears
Sou yatte boku ha tamesarete dou yatte omoi todokeyou?
By doing that, I'm tested; how can I get my feelings across?
Mayowazu ni mae he susunde
Let's advance forward without hesitating
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Dakara kakko tsukenaide kitto hana ha saku hazu sa
So don't try to look cool; I'm sure our flowers have gotta bloom
Bokura ha kagayaku yo Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
We're gonna shine! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Next Time
This sea in space
is a Spiral graveyard!
Countless crushed hopes
lie buried in its darkness.
We will find tomorrow's victory using the
flower that blossoms in the face of death!
I Accept Your Last Wish
Next time on
Gurren Lagann,
..."I Accept Your Last Wish."