Gurren Lagann
Sugita kisetsu wo nageku hima ha nai
I don't have the time to lament the seasons that have passed
Nido to mayotte shimawanu you ni
So that I won't ever waver again
Kazoekirenai hon no sasayaka na
With countless, tiny little
Sonna koukai kakaeta mama
Regrets carried in my arms
Sono senaka dake oikakete koko made kitanda
I've come this far, having chased only after your back
Sagashite ita boku dake ni dekiru koto
It's something only I, who sought you, can do
Ano hi kureta kotoba ga ima demo
Those words you gave me that day, even now,
Kono mune ni tashika ni todoite iru kara
Definitely reach my heart
Kinou yori mo kyou ha bu ha boku no
I've realized my reason for having been born
Umarete kita wake ni kidzuite yuku
Today more than I did yesterday
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who continues
to look for his own path,
...even while he is being
betrayed by fate.
Two weeks remain until the moon
slams into the Earth's surface.
To quell the panic
of the populace,
...Rossiu pursues charges of
war crimes against Simon.
Simon is sentenced
to death.
After his final mission
in Gurren Lagann,
...what does he find waiting for him
in the prison he is sent to?
Welcome to prison,
Supreme Commander Simon.
Oh, right. You aren't Supreme
Commander anymore, are you?
Now you're Simon the war criminal.
We still get news from the
outside world in here.
It's interesting,
don't you think, Simon?
Both the Beastman rebel and the
hero of the human liberation...
...are imprisoned as equals
thanks to those "trials" of yours.
Human wisdom has its moments.
Two more weeks...
What... is this?
Episode 20:
How Far Will God Test Us?
Evacuation percentage of all
Gekorn region areas, 68%.
Sakunga region, 32%.
Behama region, 44%.
In the remaining 6 days, 18 hours,
evacuation will be 98% complete.
Evacuation of Kamina City residents
aboard the Arc-Gurren is at 58%.
It is proceeding smoothly.
Leeron, what is the moon's status?
Falling slowly.
Current calculations show it will
make atmospheric entry...
...in 10 days, 6 hours,
and 23 minutes.
The moon will also begin to affect
the surface as it gets closer.
Let's get everyone into their
shelters as soon as possible.
Yes, sir.
You wear the mantle of leader well,
Supreme Commander Rossiu.
That doesn't matter. I'm doing what
must be done, nothing more.
My goodness!
You've grown into quite a man.
Would you care to join me
on a date?
There's something I'd like
to tell you in person.
That's right.
Okay, I'll be waiting.
I just hope he doesn't
get burned out.
Even if we eat, the moon's gonna hit
pretty soon and end everything, right?
Yeah, we have some Supreme Commander
to thank for that.
I won't turn down
the food, though.
Save us once again, o mighty
Supreme Commander!
I hear the people outside have
been evacuated underground.
What the--?
Who the hell are you?
I'll avenge
General Cytomander's death!
Cytomander? One of the Spiral King's
Four Generals?
That's right! If you hadn't killed him,
I'd still be flying in the sky right now!
Look at what they've
done to me!
When they locked me in here,
they cut my wings off!
I'm pathetic!
I'm a disgrace!
And it's all your fault, Simon!
DIE!
V-Viral...
The weaker the bird,
the shriller the squawking.
Why don't you shut your beak
for a while?
You're siding with Simon, you bastard?
And you call yourself a Beastman?!
It's BECAUSE I'm a Beastman that the sight
of pathetic Beastmen makes me sick!
Oh, how the mighty naked ape
has fallen.
What?
You've lost Gurren Lagann, you've lost your
woman, and you've lost your friends.
Now that you've gone back to
being just another naked ape,
...you can't even
protect yourself?
What did you say?!
Even barehanded,
Kamina held his own against me.
Shut up!
Oh, is that anger
I see in your eyes?
If you don't like it,
do something about it!
What the--?
Hey, it's a fight!
It's a fight!
So, you're not entirely helpless
after all.
What's wrong, Viral?
Kill him!
Get him, get him!
He's MY prey!
Back off!
How did you--
My new, immortal body,
given to me by the Spiral King...
...with the order to
forever bear witness.
After all that, what I have
to bear witness to...
...is a pathetic specimen like you
reduced to fighting in a towel in prison?
This is too much.
What do you know about it?
I'm just doing what I need to do!
That's a good one!
So, doing nothing is what
you "need" to do, huh?
Now you're finally the same
as the Spiral King!
Take that back!
Is that the future you won for
yourselves by destroying us?
It's unforgivable!
I never asked for your forgiveness!
Those two bastards treat me
like I'm nothing!
- Quit your yammering!
- Shut up!
The two of you are dead men!
No fighting!
No fighting allowed!
Who's the one
who started this?!
- Those two!
- Those two, sir!
Those two ganged up on
that poor bird man!
How far does goes God
intend to test us?
I can understand how you
don't want to believe it.
If you don't want to believe, don't.
This is a simulation, after all.
In my position now, I have
no choice BUT to believe.
Was it wrong for humanity to dream
of living on the surface?
Are we humans so sinful a species
that we don't deserve even that?
It's the Anti-Spiral
who see it that way.
God's will has nothing
to do with this.
Hey.
Things going smoothly here?
In terms of overall progress,
we're 48% behind.
Wow, that really takes me back!
It's some warble runners!
Boy, you were terrified of
riding those at first.
Hey, it's some slime grape hippos
and pig-moles!
What's the deal? It's the humans
we need to get on board, not those.
Is Rossiu planning to open
a zoo or something?
Now hooking up
the Lordgenome Head.
This used to be the Spiral King.
Are you sure there is no danger?
Even if there is,
we have no choice.
The Arc-Gurren activates
by recognizing his bio-signature.
It's like how Lagann won't work
unless Simon is on board.
Even so, what if this biocomputer turns out
to contain Lordgenome's personality?
You're quite the worrywart,
aren't you?
In that case, all you have to do is
strap on a bomb and sit down next to it.
If you have Kinon's courage,
that is.
If this doesn't work,
it's more all-nighters for us.
I haven't had a good night's sleep
these past seven years, anyway.
Okay, everything's hooked up.
Arc-Gurren Spiral Engine!
Begin final activation checklist!
You got it! Activating!
You moron, not yet!
Super Spiral Engine
startup complete.
Oh, I guess it worked.
For me, nothing is impossible.
You sure talk big for someone
who's just a head.
Anyway, I guess
that's everything!
Congratulations. I will notify Supreme
Commander Rossiu at once.
Legal Affairs Chief Kittan.
W-What are you doing?
You're one of Rossiu's
top ass-kissers.
You're gonna tell me what
he's thinking, Guinble.
I-I have no idea
what you mean.
Don't play dumb with me! How come you're
loading animals aboard the Arc-Gurren?
A whole lot of 'em, too.
Why's that?
I-I don't know.
If you won't talk,
let me take a guess.
Something bad's gonna happen
to the surface, right?
And that's why our softhearted
Rossiu decided to save...
...even the poor, helpless animals,
is that it?!
So, I'm right.
Now, then.
Start explaining.
It's--
It's because we will have to live aboard
the Arc-Gurren for one year.
Rossiu...
You're a key government official.
If that is how you feel,
then shoulder the burden yourself.
Come with me.
W-What the hell is this?
A simulation of what will happen
when the moon hits the Earth.
I'd never calculated anything like this,
so it took a long time to generate it.
But this means... The entire surface
is gonna be wiped out!
Not just the surface.
Underground, too.
The entire surface will be stripped off
by the shock of the moon's impact.
And then the whole world will be
blanketed by white-hot gasses.
Everything on land
will be incinerated.
It won't be capable of supporting life
of any kind for an entire year.
What're you saying, then? You're just
gonna let the people underground die?!
Do you have any other ideas?
The Arc-Gurren can't carry
a million people.
Then... Then why don't we use this
thing to destroy the moon?!
This Dai-Gun is huge!
There's nothing it can't do!
We've considered that, as well.
But it's too risky.
If we fail, humanity will
truly go extinct.
Kittan, are you able to bear
that responsibility?
We will save every life we possibly can.
And not just humans.
What the Arc-Gurren carries within it
will become a second Earth.
We will take aboard every
living beast of the land,
...and live in space for a year
until the Earth cools down.
That is all we can do.
The leader's role isn't to fight. The leader's
role is to make the hard decisions.
Am I wrong?
No... No, you're right!
But that don't mean
I have to like it.
Gurren Lagann
- Hi, brother.
- He's here, he's here!
Nice to finally see you,
Uncle Kittan.
You bet. I gotta see her at least once
while we're still on Earth, right?
You talk like you won't
get another chance.
Is she healthy?
Yep. I'm amazed at how much
she drinks when she nurses.
And when she cries,
you better cover your ears!
Let's have a look... Is it just me,
or does she kinda look worried?
Right here, around
her eyebrows.
Well, maybe...
It's possible. She took after
her father in some odd ways.
Whatever shall we do?
When are you guys
gonna evacuate?
Kiyoh needs to build up
her strength a little more.
I'm worried about
moving her right away.
You dumbass, get aboard
right away!
There's doctors on board
the Arc-Gurren!
Quit wasting time!
Now, now...
That's a good girl...
So, I hear you submitted
your resignation.
Word travels fast.
I know it's a bad time to bail on you,
but I want to be with Kiyoh and Anne.
It's BECAUSE this
is a bad time.
Maybe Kamina picked
the right time to die.
I'm sorry.
But a newborn baby girl is more important
to me right now than a dead man.
It is, huh?
I guess I can't blame you.
Looks like there's a ceiling
in the sky now, too.
Yeah, I guess there is.
Look, uh...
Nah, forget it.
What the hell?!
What happened?
A beam attack from Mugann!
Parliament Tower has been destroyed!
A second wave is coming in!
The attacks are concentrated
underneath Parliament Tower.
I don't believe it, have they detected
the Arc-Gurren's presence?
It's possible.
They might be attacking because they
detected a powerful Spiral Power source.
Is there nothing we can do?
Run a search in the Lordgenome Head!
What's this?
It looks like an energy shield.
It's a Spiral Power shield.
This is a Spiral battleship.
Naturally, it is equipped
with a defensive shield.
It's nice to be able to take them out in one
shot, but there's a ton of these things!
It's safe inside the Arc-Gurren! Please
hurry into the underground tunnels!
Is that everyone?
Everyone who's alive.
Aw, crap...
Get going, Dayakka!
What about you?!
These are Spiral shells.
They oughta be able to slow it down.
Brother!
I'm not about to let my cute little
niece die in some alleyway.
Go on without me, Dayakka!
Kiyoh, look after Kinon for me.
Get moving! It's gonna open fire
any second!
Brother!
- Brother!
Get clear, Kittan.
Makken?
Sorry, it took a long time
to find a sitter for the kids.
That gives me a good idea
of what your family life is like!
I see you brought some
handy toys to the party!
Barrier missiles we made as
a military subcontractor.
We've been helping
ourselves to a few.
Big brother's okay!
What the--?
Hop aboard, Kittan.
I thought these were destroyed!
Some government types brought them
to our place and said to scrap 'em.
So I took 'em... and kept 'em
in peak condition!
That's our Leyte!
I owe you one!
A ceiling, huh?
Yeah, I guess that's
a ceiling, all right.
All right, bring aboard the evacuees
while the shield is up!
Commander, look at that!
Impossible! What are Gunmen
doing out there?!
Attacks from old Gunmen
are effective against them?
Gunmen were originally weapons
designed to fight the Anti-Spiral.
It's only natural that their
weapons would be effective.
Forget about them. Activating the
Arc-Gurren has top priority.
Attention, all units! The Arc-Gurren will
leave the stratosphere in 30 minutes!
Bring aboard as many evacuees
as possible in that time!
Thirty minutes...
In order to exit the stratosphere,
...thirty minutes is the maximum duration
we can divert energy to the shield.
What about the evacuees who
can't get here in time?
We leave in 30 minutes.
My decision is made.
Now I get it.
That's your hard decision, huh?
Save as many lives as you can.
Nothing can shake your resolve.
What are you getting at?
That's a leaderly thing of the
new Government leader to do.
That's impressive for
a boy your age.
But if that's how it's gonna be, how's
about returning the you-know-what?
Me and the guys just don't fit in
with all this government stuff.
We're just Team Gurren.
But the thing is, Team Gurren
has its own way of doing things.
You still don't understand?!
It's a futile effort!
That's what's so great about it.
Now, hand it over.
What you have there is Team Gurren's--
That's HIS soul.
Once upon a time, I entrusted
the future to this, too.
Me, I'm gonna wager tomorrow
on this baby.
Brother...
Survive.
- I'm sorry.
- Leave this to me.
All hands, prepare for liftoff.
We don't have much time!
Move it, move it!
You're in the way!
Let us in!
- Well, it looks like we've been left behind.
- Looks that way.
You did it, Rossiu.
This stinks. To think THIS is how
I'm going to witness your death.
I'm fine with it.
As long as the others will survive,
it's fine with me.
I wouldn't be so sure.
You!
Rossiu has turned his back
on humanity.
When the moon hits, they will be swallowed,
shelters and all, by the Earth's crust,
...and they will
all die.
What the hell is this?
That can't be true!
Even if they do escape into space,
all that awaits them is despair.
What?!
What the Anti-Spiral seek
is absolute despair.
They have taken every step that is
necessary to achieve that aim.
Nia...? Nia, you'd go
that far?
Why, you little...
I don't see you for a while, and you
go and turn into a boring bitch...
...Nia.
To Be Continued...
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Nariyamanai kodou ga itsumo itazura ni kokoro ni tane wo maku
My ever-sounding heartbeat always idly sows a seed in my heart
Sono tane ga kibou no hana wo sakasu ka mo shirenai
That seed might bloom into a flower of hope
Dakara kou shite yume wo egaku koto ga dekirunda
That's how I can sketch my dreams like this
Bunansou na nukemichi ga ukande ha kieteku
A loophole that seems safe comes to mind, but then disappears
Sou yatte boku ha tamesarete dou yatte omoi todokeyou?
By doing that, I'm tested; how can I get my feelings across?
Mayowazu ni mae he susunde
Let's advance forward without hesitating
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Dakara kakko tsukenaide kitto hana ha saku hazu sa
So don't try to look cool; I'm sure our flowers have gotta bloom
Bokura ha kagayaku yo Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
We're gonna shine! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Next Time
What that man loved was a future
beneath the blue sky.
And when that sky begins to fall,
she rises up.
And then their intertwined fates
merge and become one.
You Are Someone Who Ought To Survive
Next time on
Gurren Lagann,
..."You Are Someone
Who Ought To Survive."