Gurren Lagann
Sugita kisetsu wo nageku hima ha nai
I don't have the time to lament the seasons that have passed
Nido to mayotte shimawanu you ni
So that I won't ever waver again
Kazoekirenai hon no sasayaka na
With countless, tiny little
Sonna koukai kakaeta mama
Regrets carried in my arms
Sono senaka dake oikakete koko made kitanda
I've come this far, having chased only after your back
Sagashite ita boku dake ni dekiru koto
It's something only I, who sought you, can do
Ano hi kureta kotoba ga ima demo
Those words you gave me that day, even now,
Kono mune ni tashika ni todoite iru kara
Definitely reach my heart
Kinou yori mo kyou ha bu ha boku no
I've realized my reason for having been born
Umarete kita wake ni kidzuite yuku
Today more than I did yesterday
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who continues
to look for his own path,
...even while he is being
betrayed by fate.
The war between the Spiral races
and the Anti-Spiral.
This was the root cause
of everything.
In order to exterminate humanity,
in which Spiral Power lies dormant,
...they send the moon plummeting
towards the Earth.
It was Simon and his fellow Team Gurren
members who triggered this calamity.
Will their struggle for freedom
lead to mankind's downfall?
Having lost Nia, Simon is shackled
by the handcuffs of despair.
Episode 19:
We Will Survive, By Any Means Necessary
- Give us Simon!
- Make him pay for what he did!
He was never a hero!
Simon is the cause of all this!
It's his fault that
the moon is falling!
Rossiu.
Tell me why.
The citizens who were evacuated to the
Parliament Tower have begun to riot.
Our defeat of Lordgenome is what
set this catastrophe in motion.
Team Dai-Gurren is to blame
for the moon falling from the sky.
That anger is being directed
at the New Government.
Your conversation with Nia was
broadcast live across the world.
Every citizen now knows that the moon will
slam into the Earth in three weeks' time.
Your reckless fight earlier was
also seen by the entire city.
I can no longer protect you.
Protect me?
This is the guy!
It's all his fault!
Tear it down!
In their eyes, you are now
no different from Lordgenome.
In which case, we must punish
you in the same manner.
Exactly as we could not restrain
ourselves from doing back then.
Please wait here until
it is time for your trial.
Trial?
We are now a nation
of laws.
Questions of war responsibility
are also settled in a trial.
First it was God's rules,
and now it's the law.
You're a man who loves to
be tied down, aren't you?
We have always made progress
on the backs of the dead.
Such as my mother.
And Kamina.
What?
When Kamina died,
it made us stronger.
It was thanks to Kamina's death
that we were able to win that battle.
Hold it right there, Rossiu!
Are you trying to tell me that
my Bro's dying was a good thing?
Judging it from the outcome
it produced, then yes, I am.
Don't joke about that! There are
some things you can't say!
Hey! You bastard!
Do you really think that?!
You are exactly like Kamina
was in the old days.
Have you learned nothing from his death?
You haven't grown at all!
I will keep your Core Drill.
It's ironic. The source of your power
was the seed of mankind's destruction.
Rossiu, you'll never understand
what he was feeling.
Or what his death
gave to us.
That look in your eyes... It's exactly the
same as the priest back in Adai Village.
No, it is you who
understands nothing.
You haven't so much as tried to
change in the past seven years.
It is you.
So it's true what they say?
Simon's been arrested?
Yeah.
Why would they do that?!
That's so messed up!
That jerk Rossiu's
gone crazy!
- Kiyal, don't shout in the hospital.
- Oops!
What Rossiu says makes a
certain amount of sense.
What he did to Simon might only
be a temporary solution.
Rossiu might have common sense, but
he's so coldhearted that I can't stand him.
What the heck does Kinon
see in that guy?
Kiyal.
I don't care HOW busy she is, how can
she not even stop by to see Anne?
Kinon's totally changed, too.
Kiyal!
Now, now. It's one thing to talk like that
in here, but don't say that outside.
These days, there's no telling
what might happen.
Send out Simon! The guy who's
responsible has to pay!
Do you have a plan to deal
with the moon falling?!
What's the government doing?!
Give me back my house!
Reimburse me!
I want my peaceful
life back!
The Mugann's energy barrier
can be breached...
...by using the Giga Drill to reflect
its beam back at it.
The problem is, how do we stop
the body itself from exploding?
This enemy
is pretty tricky...
What I don't get is, aren't the Grapearls
superior to Gurren Lagann?
It isn't right for the prototype
to be more powerful.
Goodness, what a cheeky
thing to say.
Whatever shall I do to close
that mouth of yours?
Ever since I was a kid, he's been
the one guy I can't deal with...
What do you think is gonna
happen with Simon?
You mean his arrest?
Arrest?! Is he gonna
be executed?!
Don't get ahead of yourself,
Aretenborough.
I think that Rossiu has
something up his sleeve.
Anyway, our task at hand is developing
weapons against our new enemies.
I guess it's no sleep for us
until we come up with something...
Aretenborough, turn this
report in to Rossiu.
You got it!
What...are...you...doing?!
I said to turn in the report,
not to turn me! Honestly!
Spinning?
Could it be...?
Show us that again!
You got it!
Didn't you hear me?!
I said, NOT me!
We have completed our survey
of surviving underground cities.
Scattered around the world, there are
36 cities over 1000 meters underground...
...whose construction is estimated to be
capable of withstanding the lunar impact.
They are capable of holding
640,000 people.
That's wonderful news.
That's more than we expected.
I suppose we owe a debt of gratitude
to the humans of the past...
...whose civilization
reached such heights.
Even so, those humans were
no match for the Anti-Spiral.
Nevertheless, we will survive.
By any means necessary.
That leaves 360,000.
The citizens here in Kamina City
will be especially difficult.
Advisor Rossiu! I found this file in the
biocomputer's deep-level database.
What in the world...?
Where is it?!
Right underneath Kamina City's
Parliament Tower.
Amazing!
That's the Spiral King for you... He had
this card up his sleeve the whole time.
Gurren Lagann
I will now hand down
the sentence.
The defendant is hereby
sentenced to death.
Hey, hold on a second!
Get real!
What the hell?!
This don't make no sense!
First of all, it was crazy to make
Balinbow his defense attorney!
And Guinble was the prosecutor,
and you were the judge!
You never had any intention
of giving him a fair trial!
I will have quiet in my courtroom,
Legal Affairs Chief Kittan.
If no one is held responsible,
the populace will never be satisfied.
Who do you suggest we hold responsible,
if not Supreme Commander Simon?
But that don't mean you have
to have him put to death!
This may quiet down the unrest for now,
but what about afterwards?
What do you plan to do
about the falling moon?
An evacuation plan for that
very purpose is already underway.
To ensure humanity's survival, we must
quell this foolish disturbance at once,
...and then take calm,
swift action.
Yes, with
Chief Advisor Rossiu,
...no, with New Supreme Commander
Rossiu at its heart.
New Supreme Commander...?
Is this some kind of coup, Rossiu?!
This is nothing of the sort.
According to the law, the instant Simon
was found guilty, I succeeded him.
Bro... If you were in my shoes
right now, what would you do?
Nia?!
Hey, it's Nia!
Are you serious?!
Where'd she come from?
What the Anti-Spiral want
is absolute despair.
There is no hope of survival
for Spiral life.
What are you saying, Nia?
What do you mean, absolute despair?
Why are you doing this?!
For the next two weeks,
meet your end...
...in suffering as you clutch
desperately to life.
Nia! Don't go!
Cybela!
What's happened?
I'm detecting a Mugann above
planned shelter area Littner.
It's a good deal larger than
what we've seen before.
T-This is Littner Sector! A huge clump
of Mugann is heading this way!
We're under attack!
They're pulling out all the stops!
The shelter can't take much of this!
Request immediate assistance!
Help us! Please, help us!
The Mugann have apparently begun
moving towards Kamina city.
Littner...
What's happened to Littner?
Back to the Operations Room!
Rossiu, wait!
Let me... Let me pilot
Gurren Lagann.
What did you say?
Gurren Lagann is our only means
of fighting against them.
Trying to redeem yourself
through an act of heroism, eh?
That has nothing to do with it!
I just want to protect the city!
Nevertheless, you are
a condemned man.
Am I supposed to entrust a prisoner with
Gurren Lagann when he might escape in it?
Rossiu, you son
of a bitch!
Then wire me with a bomb or something!
If I run, all you have to do is detonate it!
Guinble.
Sir.
Disengage the lock on the
Core Drill storeroom.
And don't forget to wire Gurren
with explosives. Have it done at once!
Gurren Lagann, heading out!
Roger that.
I'm standing by and ready to go.
Kinon? What are you
doing aboard Gurren?
I've wired the detonator switch
to my belt.
What?!
Simon, if you try anything funny,
anything at all, I'll hit the switch.
This is crazy!
What do you think you're doing?!
Why does Kinon have
to come with me?!
With her aboard, you have no choice
but to return to base intact.
If it were just you, I expect you would
try to go out in a blaze of heroic glory.
That doesn't mean you need
to risk Kinon's life like this!
I volunteered to do this.
Kinon?!
It's all right. If we make it back in
one piece, there won't be any trouble.
Come home safe and sound so I can
be put to death properly, huh?
- Let's go!
- R-Right!
Commander Rossiu, we are
ready for your broadcast.
Hey, ain't that
Gurren Lagann up there?
But Simon was arrested, wasn't he?
What's going on?
Stand by for an urgent message
from the government.
I repeat, stand by for an urgent message
My fellow citizens.
The surface will be severely damaged by
an attack involving dropping the moon,
...carried out by unknown enemies
calling themselves the Anti-Spiral.
In response, the New Government pressed
charges against Former Commander Simon.
As a result of his trial today,
he was sentenced to death.
There it is!
I can't let that thing get
anywhere near Kamina City!
Whatever it takes,
I'll stop it here!
I have dispatched Former Commander
Simon in Gurren Lagann...
...to intercept the Mugann that have
appeared outside Kamina City,
...but he is completely under
the New Government's control.
We are able to blow it up if he exhibits
any suspicious behavior whatsoever.
Son of a...
Rossiu, you bastard!
To protect its citizens from
the impending lunar impact,
...the government will carry out
a large-scale evacuation plan.
Citizens will be evacuated to 36 giant
underground shelters around the world.
Residents in the Kamina city area,
which has no shelter,
...will temporarily leave the stratosphere
in the Superdreadnought Space Dai-Gun.
And this is that Space Dai-gun!
The Arc-Gurren!
Have faith in the New Government!
We will not be defeated by the Anti-Spiral!
We shall survive, no matter what!
Rossiu!
This will keep us alive!
Simon! The Mugann have turned
around and are heading this way!
That's what I want. Now, let's draw
them away from Kamina City!
These guys are slow.
We'll go slow enough for them to keep up.
Right!
The beams have stopped...
Now they're just showing off...
This is bad... They've got us heading
towards Kamina City again!
Simon! That big Mugann has stayed
at a distance this whole time!
It's possible that it's
their control tower!
I follow you...
Let's put that to the test!
You're mine!
- Nia!
- Goodbye, Simon.
We're surrounded!
If this many fire at us at once, one Giga Drill
will never be able to deflect them all!
Then we'll just use
more than one!
GIGA DRILL MAXIMUM!
Kinon? Are you okay?
Kinon!
Simon?
Yes, I'm all right...
Damn, the big one's still alive...
It's no use, I can't move...
Damn it!
Whew, made it
just in time!
Is that Gimmy?
Sorry to keep you waiting! Now, we'll
show you what the Grapearls can do!
Let's do it!
Tornado Formation!
Firing Spiral Bomber!
Erecting Tornado Shield!
It worked!
Ron, it worked!
For adults, making it in time
is all part of the job.
Kinon. I'm sorry.
What we saw...
That wasn't the Nia I used to know.
Your Core Drill, please.
Gurren Lagann
will be scrapped.
We will no longer rely on you.
I understand.
Simon!
SIMON!
Rossiu!
You bastard, what do you think
you're doing to my sister?!
The bomb you talked about, that was Kinon?!
Is that how you do things?
You're gonna pay...
You'll pay!
Don't get the wrong idea, brother.
The reason I volunteered to go, the reason
I said I would be a human bomb,
...it was because I wanted
to be of use to Rossiu.
Kinon...
Brother, you don't know the
first thing about Rossiu.
Former Supreme Commander Simon,
By Reason of Major War Crimes,
Sentenced to Death
To Be Held In Lincarne Prison
Until Sentence Carried Out
Well, well, look who
we have here.
Welcome to prison,
Supreme Commander Simon.
To Be Continued...
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Nariyamanai kodou ga itsumo itazura ni kokoro ni tane wo maku
My ever-sounding heartbeat always idly sows a seed in my heart
Sono tane ga kibou no hana wo sakasu ka mo shirenai
That seed might bloom into a flower of hope
Dakara kou shite yume wo egaku koto ga dekirunda
That's how I can sketch my dreams like this
Bunansou na nukemichi ga ukande ha kieteku
A loophole that seems safe comes to mind, but then disappears
Sou yatte boku ha tamesarete dou yatte omoi todokeyou?
By doing that, I'm tested; how can I get my feelings across?
Mayowazu ni mae he susunde
Let's advance forward without hesitating
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Dakara kakko tsukenaide kitto hana ha saku hazu sa
So don't try to look cool; I'm sure our flowers have gotta bloom
Bokura ha kagayaku yo Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
We're gonna shine! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Next Time
Even hope will change to despair
in an instant.
What had been the best option
turns into the worst possible choice.
Even so, I make the decision.
And then they will...
How Far Will God Test Us?
Next time on
Gurren Lagann,
..."How Far Will God
Test Us?"