Gurren Lagann
Sugita kisetsu wo nageku hima ha nai
I don't have the time to lament the seasons that have passed
Nido to mayotte shimawanu you ni
So that I won't ever waver again
Kazoekirenai hon no sasayaka na
With countless, tiny little
Sonna koukai kakaeta mama
Regrets carried in my arms
Sono senaka dake oikakete koko made kitanda
I've come this far, having chased only after your back
Sagashite ita boku dake ni dekiru koto
It's something only I, who sought you, can do
Ano hi kureta kotoba ga ima demo
Those words you gave me that day, even now,
Kono mune ni tashika ni todoite iru kara
Definitely reach my heart
Kinou yori mo kyou ha bu ha boku no
I've realized my reason for having been born
Umarete kita wake ni kidzuite yuku
Today more than I did yesterday
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
In a spinning body, its axis of rotation
will always point in the same direction...
...even when force
is applied to it.
The so-called gyroscopic effect. One of
the fundamental laws of the universe.
It's the strangest thing.
Until seven years ago, I was one of the
hereditary guards of the Littner armory.
I was a man who could barely read, and now
I can fine-tune a gigantic battleship like this.
Every once in a while,
I frighten myself.
Is this another form of
the Spiral Power awakening?
What're you doing in there
talking to yourself?!
If we don't do something,
this ship will be destroyed!
We've already done everything
that we CAN do.
Right. The faster we spin, the more we
break free of the bonds of gravity...
...and aim for the heavens.
And there it is!
Now, show us what lies beyond
those heavens we've aimed for!
The Spiral Path, in which the twin paths
of man and beast wind and intersect!
Join with yesterday's enemy
to smash fate!
And grab hold of tomorrow's path
with our own hands!
Destiny Combining!
Gurren Lagann!
Who the hell do you
think I am?!
Episode 22:
This is My Final Duty
Amazing... That shockwave just now
destroyed over half of the small Mugann.
That's a--
There's a massive energy buildup on the
lunar surface behind the jumbo Mugann!
What the--?
Giant beam firing platform
detected on lunar surface!
I wonder if its target
was Gurren Lagann?
Simon! Leave the Arc-Gurren to us,
you deal with the moon!
Got it!
- Let's go, you bozos!
- Yeah!
Wow, look at how many Kittan and the gang
destroyed in their first space attack.
The small Mugann have
pretty much been wiped out.
Simon... Kittan...
Jorgun! Balinbow!
I knew it...
You guys came.
Good news, isn't it?
- Awesome...
- Yeah.
My Dayakkaiser!
Who the hell is piloting it?!
Gimmy!
Pay attention!
Y-Yoko?
Any more daydreaming out of you, and I'll
make you stand out in the hallway!
You sound like
a school teacher...
Remaining Grapearl units,
form up on me!
Don't let the old-timers
show us up!
Spiral energy is recovering!
Is it because of them?
Is this the power of hope?
If that's true, then what have
I been doing all this time?
Divert all energy to Spiral shields!
Protect the ship at all costs!
Roger!
Viral, we'll destroy that cannon
before it gets off another shot.
You're giving me orders now?
It's not an order.
It's a suggestion.
In that case, I accept!
Double Boomerang Spiral!
What the--?
As if!
The moon...
Go to the moon.
It is my...
What was that?
- The moon... Go to the moon.
- Is he accessing new information?
- No, in his case, he's recalling old memories.
- It is my...
The moon...
I'm getting massive power readings
from the two giant Mugann!
Lordgenome!
They're focusing on us this time?
I tell you, it's not easy to be so popular.
Arc-Gurren, we're on our way!
Damn!
Don't cry. Don't cry, now.
Everything will be okay.
Stay calm, everyone. It'll take more
than this to destroy this ship.
My people will keep us safe.
The Arc-Gurren can't take
much more of this...
Rossiu, don't give up!
We've always held out
until the very last second.
It's just like when we stole Dai-Gurren!
And when we took Teppelin!
We hung in there until the last second and
snatched victory from the jaws of defeat!
Yes, it was always
like that for YOU...
Now, now, none of
that whining.
Leeron? What are you doing?
Don't you remember? The Arc-Gurren is
a giant Gunmen, just like Teppelin!
That's right! We snatch victory
from the jaws of defeat!
And that's what we'll keep doing...
As many times as it takes!
I swear, it's never a dull moment
with you around!
Let's do it, Arc-Gurren!
- Simon?
- Is he gonna ram them?
Move it, move it,
make a hole!
That's--
We've combined
with Gurren Lagann?!
We're getting a massive
influx of Spiral energy!
What's this signal we're receiving?
It's a transformation signal!
Adjusting shipboard gravity
to match transformation!
Assuring integrity of
living quarters!
Okay, Simon!
Hit it!
Giga Drill, spin on!
Smashing through both
karma and fate!
The screams of life
echo through the galaxy!
Raging Wave Combining!
Arch-Gurren Lagann!
But that's--
I don't believe it!
What the hell is that?!
They transformed
something that big?
Good job spotting this.
We can always count on you, Leeron.
I don't want just your words of praise!
I want your burning heart, too!
Can I kill him?
Let it go.
For now, we need to start
with this thing.
Oh, so they can combine, too?
C'mon!
Arch-Gurren Lagann, full power!
Let's do it, Viral!
Suits me fine!
Have a taste of the
Space-time Shattering...
...Burst Spinning...
...Punch!
Is that Simon's power?
Right. It's always Simon who unleashes
unbelievable power at the last moment.
Sure looks that way...
What's that hole?
Looks like a hole in the
fabric of space and time.
He sent it flying to the far end
of the space-time continuum.
Amazing...
This is the awakening of
Spiral Power, isn't it?
Now, then...
All we need to do now is push
this thing back into place!
Gurren Lagann
It's getting hot in here...
It'll be entering the atmosphere soon.
It's dangerous, so return to the ship.
But we haven't--
Let Arch-Gurren Lagann
take it from here.
Look at that!
The moon was another
gigantic machine?
Either way, we're gonna
stop it in its tracks!
Yes, that is my flagship.
The biocomputer has reactivated!
You recognize it, Lordgenome?
Lordgenome?!
Don't worry, it's a biocomputer
that we generated from his cells.
It's not like we completely
brought him back to life.
Reprehensible...
It was necessary.
Is that you, Viral?
Don't be angry. I must say, this is
a rather fascinating experience.
I see you've changed, Spiral King.
Yes, perhaps I have.
Perhaps it's because I've been set free
from the yoke of my flesh.
Atmospheric entry
in five minutes!
Maybe it really is hopeless.
It's just too big!
I'm not about to give up,
not after coming this far!
What's all this?
Insert your source of Spiral Power here.
The moon will come under your control.
Under my control?
The moon is my flagship,
the Cathedral Terra.
It's another Gunmen?
Judging from the size of the hole,
it looks like it takes a Giga Core Drill.
You want me to fly in
with Gurren Lagann, huh?
Gimmy, Darry!
Take over the controls!
- Right!
Let's give it all we've got, Gimmy. We have
to buy Simon as much time as possible.
Hang in there, Grapearl! Mass-production
models have their pride, too!
Three minutes to
atmospheric entry!
Did you hear that, Gimmy and Darry?
Do what you can to give us an extra minute.
And then, a minute before entry,
Arch-Gurren Lagann will disengage.
I will protect the 180,000 lives
aboard this ship.
No matter how much scorn you heap
on me, that is my final duty.
- Roger.
That's the heart of
the machine, huh?
We're nearly out of time!
Go!
Nia?
Get out of the way, Nia!
I'm afraid that I can't do that.
I am the messenger of the Anti-Spiral.
Causing the extinction of you
Spiral lifeforms is my mission.
Spare me the speeches.
Stand aside.
Then insert that drill,
crushing me in the process.
If that's the way
you want it!
Wait, Viral!
Lordgenome says not to!
He what?!
Her body is composed of the same
energy blocks as the Mugann.
If you crush her, it will
cause an explosion,
...and the control system
will be destroyed.
What...?
But we're so close...
That is absolute despair.
What?
The survival instinct is incredibly
strong in you Spiral races.
That is why we extinguish one by one
every ray of hope left to you.
When there appears to be hope, but then
you learn it is beyond your reach,
...that is when your despair
is the deepest.
The appearance of the Mugann.
The falling of the moon.
The predicted destruction of
the underground shelters.
The ambush in space.
Is she saying these were
all calculated moves?
How far does this all go?
Yes. Terror and despair are the
most powerful deterrent...
...for the magnifying nature
of Spiral Power.
Are you sure about that?
Nia, the way I see it, I think you've
been trying to toughen up humanity.
No matter how dire the situation,
we've always risen to meet it.
The more dire the situation you've put
us in, the stronger we've become.
That's what's brought me
to this place.
And that's what you hoped, too.
Tell me I'm wrong.
You and I exist in
different dimensions.
My past was entirely
a fictional creation.
Your words mean nothing
to me.
- You're wrong.
- It is a fact.
If that's true... If that's true,
why are you wearing that ring?
What is--
It's your desire. Your desire
to not let go of the past.
Oh, that's it.
I finally get it now.
I get why you appeared to me
at crucial times.
To inflict absolute despair
upon you.
I thought I just
told you that.
You're wrong.
Maybe you don't realize it yourself,
but when you appeared to me,
...you wanted me
to help you.
Simon!
I'm right here!
Please! Help me!
You're wrong.
I was--
When we defeated Lordgenome, you said
you would head towards tomorrow.
You and I built that future with the
people who came to the surface.
Would you destroy
that yourself?
I'm gonna grab hold of your future
with my own two hands!
So get out of the way!
Please!
Look, Simon!
The moon is transforming!
It's a--
It's a battleship type!
Yes, that is my Cathedral Terra...
I guess that means he managed
to take control of it.
The moon battleship has
fired its retro rockets!
It's slowly climbing back
into its old orbit.
I guess he really did pull
a victory out of our hats.
That's our Simon!
That's for sure.
He's quite a man, isn't he?
Thank you, Nia.
But this will not change your fate.
What?
With the defusing of the
Humanity Annihilation System,
...the Anti-Spiral will enter
a total war footing.
If they set their minds to it, not
even you will be a match for them.
The main Anti-Spiral fleet will
arrive in this galaxy...
...to exterminate the human race
and their awakened Spiral Power.
The fight isn't over yet, huh?
If we win, will you go back
to your old self?
I will be recalled to the
Anti-Spiral homeworld...
...so that my data on you
can be analyzed.
The likelihood of that is
infinitely close to zero.
Maybe, but it isn't zero.
As far as I'm concerned, that makes it
the same as a 100% chance.
You will come to get me?
Yeah. Who the hell
do you think I am?
I am being recalled... to
the Anti-Spiral homeworld.
NIA!
I can't hold a candle to him. In the end,
he overturned every plan set against him.
The lunar impact
has been averted.
The ship will return to the
Earth's surface momentarily.
We can go home.
Wait for me, Nia.
To Be Continued...
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Nariyamanai kodou ga itsumo itazura ni kokoro ni tane wo maku
My ever-sounding heartbeat always idly sows a seed in my heart
Sono tane ga kibou no hana wo sakasu ka mo shirenai
That seed might bloom into a flower of hope
Dakara kou shite yume wo egaku koto ga dekirunda
That's how I can sketch my dreams like this
Bunansou na nukemichi ga ukande ha kieteku
A loophole that seems safe comes to mind, but then disappears
Sou yatte boku ha tamesarete dou yatte omoi todokeyou?
By doing that, I'm tested; how can I get my feelings across?
Mayowazu ni mae he susunde
Let's advance forward without hesitating
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Dakara kakko tsukenaide kitto hana ha saku hazu sa
So don't try to look cool; I'm sure our flowers have gotta bloom
Bokura ha kagayaku yo Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
We're gonna shine! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Next Time
Even warped and twisted roads
will snap into place...
...if you kick reason to the curb
and give 'em a whack!
Spirit and love change the universe! That's
how manly stubbornness shows itself!
Let's Go, This is the Final Battle
Next time on
Gurren Lagann,
..."Let's Go, This is
the Final Battle."