Huge buildings are falling this way!
What in the world is happening?!
This is the tale of a man who continues
to fight against fate.
Damn!
Gabal, fall back!
Aye, aye!
What the hell is going on?
What IS all this?!
Brother!
Quit your squealing, just run!
Simon! We should evacuate
to a safe location, too!
Y-Yeah.
I don't believe it...
It can't be...
At that very moment, fate took shape
and revealed itself to the man.
A Gunmen?!
Gurren Lagann
Episode 15:
I Will Head Towards Tomorrow
Look at the size of that thing!
This has to be against
some rule or other...
I'm getting something from Teppelin's
old location! The pattern is...
It can't be!
What's wrong?
This signature is...
It's Gurren Lagann!
What?!
I'm picking up another reading that's
completely identical to Gurren Lagann's!
What's that?
That's...
Father!
Nia?
That means--
That's the Spiral King, Lordgenome...
That's him!
I just need to defeat him!
That's the whole thing?
Is that all you have, human?
Simon!
Nice catch!
Ow...
- Simon, are you okay?
- Yeah, somehow...
I can't believe that the drill tip
couldn't penetrate that.
Simon, do this for me.
Take me to my father!
Nia?
I want to speak to my father.
That's crazy! Lordgenome isn't going
to let us get anywhere near him!
We should focus on working out
a long-range attack plan,
...not getting close enough
to have a chat!
Rossiu, have you forgotten?
This girl has come all this way to give
her father a piece of her mind.
But that's--
When a girl sets her mind to something,
a good man is obliged to let her do it.
Please, I beg you!
Sure! Let's go, Nia!
Are you serious, Simon?
You better believe it!
I'm coming, too, Simon!
If I don't give that guy a swift kick in the ass,
I won't be able to live with myself!
- Yeah!
- What he said!
I hate to break it to you,
but that doesn't seem likely.
Say what?!
Rossiu was right. They aren't going
to let us just walk up to him.
How many of those damn things
are there?
I like the looks of this, Kiyoh!
Yeah. With this many enemies,
we can finally show the world...
...what the Black Siblings
are capable of.
You guys...
Ain't that right, Brother?
Yeah, it sure is.
But she's wrong about one thing.
It ain't the power of the Black Siblings
that we're gonna show 'em.
It's the power of Team Dai-Gurren!
Yeah!
Get going, Simon! We'll open up
a path for Dai-Gurren!
Kittan...
Give that guy
a few whacks for us, too!
I will.
Thanks, Simon.
- Here we go!
- Ready!
Dai-Gurren, lift off!
Lifting off!
Here they come!
Outta the way!
You won't beat us!
- There's a thin patch on the right!
- Good! Don't miss this chance!
We can do it if Gurren Lagann
pools its strength with Dai-Gurren!
Oh? The end result
will be the same.
- Let's do it!
- Open fire!
- Fire the Knife Anchor!
We did it!
We got you to where you
were going, Simon.
Explosion in the engine room!
Fires breaking out in main shaft
and generator room!
Ron! That last burst
was all we had.
It's okay,
that's all we needed.
Let's put the old girl
to bed.
What's wrong?
What was that explosion?
Don't worry about us, Simon.
You go to Lordgenome.
Yeah, but--
Hurry up and get going!
Yoko...
Go, Simon. That's what we've all
been working so hard for.
I understand.
Okay, Dai-Gurren.
Time for your last job.
Set the timers on the explosives
in the powder magazine!
Set!
Detonate!
Emergency ejection!
It's all up to you now, Simon.
Well, I see that you've somehow
managed to arrive, man of the Spiral.
Lordgenome!
Nicely dodged!
I expected nothing less, Simon!
Viral!
Gurren Lagann
I'm a whole new man today.
What?
I have a new body that can go on fighting
indefinitely without needing sleep!
I've overcome the limits
of the Beastmen!
This place will be
your grave, Simon!
What?!
T-This isn't possible!
How can this be?!
Why?! Why can't I beat him?!
Viral, you poor creature.
Majesty?
The power I gave you isn't meant
to overcome humans.
M-Majesty...
To begin with, no Beastman
will ever be a match against...
...a human who has acquired
the power of the Spiral.
Viral, it's true that I gave you
a body that cannot die.
But it was not so that
you could fight.
It is so you could be a storyteller
who will recount for all time...
...the victory of the
Spiral King.
Your storyteller?
Stay where you are
and observe.
Observe the fate of
a foolish human.
And until the end of time,
tell your listeners...
...of the futility of raising the flag
of rebellion against the Spiral King.
Ah, Nia.
It has been a long time, Father.
You're looking well. I didn't
expect to see your face again.
Why are you doing this, Father?
You drive humans underground, and kill
them if they come to the surface.
It is horrible!
Why would you do such
a cruel thing?
Oh, ignorance is
a frightening thing.
You might believe yourselves to be fighting
on the side of righteousness,
...but I am the one who is
protecting this world.
It is I, Lordgenome,
who is the guardian of humanity.
What are you saying?
There can be no such thing as
a guardian who kills his charges.
Don't you see that there is something
wrong with this world?
Nia, this world that I have created is the
only path to ensure humanity's survival.
You and your friends have strayed from
that path, and I cannot allow that to continue.
For the sake of humanity, you must die.
The Spiral Power is strong within you.
Yet you are unaware that such power
leads only to destruction.
Allow me to teach you.
Teach you how foolish that is.
You are not the only one who
possesses the power of the Spiral.
I will show you
what true Spiral Power is.
Using my Lazengann.
Father?
That's...
Spiral King's Personal Gunmen:
Lazengann
That's a Gurren Lagann-type!
This is the source of the identical
Gurren Lagann reading?
Nia, I have no choice
but to fight him.
Right.
There was once a man
who fought as you do.
He also was unaware that his actions
would doom humanity to extinction.
What do you mean?
You don't need to know.
After all, you will be dead soon.
GIGA DRILL BREAK!
Impossible!
It's hopeless...
We can't possibly beat him...
Don't give up!
Rejecting common sense to make the
impossible possible is the Team Gurren way.
Rossiu, have faith in me.
Believe in the Simon
who believes in you.
We still have some
fight left in us!
You have strength enough
to get back to your feet, I see.
Even so,
it's a wasted effort.
We'll see about that!
- Rossiu!
- I'm all right!
I'm not helpless...
Now's your chance, Simon!
Use Lagann!
Got it.
You're in my way.
LAGANN IMPACT!
You hope to incorporate
my Lazengann, too, do you?
He self-destructed?
Well, well. I see that it was not a fluke
that you made it this far.
However, your mischief ends here.
Now that you have lost your body,
you don't have the slightest hope of winning.
Quit your yammering!
I'm not gonna lose.
Nia. Yoko.
Rossiu.
Ron. Kittan.
Dayakka.
Every member of Team Dai-Gurren
believes in me.
The me that my Bro believed in,
the me that I believe in...
...isn't possibly gonna lose
to the likes of you!
You don't say. In that case,
I will pull out all the stops to crush you!
I should have known I couldn't
trust a Gunmen to do the job!
Simon!
I can't produce
any more drills...!
What's the matter?
Has your Spiral run dry?
Simon!
Simon, if our faith in you is
what gives you your strength,
...then I'll believe in you
with all my heart!
So, please! Win!
I haven't had this much fun
in a long time, boy.
Now, back into the dirt
with you!
A Core Drill?!
My name is Simon.
Simon the Digger,
leader of Team Dai-Gurren.
If you decide to be a wall
that's standing in my way,
...there's something that will
open a hole in you every time!
And that something
is my drill!
I see... Your Spiral Power
outstripped my own.
You will come to regret it
once you learn its importance.
Lordgenome...
I will leave you with
this warning.
When the land comes to overflow
with a million apes,
...the moon shall become Hell's messenger
and destroy the world of the Spiral.
What do you mean?!
Father!
Farewell, Father.
I will head towards tomorrow.
Simon!
What happened?
All enemy Gunmen have
stopped moving!
You mean it's over?
Wow! You did it, Simon!
Simon...
It's Gurren Lagann!
They're all right!
They're coming home!
Battle of Teppelin
The 7th Day
Teppelin, the Royal Capital:  Fallen
To Be Continued Some More!
Hikari wo motomete kage ha tawainai jooku wo shaberu
'Cuz they seek light, the shadows chatter out grade-school jokes
Kikitai no ha sonna koto ja nai
I don't want to listen to that crap
Taiyou motomete kage ha tamashii no nuketa koe kara
'Cuz they seek the sun, the shadows suddenly change from
Kyuu ni surudoi kuchou ni kawaru
The soul's missing voice to a sharp tone of voice
Sono oto ga machi no naka ni kodama-shite hibikinagara
While that sound echoed and bounced in the middle of town,
Kemono no you na koe de sakebitsudzuketa
I kept on screaming in a beastly voice
Kidou wo kaeta tsumori ha nai
No way I'm going to change my course
Zankyou ha giratsuiteru ga
The reverb's dazzling, but
Kussetsu-shite hanarete iku
It refracts and comes apart
Koko no sekai ha itsumo kou da
The world right here is always like this
Soto no sekai ni ha hikari ha aru no ka
Is there light in the world outside?
Next Time
Next time on Gurren Lagann!
We'll relate memories
of past battles!
Watch and learn! This is how compilation
episodes should be done!
Compilation Episode