Gurren Lagann
Sugita kisetsu wo nageku hima ha nai
I don't have the time to lament the seasons that have passed
Nido to mayotte shimawanu you ni
So that I won't ever waver again
Kazoekirenai hon no sasayaka na
With countless, tiny little
Sonna koukai kakaeta mama
Regrets carried in my arms
Sono senaka dake oikakete koko made kitanda
I've come this far, having chased only after your back
Sagashite ita boku dake ni dekiru koto
It's something only I, who sought you, can do
Ano hi kureta kotoba ga ima demo
Those words you gave me that day, even now,
Kono mune ni tashika ni todoite iru kara
Definitely reach my heart
Kinou yori mo kyou ha bu ha boku no
I've realized my reason for having been born
Umarete kita wake ni kidzuite yuku
Today more than I did yesterday
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
This is the tale of a man who blows
a hole in the fate of a universe...
...that is ruled by the endless
cycle of violence.
The Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren sets sail to
put an end to the conflict once and for all.
The men of Team Gurren are destroyed
one by one by the fierce attack...
...of the enemy fleet, which was
lying in wait for them.
Even the Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren,
hoping to turn the tables by transforming,
...is swallowed up by a black sea
that unfolds in space,
...and is about
to meet its end.
Episode 25:
I Accept Your Last Wish
The Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren
is sinking!
Sinking?! We're in space!
What's an ocean doing in space?!
The fabric of space-time is being
compressed until it's ultra-dense.
That's why it
looks like water.
Nothing makes sense anymore!
Get us to the surface, Gabal!
I can't! Engine output
isn't increasing!
- Careful!
- Thank you.
You must be getting soft, losing your
balance over a little rocking like this.
Not to worry. It's all about filling
in the blanks with life experiences.
- E-Experiences?!
- What's gotten into you?
Nothing!
I don't like the sound of that.
What the hell is going on out there?
Enemy fleet is gathering
on the surface!
Firing main guns!
Wait! The energy
will be--
What happened?
Main guns' beams
have died out!
The Spiral energy
was absorbed?
But that's impossible!
How could my beloved main
guns not work...?
They NEVER work
when you use them!
It would appear that this
is a Death Spiral Field.
Death Spiral?
Spiral Energy is absorbed
and converted into mass.
The more Spiral Power we use,
the denser this region becomes.
Ah, so that's why
it looks like a sea.
If we were to sink
into its depths,
...not even the Super Galaxy
Dai-Gurren would survive.
Meaning we'll be crushed flat
by the water pressure.
No, the SPACE pressure...
This can't be happening...
Just leave it to me, Dayakka!
The key is to rev up the engines faster
than the energy can be drained.
Our power is limitless!
Just as long as our hearts
don't give in!
You're a man who spouts a bunch of crap.
But this is crap that I can get behind!
Leave the fine-tuning to me!
Damn it!
Output is increasing!
Raise the bow!
Take us up!
That did the trick!
Enemy units have entered the water
and are headed this way!
Intercept them!
Aretenborough!
Switch to physical ammo!
You got it!
Chew on this!
The missiles are working!
But there's too many!
They're trying to force us
down to the bottom!
Isn't there anything we can do
to shake them off?
Aren't you scared?
Aren't you afraid of dying?
You'd be fighting a ton of enemies
in an ultra-dense region of space.
How much fighting could you do
in your smashed-up Space King Kittan?
How can you go out and fight,
knowing what might happen?
Gimmy, what're you--
It's no fair.
I want to be like you and choose
to go out in a blaze of glory...
But I just can't get
my body to move.
Gimmy...
What are you,
some kinda moron?
Show me the person
who ain't afraid of dying!
But I got no choice!
This is all I'm good at!
We do this because
we WANT to!
You gotta move forward, and that
goes double when you're scared!
Basically, it's, you know...
Aw, man, I can't
explain it right!
I'll just say this.
The reason Jorgun and Balinbow saved
you two is because they wanted to.
So there's no reason for you
to feel like you owe them.
Got it?
I can't get the right words out...
Damn it.
You think?
If that guy was here, he would've done
a better job inspiring them.
When he rallied the troops, his words
went straight to your heart.
I really envy him
for that...
"That guy"...
I feel it even more as I get older.
Kamina was one hell of a man.
You're overlooking something, Kittan.
Team Dai-Gurren never would have
come this far if it weren't for you.
Simon pulled us from above, and you
pushed and shoved us from below.
That's how we managed to come
all this way. That's the way I see it.
That's just as much a man's job
that you can be proud of, right?
We're wasting time.
Let's do it!
Is that Kittan?
His Space King Kittan
works in this soup?
Its Spiral Engine isn't its
only power source.
They ran on electricity when we
were on the surface, remember?
Oh, I get it! The Space Gunmen
have backup power sources, too!
Look out!
Don't mess with me!
Are you okay?
I lost an arm, that's all.
It's no big deal.
That was a rookie mistake.
Sorry.
Don't sweat it. You fill in the blanks
with life experience, right?
Man, these guys are coming
in swarms now...
Hey, Yoko.
When we get back to Earth, how about
introducing me to those kids of yours?
I got a gruff exterior,
but I love kids.
Once we waste these guys, take out
the Anti-Spiral, and go home to Earth,
...that's when I'll--
Damn it, let me finish!
Are you two okay?
Show a little common sense,
why don't ya?
Hey, we reject common sense to
make the impossible possible!
That's the way
Team Dai-Gurren rolls, right?
Yeah, but--
We're doing this
because we want to.
Please, let us
fight with you.
Unbelievable... Kids and women,
I just can't say no to 'em.
Okay, you three! We're gonna rip
those monsters off the ship!
Roger!
Gurren Lagann
Okay, that's about all of 'em.
Yoko! Look at that!
Zooming in.
Why, those are Laganns!
What the hell's going on, Leeron?
Those are Spiral warriors who once
faced the Anti-Spiral in battle.
So this means that others besides us
made it this far?
Indeed it does,
foolish people of the Spiral.
Do not believe yourselves
to be special.
In the battle between Spiral races and
Anti-Spiral that has crossed the eons,
...you are nothing more than
paltry, insignificant beings.
Now, behold the history
of the Spiral races' defeat.
You are in the Galactic Spiral Abyss.
The Spiral graveyard.
High-order energy reading detected
from the deepest area.
We're being slowly pulled in!
The Death Spiral Machine.
That is what is generating this field.
Galactic Spiral Abyss
It's killed that many Laganns?
This space ocean is where
the tears of the Spiral races end up...
This is no time to get poetic!
We gotta do something!
If this keeps up, the whole damn ship
is gonna be crushed!
Don't give up, everybody!
We won't let the Anti-Spiral
have things their way!
Our dead friends...
The Spiral races
that fell in battle...
We'll take in
all their regrets.
We'll take them in, and turn it
all into strength!
We're not gonna let it end,
NOT HERE!
Gabal, turn us around!
Point the bow towards the core!
What do you have in mind?
What else? We'll fly down the Death
Spiral Machine's throat and destroy it!
That's how Team Dai-Gurren rolls!
He has a point. We've always
rolled the dice on Simon's drill.
Up until now.
And from now on, too.
Am I right?
Gabal, bring us about
180 degrees, full speed!
I'm on it!
The Death Spiral Machine is surrounded
by a region of super-ultra-dense space.
Even the Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren will
be lucky to survive 300 seconds within it.
A Spiral conversion field
is in place around the machine.
This field protects the machine by
converting mass into Spiral Power.
It negates the pressure and generates
energy at the same time.
Two birds with one stone...
Still, that has a fatal flaw.
A massive dose of Spiral Power
will disrupt that process,
...and cause a localized
collapse of the field.
We then lob in as many Spiral missiles
as we can into the gap.
And that's the end
of the machine.
Wow, it ain't as tough
as I expected!
I guess it means that the Anti-Spiral
didn't anticipate that there would be...
...people crazy enough to plunge
into this ultra-dense space.
How are the Super Spiral
missiles coming?
Simon is really running himself
into the ground in there.
We'll be lucky to have two ready
by the time we get there.
Two shots will be enough
to get the job done!
What was that?
There's flooding in block 5826!
Flooding?
We're taking on ultra-dense space!
We're not flooding,
we're spacing!
And block 280! And block 447!
Block 2391, too!
Close bulkheads!
Don't let any more space
aboard the ship!
The probability of this
operation's success is--
You don't need to tell us.
We know it's crazy.
We'll have five minutes to carry out
the operation once we enter firing range.
If we take longer than that,
we'll be crushed as flat as a pancake.
Tetukan, let Cybela handle things here.
Go give Leyte a hand.
Understood.
Simon!
I can handle it.
Don't worry.
Get it replaced ASAP!
We don't have much time!
They're replacing the drill.
Get some rest.
Okay, but just for a minute.
I'm sorry, Simon.
If I had Spiral Power, I'd...
Crap!
What do you want,
you little pig-mole?
You want me
to let you inside?
All right, all right.
What the--?
I can't believe it, you're--
What happened?
This little pig-mole is a
bundle of Spiral Power!
Gurren and Lagann can now
operate in tandem!
Boota! Keep it up!
You're a Team Dai-Gurren
member, too!
Boota has Spiral Power, too?
Humans aren't the only
Spiral lifeforms.
Perhaps it underwent a mutation.
Or is reacting to Simon's Spiral Power.
In any event, it has stored up a massive
amount of Spiral Power within itself.
Spacing aboard the ship
has grown more severe!
Gate 589! Gate 3264!
Gate 779 destroyed!
Gabal, hurry it up!
What the hell are all these?
Drills that we took off of
Gurren Lagann.
They broke?
Yeah. I've never seen
one break before.
This is really taking
a toll on Simon, too.
It is, huh?
Approaching Death Spiral Machine.
Will enter firing range momentarily.
That's what I've
been waiting for!
What's the status on the
Super Spiral missiles?
Ready to go.
Enemy mechanism is now
within firing range!
FIRE!
It didn't reach?
But we ran strength calculations
for the missile casing!
The density was even higher
than we calculated?
Spacing is advancing.
Time remaining, 4 minutes,
10 seconds.
Leyte! Beef up the Super Spiral
missile casings! In one minute!
Already on it!
Leyte.
Hold on there, Yoko.
This is MY job.
Leyte, load the missile onto
my Space King Kittan.
What?!
In Dan-Gunmen mode,
its armor is really thick.
We're short on time.
It'll be faster and more reliable than
changing out the missile casings.
That's what you had
in mind, right?
Sorry. That's just me thinking
of myself, same as always.
Thanks.
You're doing this because
you want to, right?
I can't stop you.
I ain't gonna say some showy
crap like, "Later, buddy"!
I'll be seeing ya soon,
you bozos!
We're counting on you...
That's it, huh?
Now, fire missile!
Crap! Why'd they
have to bust NOW?
Explosion confirmed inside
Spiral conversion field!
Did he do it?
No, the Death Spiral Machine
is still intact.
Kittan...
You died for nothing,
you dumb bastard...
Not so fast! What's that
energy reading?
From the size, it's... the Gunmen
that was inside the Space Gunmen!
My King Kittan
is still doin' fine!
I borrowed one of Gurren Lagann's
drills as a good luck charm!
And I'm gonna put it
to good use!
Kittan!
This is Simon's soul!
Team Dai-Gurren's soul!
Humanity's soul!
No, it's MY soul!
You think it's gonna be wiped out
by the likes of you?!
Chew on this!
KING KITTAN
GIGA DRILL BREAK!
So this is the power
of the Spiral, huh?
Okay, I'm impressed...
This operation had a zero percent
chance of succeeding.
But it seems that theoretical calculations
are pointless where you are concerned.
What's happening?
It's an immense... An unbelievably
immense Spiral energy reading...
With the destruction of the
Death Spiral Machine,
...this dark sea is being converted
back into Spiral energy.
It is the logical outcome.
You should have mentioned that
before we got started!
Our Super Spiral gauges
are climbing!
Ten thousand! A hundred thousand!
One million!
Simon, we're ready to go!
Kittan... I accept your last wish.
Viral. Boota.
Let's do this.
Transform!
That's what I've been
waiting to hear!
Our friend's hopes and dreams
are etched into its body...
Ultra Spiral  Superdreadnought Gunmen
Transforming the infinite darkness into light!
Unmatched in heaven and Earth...
One machine, equal to the gods!
Super Galaxy Gurren Lagann
Super Galaxy Gurren Lagann!
We're gonna show you
the power of the human race!
To Be Continued...
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Nariyamanai kodou ga itsumo itazura ni kokoro ni tane wo maku
My ever-sounding heartbeat always idly sows a seed in my heart
Sono tane ga kibou no hana wo sakasu ka mo shirenai
That seed might bloom into a flower of hope
Dakara kou shite yume wo egaku koto ga dekirunda
That's how I can sketch my dreams like this
Bunansou na nukemichi ga ukande ha kieteku
A loophole that seems safe comes to mind, but then disappears
Sou yatte boku ha tamesarete dou yatte omoi todokeyou?
By doing that, I'm tested; how can I get my feelings across?
Mayowazu ni mae he susunde
Let's advance forward without hesitating
Dakara kakko tsukenaide motto jibun wo shinjite
So don't try to look cool; believe in yourself more
Sono yume wo oikake Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
Chase after that dream! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Dakara kakko tsukenaide kitto hana ha saku hazu sa
So don't try to look cool; I'm sure our flowers have gotta bloom
Bokura ha kagayaku yo Love & Rock Love & Rock, Peace!!
We're gonna shine! Love & Rock, Love & Rock, Peace!!
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Minna no piisu It's all right!
Everybody's peace, it's all right!
Love & Rock notte OK!
It's OK to harmonize with Love & Rock!
Minna de utau Song For You
With everybody, I'll sing a song for you!
Love & Peace Rock, My Song
Love & Peace Rock, my song
Next Time
A supergalactic god-machine
given to us by our friends' dreams...
Even when trapped in a multi-dimensional
hell, all roads lead to manliness!
Let's Go, Buddy
Next time on
Gurren Lagann,
..."Let's Go, Buddy."