Gurren Lagann
Kimi ha kikoeru?
Can you hear it?
Boku no kono koe ga yami ni munashiku suikomareta
This voice of mine was sucked emptily into darkness
Moshimo sekai ga imi wo motsu no nara
If the world has meaning to it,
Konna kimochi mo muda de ha nai
Then these kinds of feelings aren't futile
Akogare ni oshitsubusarete akirametetanda
I was crushed by my longing and had given up
Hateshinai sora no iro mo shiranaide
Without even knowing the color of the endless sky
Hashiridashita omoi ga ima demo
I began to run, because my feelings, even now,
Kono mune wo tashika ni tataiteru kara
Are definitely beating against my heart
Kyou no boku ga sono saki ni tsudzuku
The me of today will continue towards our destination
Bokura nari no asu wo kizuite yuku
We'll amass our own tomorrows
Kotae ha sou itsumo koko ni aru
The answer, yes, is always right here
Episode 16:
Compilation Episode
Underground village
Don't call me Kamina,
call me "Bro"!
Day after day...
Yours is the drill that will break
through the vault of heaven!
...he digs through the dirt.
I don't run from anything
His parents are dead.
Oh, right. I forgot what
happened to you.
Up on the surface,
there ain't no ceiling!
Somewhere that isn't here...
When they speak of that
paragon of masculinity,
...they're talking about ME,
the mighty Kamina!
...there's a wide open world.
Dumbass! Reject common sense to
make the impossible possible!
That's the way
Team Gurren rolls, right?
He's tough, kind, and big.
Farewell, Giha Village!
We're off to the surface!
Off to the surface
I saw as a kid!
I want to be like my Bro.
I'm Kamina,
and this is Simon.
Listen up, you walking faces!
Having left his homeland, he never yields,
never retreats, and never regrets!
He was still a child.
When you're ready,
come up and join me.
Until then!
Goodbye for now, Kamina!
His father's back.
You got here just in time,
blood brother!
He takes over...
That body gives me chills
every time I look at it!
Oh, yeah! It's all about
the fighting spirit!
...an enemy Gunmen!
Let's see some more spirit!
Don't screw with me,
you Gunmen bastards!
Who the hell do you
think I am?!
All right, you two!
Get back!
You came from
the surface, right?
Pretty much.
That's awesome. So, that's a weapon
they use on the surface, huh?
A dangerous woman.
Damn, you got a fine body!
Surface chicks are a breed apart!
A new companion.
It's Yoko.
That's my name.
I never introduced myself, did I?
Hold us steady, Simon!
Hold us steady, I said!
Sheesh!
A powerful rival...
Human Eradication Forces,
Far East Theater Commander Viral.
...appears!
You're not getting away!
I never turn my back
on an enemy!
That bravado will
get you killed.
What was--
Damn, you dodged it...
Impressive, you managed
to injure me.
But a sneak attack is just a sneak attack.
It's only a surprise once.
It's over!
A showdown at high noon.
Don't put yourself out
on our account.
If he isn't beaten here,
we'll lose our home.
You're members of Team Gurren!
I'm not gonna let this guy take you out!
You never learn
any new tricks...
...do you?!
On your feet.
Who do you think you are,
having two faces!
Time for the last resort! It's time
to break out the you-know-what!
The what?
Sorry, I don't know what.
Dumbass! What else would
I be talking about?!
We're gonna combine!
Manly combining is about fighting spirit!
The beauty of soaring through the air!
Brotherly Combining!
Gurren Lagann!
You're being awfully understanding!
Warriors of the Capital
prize decorum above all else!
The Capital?
It is the sole example of civilization on
the surface, ruled by the Spiral King!
Spiral King?
Civilization, huh?
Royal Capital
I am one of the Spiral King's
Four Generals...
...Thymilph, the Raging Wave.
Spiral King
Yoko, watch my back.
I'll crush anything that comes
at me from up ahead.
So I need you to deal with
anything from behind.
Kamina.
Your back is one big
blind spot, isn't it?
What are you--
I'll pay that back
ten times over.
When we get back,
I'll repay that ten times over.
Mark my words.
What's with you?
Don't you think you could phrase that
a little more romantically?
Now, let's head out there
and raise a little hell!
Take over Dai-Gunzan!
We have the edge in spirit, too!
Get in there, Simon!
You're Gonna Do It!
Lagann Impact!
- That was close!
- General Thymilph, you're in danger here!
What are you trying to do?!
We merged 'em! We merged our
Lagann with your Dai-Gunzan!
You've what?!
That behemoth is now ours!
Damn you, Kamina,
you set us up!
Yeah, that I did!
I put our luck and our
mettle to the test!
I can't do it.
You guys keep the Gunmen pinned down!
I'll see what I can do about Simon!
Yeah!
Open the hatch, Simon!
Let's see you grit those teeth!
Bro?
Have you snapped out of it?
If you ever start to doubt yourself,
I'll always come to belt you one.
So don't worry,
I'm here at your side.
Believe in yourself.
Believe in the Simon
that I have faith in.
I can never be like you, Bro...
You got it!
Bro?
Kamina?!
I won't hand over
my Dai-Gunzan so easily!
Thymilph?!
Damn, I didn't--
That day, we lost something that
could never be replaced.
Gurren Lagann
I can't do it...
I can never be like you, Bro...
They seek out the light,
even though only death awaits them.
It is enough
to make me despair...
...at the nature of these
creatures called humans.
The Spiral King's daughter...
...Nia.
Hail fellow well met!
Why are you
the same as I am?
A meeting amidst despair.
You have no tail,
nor fangs or scales.
Your skin is soft, as well.
Well, that's only natural.
I'm a human being.
"Human being"?
Right. A human being.
A human. A person.
And what, exactly,
is a human?
How do you do?
My name is Nia.
And what is your name?
Enemy pursuit.
There's no escape, human scum.
I know that voice...
Wha--? That idiot, is she trying
to get herself killed?
Stop this, Adiane!
First Princess Nia, daughter of
Spiral King Lordgenome, orders you!
Leave us,
Adiane, the Elegant!
Are you aware of
who I am?
Termination orders.
You piss me off, you flake!
If you wanna go, take your
own sorry ass there!
Do you hate me, as well?
Hate you? I couldn't
care less about you.
I was told to kill you, so that's
what I'm going to do!
Then if my father told you to die,
would you do that, as well?!
You are wrong!
These people have done
nothing wrong!
Don't you think that there is
something wrong with that?
NO, I DON'T!
Your father says he has
grown tired of you.
Like a doll?
I'm told that you asked him,
"Why was I born?"
That was a bad move. His Majesty
detests human self-awareness.
The valley of discarded princesses.
Who can blame him? Why would a puppet,
a plaything, need self-awareness?
I am just like that doll...
That's right. And once he grows tired
of them, they're discarded.
Just like you were.
Simon will protect me.
Simon.
You aren't your Bro, Simon.
I think you should just be yourself.
Listen, Simon. Never forget this.
Believe in yourself.
Not in the Simon
that I have faith in.
Not in the Kamina
that you believe in, either.
- Believe in the Simon--
- ...who believes in you!
He won't lose to the likes of you.
I believe in Simon, too!
Nia! I'm here to rescue you!
Come on!
Simon!
Sorry I took so long.
I understand now!
So do I.
Thank you, Simon!
My Bro is dead.
He's gone.
But he's on my back!
In my heart!
Believe in yourself!
He lives on as part of me!
If you're gonna dig,
dig to breach the heavens.
Even if it's my own grave
I'm digging, I keep going!
Once I've dug my way through,
that means I've won!
What? What are you
talking about?
Who the hell do
you think I am?
I'm Simon.
I'm not my Bro, Kamina.
I'm ME!
Simon the Digger!
Finishing Move!
That move, it was--
GIGA DRILL BREAK!
The invincible drill.
Put Nia down!
General Adiane!
No you don't!
The power of the Spiral.
Reawakened humans...
Damn you, Gurren Lagann!
Damn! DAMN!
...go on the offensive.
The time has finally come
to demonstrate my power.
Spiral King Lordgenome,
watch closely!
All units, advance!
A rout.
It worked!
How can this be?! How can
I be losing to a mere human cub?!
What are humans?
Do you really wish
to know the answer?
Do you, Viral?
Yes!
I can never be you, but I'm going off
to do what only I can do.
The things that only
Simon the Digger can do.
Towards the final battle...
What's the matter?
Has your Spiral run dry?
Simon!
Simon, if our faith in you
is what gives you your strength,
...then I'll believe in you
with all my heart!
So, please! Win!
The Spiral King, Lordgenome
I haven't had this much fun
in a long time, boy.
Now, back into the dirt
with you!
A Core Drill?!
And that something
is my drill!
I see... Your Spiral Power
outstripped my own.
Lordgenome...
I will leave you with
this warning.
When the land comes to overflow
with a million apes,
...the moon shall become Hell's messenger
and destroy the world of the Spiral.
What do you mean?!
Father!
Farewell, Father.
I will head towards tomorrow.
The royal capital Teppelin...
...falls.
Humanity...
...has broken through the heavens.
And beyond it lies...
Kimi ni au mae no jibun wo wasureta mitai ni
Like how I've forgotten what I was like before I met you
Kimi ga ita koro no kioku wo wasurerareta nara
If I can forget my memories of when you were around
Donna ni ii darou
How many will be all right?
Kazoekirenai hoshikuzu no naka
Inside of countless specks of stardust
Dokoka de sotto mimamotte kureteru hikari wo
The lights that are secretly, somewhere, watching over us
Bokura ha ima mo koko de sagashiteru
We are even now searching for them here
Shiawase ha itsudatte ushinatte hajimete
Happiness is a modest thing, wherein we always realize
Shiawase to kidzuku sasayaka na koto
For the first time that it was happiness once we part with it
Shiawase ha itsudatte nakushite hajimete
Happiness is a precious thing, wherein we always realize
Shiawase to kidzuku taisetsu na koto
For the first time that it was happiness once we lose it
Ima datte kitto mada ma ni au hazu dakara
I'm sure we can still make it even now, so
Negai ha tatta hitotsu
I have only one wish
Dokomademo oikakeru yo
I'll chase after you through thick and thin
Next Time
Seven years have passed.
People are indulging themselves
in these days of peace,
...not knowing that their empty stomachs
are being filled with the wine of ruin.
You Don't Know Anything
Next time on Gurren Lagann,
"You Don't Know Anything".